Welcome to the next module in our Java Fundamentals Course
on the Java language.
In this module, we're going to look at class initializers
and constructors, my name is Jim Wilson.
In this module, we're going to first look at
the idea of establishing the initial state of our objects.
We'll look at how we can set the value of class fields
as part of the class declarations.
We touched on constructors in the last module,
we'll look a lot more at how we work with constructors
and the idea of having multiple constructors.
We'll then look at how we can chain multiple constructors
together and even use constructor visibility
to control how and where our class instances are created.
We'll talk about a way to share code across constructors
called initialization blocks.
And with all these different ways to construct
and initialize our objects, we'll talk about how the order
of those things occur.