Remember that we talked about the fact that classes
are made up of both state and executable code.
It's reasonable to expect that when
an object is first created, that it's going to be in some useful state.
Java will provide a default state
when the object is first created, but that might sometimes not be enough.
You may need to actually set these values yourself
or even execute some code.
Java gives the ability to set the initial state
of an object and it provides three separate mechanisms
for doing so.
One is what they call Field initializers, where we assign
a specific value to a field.
Another is called Constructors where we can potentially
pass in parameters and run code to set the state.
Another one is called Initialization blocks
that allows us to run code that can be shared potentially
across constructors.