You recall that when we talked about variable declarations,
we said that variables always have to have
an explicit value assigned to them.
That's not true for fields.
Fields will get a default value automatically
as part of the object construction.
That default value will always be what I call
the field's "zero" value, and what I mean by that,
is that it's kind of whatever the empty state
of that field is based on its data type.
If we take a look here, for example,
all of the integer fields, byte, short, int and long,
the value is actually zero.
Same with the floating point, the value is zero.
For the char type, zero value, it's basically gamma zero,
it's kind of the null character.
For Boolean, it defaults to false and for reference type,
they default to null.
We have all these default values that they get
and these are all reasonable defaults,
but as your objects get more sophisticated,
those default values may not be the right thing
for your object's initial state.
The good news is we don't have to accept
those default values.
Java provides what they call field initializers,
and a field initializer allows you to specify
the field's initial value as part of its declaration.
Imagine we have this class, we call the class Earth,
and it has a field called "circumference in miles".
We want to go and set that to our initial value,
initial value of zero doesn't make sense,
we know that Earth actually has a circumference.
What we can do is just do a simple assignment
to set its initial value.
We can just simply say:
"Circumference in miles equals 24,901."
By creating an instance of the Earth class, that field
will have the value 24,901.
Now, simple assignments are a good start,
but that may not be enough.
You can also use an actual equation.
If we had circumference in kilometers, we could
calculate that out by hand or we can simply say that
well, I know that if I take 24,901 and multiply it by
one point six, that will give me the circumference
in kilometers as we actually have that equation.
Remember though that the equation has to be
a valid equation.
Right now, this wouldn't compile because 24,901 is an
intertype, when I multiply it by one point six,
which is a double, that result will be a double
that it can't assign directly into the long,
circumference in kilometers.
So we just go and put a cast in place and that now
becomes a legal assignment.
If we look here, we see that we're duplicating that
24,901 in two places, it would be nice to only use it once.
Well, we can actually reference other fields in our
field initializers, so we can take that 24,901
and replace it with the field circumference in miles
so that the equation will then use the value
of circumference in miles when it does the calculation.
Things are getting better and better
as we go along here.
One thing that's interesting to note, if we calculate out
24,901 times one point six, the value that
that calculates to is 39,841.6.
Now, when we cast that to a long,
the cast is just going to truncate it,
so the value of circumference in kilometers
will end up being 39,841 and less than
ideally accurate, the better answer for that would be
39,842.
The good news is we can make any method calls
that we need to in here, so, one of the things we can do,
there is a built-in method called "Math dot round".
If we call Math dot round, it will take the result
of that equation, 39,841.6 and actually round it,
so that we then would get 39,842
into our circumference in kilometer.
You notice that these field initializers are really powerful
because you can do as much as you need to,
anything from a simple assignment,
to equations, all the way up through method calls.