We talked about constructors briefly in the last module
and from that we know that a constructor is
executable code that is used during the creation
of an object to set up that initial state.
Remember that we worked with our flight class
in our last module, we saw that the flight class
had a constructor in it.
One thing that's interesting to note is that a constructor
is not a method, it is an executable code,
but it's not a method.
You'll notice that constructors don't have return type.
It's just a code that we want to run during the construction
of our object and every class has at least one constructor.
It's interesting to note, if we look at our flight class,
what's going on inside of our constructor
isn't really necessary.
We see setting "passengers equal to zero",
that's not necessary because we know that ints
are automatically set to zero when your field
is in a class and "seats equals 150", we could've actually
put that up in the declaration of seats.
We didn't really need to have an explicit constructor here.
What happens in a case where we don't really need
to have an explicit constructor?
Let's take a look here at how to deal with that.
Let's use another class, we're going to call that
passenger class and our passenger class
is going to have three fields.
These are all related to "check in bags", that we got
on the flight, so we have the "checks bags" field,
which is how many bags the passengers checked.
"Free bags" indicates how many bags they are allowed
to have for free.
The "per bag fee" is what is the cost of each bag beyond
the number of free bags.
Let's assume that we've provided accessors and mutators
for checked bags and free bags so that we can
interact with that data.
As we can see, this class does not have
a constructor, yet, if I write code, to go and create
a new passenger and assign it to "Bob", that code will run.
Well, how is that possible if we said
that every class has to have
at least one constructor?
It turns out that if you don't have an explicit constructor,
Java actually provides one, you wouldn't see it
in your source code, but when the class is built,
Java generates a constructor that doesn't do anything.
Therefore, it makes it possible to create an instance
of your class without explicitly writing a constructor.
There is nothing special about that class,
it will behave normally so you can interact
with all of its methods and so forth.
But, classes can actually have multiple constructors.
The parameter list has to differ for each constructor,
that's an idea we call the signature.
We'll talk more about how signatures work later
in the course when we talk about methods in more detail.
The key thing is that, just the numbering types
of parameters have to differ across various constructors.
Let's say that we want to be able to create passengers
and as part of the creation, indicate how many free bags
they're allowed to have.
All that constructor would do is accept the parameters
that number free bags then assign that to the field.
What that allows us to do is write code like this
where our passenger Jane equals new passenger two,
that calls our constructor that accepts the integer
and sets the number of free bags for Jane to do.
Of course, we can then set the number
of checked bags for her from there.
The thing is that once we introduce this new constructor
that accepts the integer free bags, the line above there
where we create Bob as a passenger
would no longer compile.
What happens is that, once you write any constructors,
you're now responsible for all the constructors.
That constructor that was created by Java
is no longer there, the point is that Java doesn't assume
that your class needs a constructor with no arguments.
Once you write any constructors, you're now responsible
for all the constructors, so if we still want to allow
users of our class to create instances that don't provide
any arguments, we're responsible to go ahead and write
a constructor that doesn't take any arguments.
Doesn't have to do anything, but just by putting it there,
we're saying that that code that creates an instance
without providing the parameters is now valid again.