Looking at our passenger class, what I want to focus you on,
is just the constructors for a second, so we'll assume
we have all the fields and methods we saw
on the earlier slides.
Remember that we have a constructor that takes no arguments,
we also have our constructor that accepts an integer
which is the number of free bags that we set
and of course, that allows us to go out here
and do something like create a reference called Jane
to a new passenger and when we create,
we say that Jane is allowed to have two free bags.
The we can call the method "check bags",
to set how many bags she's checked.
If we find this as a scenario that comes up a lot,
where we create a passenger who has a number of free bags
and a number of checked bags, it might make sense
to introduce another constructor that allows us to combine
those operations, so we can go and create a passenger
and in one call, say that they can have two free bags
and they've checked three bags.
Writing a constructor like that is really straightforward,
now we just introduce another public passenger
with two integer arguments, one for free bags,
one for checked bags.
While we can write this, again we just make the assignments,
we assign free bags into the field "free bags",
we assign checked bags into the field "checked bags".
That would work, the thing is that now we're getting
some duplicate logic, that assignment of free bags
is now happening in two separate constructors.
In this case, that logic is really simple,
but if times goes on and the logic around the management
of free bags gets more sophisticated, we would actually
have to change it in every place that we have currently
assigned free bags.
It would be nice to be able to chain these constructors
together, and in turns out we can do that.
One constructor is allowed to call another constructor.
All we do, is use this keyword followed
by the parameter list.
If we look at the constructor that takes free bags
and checked bags, that line where we assign free bags,
we can replace that with this
and then our free bags parameter.
What that will do is then call into the constructors that
accepts the single integer free bags
and run that constructor.
The one qualifier is, the call to the other constructor
has to be the first line in our constructor.
Now, when we create this passenger Jane,
it calls into the constructor that takes two arguments
as part of that calls up to the constructor that takes
one argument which sets to free bags,
and when that returns, we assign checked bags
into our checked bags field.
With multiple constructors, we may want to start thinking
about the visibility of our constructors.
Because, just like any other members, with constructors
we can use access modifiers to control the visibility
of those constructors.
What that allows us to do is limit what code
can perform specific creations, let's see that
on an example here.
Let's say that we introduce a constructor that allows us
to identify the "per bag" fee for passengers.
Of course, all that does is assign whatever
that parameter is into our per bag fee field.
Thinking about it is that if the logic around
setting back fees is kind of meant to be part of our class,
we probably don't want a program to easily go
and change that, we don't' want to cheap Joe to come along
and just create himself as a passenger where he pays
a penny a bag.
We probably don't want that broadly accessible,
what we do here is that for our constructor
that accepts the baggage fee, instead of being public,
go and make that guy private.
By making it private, it can't be called from the outside,
it can only be called from within our class.
Maybe, what we want to do here is say that
based on the number of free bags a passenger is allowed
to have, we will set the baggage fee.
The idea being that a passenger is assigned a certain number
of free bags based on the level of customer they are,
so a customer who is actually allowed
more free bags may also as part of that get a lower
"per bag rate" for the ones that they have to pay for.
If we look at our constructor here that accepts free bags,
we make a little room in here, maybe what we want to do
is make a call down to the other constructor
based on the baggage fees and pass in a different value
based on the number of free bags the customer has.
We can do here, is call out to that and say if free bags
is greater than one, they pay 25 $ per a bag
depending on the free bags, otherwise they pay 50 $.
The idea being that a customer who gets more free bags
also gets a discount rate on bags they pay for.
What that allows us to do now is have our baggage fee rate
tied to the number of free bags a passenger gets.
If we have one call here, where we create a passenger Fred
who gets two free bags, that goes directly
to the constructor that accepts the free bags parameter,
as part of that, it's chained down to the constructor
that sets the baggage fee.
We have another passenger created who accepts
the two parameters, the free bags and the checked bags.
We'll call in the first, that constructor, that constructor
will chain up to our constructor that accepts
the number of free bags which then in turn
chains down to the constructor that sets the baggage fee.