Let's take a look now how we can use
field initializers and constructors to improve
our CalcEngine app.
Before we start changing anything in our class,
let's imagine what it's like for someone who is using
our math equation class for the first time.
Whenever you start working with a new class
or class library, something you'll often do is
kind of write the simplest thing you can
and see what happens.
Let's imagine what that would be like with our class.
I will declare a variable called Test Equation
of type math equation.
We'll go ahead and new up math equation and of course,
what's the simplest thing we can do with our math equation?
We can go to our test equation and call execute.
Then what you would do from there
is just print out the result.
With that, we see the simplest thing you can do here.
Let's comment out all other code for just one second,
we're going to take this area of code and comment that out.
Let's go and run this now and see what the experience
will be like for someone who had just come
to explore our class.
You see what happens here, it's that they see a message
that says "Invalid opCode", right away they've had
this negative experience because what's happening is that
we're allowing them to create our class in a way where
our class has an invalid initial state.
Basically what's happening is that if I go
into the math equation class, the value of opCode
is at the null character, the all zeroes character.
If we go down here, to our execute method, since it's not
one of the valid opCodes, we right away print
an error message.
I think one of the best ways to deal with this
is actually allow the object to be initially created
in a valid state.
There is a couple of ways we can do this.
One way to do that is just set the opCode
to something that's valid, like an "a", that way
when they run it, what we'll do is we'll add
two zeroes together, and it will print out zero,
it won't do something useful, but it won't give them
a negative experience.
Now, when we run that code, it just prints out zero.
That's a reasonable experience for someone
who is exploring our class.
We want to make sure that our classes are being created
in some kind of reasonable state.
Let's head back here on the Main, let's go
and comment out that test code and let's bring back
our original code, uncomment that stuff.
Now, remember what happens here is that
the way we do it, we create this array for math equations
and then we go through them, we call to create
a math equation in each one of the array instances.
Remember that we've got this create method down here.
But the thing that's kind of ugly about this
is that the application has had to handle all the details
of setting each value, setting the opCode,
we don't want to have to do that.
If that's something that goes on frequently,
that's a perfect chance for a constructor.
Let's go back to our class here.
Let's take a look at some constructors that we could write.
Now, one very reasonable constructor, I think,
is to have one that accepts just an opCode,
it would make a lot of sense if I'm going to create
an equation and I know what kind of operation
I'm going to perform on it, but I don't know the values yet.
Let's go and create that constructor.
Make a public math equation, I'm going to give it a
single argument, a "char" opCode, then all we're going to do
inside of here is assign that parameter to our field opCode.
Now we support the ability to create into this math equation
with a specific opCode.
The thing is that it doesn't solve our current problem,
because we know that we want to create instances
that have the opCode and both values.
Let's go and create another constructor.
In this constructor, we'll accept the opCode
as well as left and right values.
Once we have that all set up, now,
inside of here, let's first look at storing the left
and right values.
We're just going to assign each of those
to the appropriate field.
So, we have that in place, we could do the same thing
with opCode, but since we already have
the constructor that accepts opCode, that's a perfect time
to go and chain up to that constructor.
We'll say this, and pass in the opCode we've received.
That way, we just call up to the other constructor
that already knows how to do that.
Before we go any further, let's just go and run our program
and make sure everything is OK.
If you look at what's happened here,
we've broken the existing code, you see,
we're back here in Main and right there we actually
tried to create just math equation,
we're not able to anymore because remember that we were
getting a default constructor before when we didn't provide
any constructors.
Once we provided a constructor, we're now responsible
to provide all the constructors.
What we want to do is head back to our math equation class
and go and create that constructor
that doesn't take any arguments.
With that, we should be able to run our code now.
Let's go and run it.
Now the code works again, we've now kept our old code
working and that's something we want to do.
Now let's look at how we can improve the code.
Now that we actually have a constructor
that accepts the opCode and both values,
if we go back to our Main up here, we shouldn't need
this create method anymore, we should be able to do
all that with constructors.
I head up here, each of these places where I called "create"
I can instead call the constructor, I can simply new up
math equation and when I new it up, I make sure
the parameter order matches, so in our constructor
we have the opCode first, then the values.
We'll cut that away, put that in the beginning.
Now, we're using the constructor to create that zero
instance of the array.
Going to do the same thing for the other three elements.
Now we're using the constructor to create
all the array elements so we can actually scroll down here
and just get rid of this "create method".
With that, it's good and running.
We get the same results we have been getting, which is good,
but the key thing is that we're using the constructor
to set up the object and get the object
to the appropriate state, so that we take that burden
off of the program that's using the object
and keep those details and housekeeping inside the object itself.