Constructors are not the only way to run code
as part of the initialization of our classes.
We have another mechanism called "Initialization Blocks".
What they allow us to do is create code
that is shared across all our constructors.
What they do is they run the code as if that code
were placed at the very beginning of each constructor.
Let's revisit our flight class for a second.
Remember that our flight class has some fields in it,
we know that we have that "passenger fields".
Going to have a look at another field here,
called "flight number" we'll talk about the second
that I've added and of course we have our "seats" field.
I'm going to choose another new field here
called "flight class", and the idea is that "flight number"
and "flight class" are two different ways
to identify a flight, so a flight is either created with
an individual number or it's created with an individual
character as a flight class that I group it somehow.
Remember that constructor that we wrote earlier.
It took no arguments and it set seats to 150
and our passengers were set to zero.
We've learned a lot since we've originally wrote
this constructor.
We know that passengers will automatically be set to zero
so we don't need to have that code here.
We also know that we can initialize that we added
the "seats field" right up there in the declaration.
Let's go and move that up there and we no longer
need it inside of our constructor.
Now, let's add two more constructors.
One that accepts our flight number.
We'll go ahead and initialize that.
Another one accepts our flight class and that initializes
to "flight class" field.
As we're enhancing our class, let's go one step further,
in addition to having these different ways
to identify our flights, let's keep track of the seats
a little more closely.
Right now, all we have is the ability to have
the number of seats, earlier we just kept count of how many
passengers we had.
Let's go and advance this a little bit and say,
let's keep track if each individual seat is available.
We've got this new array here, "is seat available"
that's an array of Boolean.
If we just declare this array of Boolean, all the values
are going to "false".
We, of course don't want to have all the seats available
set to "false", that would imply
that they were unavailable, we want them to be available
or set to "true".
Now, based on what we know so far, a way we would do that
is we'd go to our no-argument constructor here,
we would go ahead and allocate up the array
for "is seat available", what we would do is loop through
each one and then set each one to true.
That's a reasonable thing to do.
What it would do, of course is that each
of the other constructors, we would call up to that
constructor, so our constructor based on flight number
and our constructor based on flight class would both
call up to the no-argument constructor.
That's a reasonable thing to do, but in cases like this
where we have code that we want to share across
all the constructors, that's a perfect place to use
initialization blocks.
All we have to do is take that code that we want to share
and place it within brackets outside
of any method or constructor.
Let's take our no-argument constructor and take all the code
out of it and we'll move it down,
so now it has no actual code inside of it.
We'll take that code we want to run
and wrap that in brackets.
Notice there is no constructor name here,
there is no method name,
it's just the brackets and the code.
That turns that code into an initialization block.
It will automatically be executed at the beginning
of each one of our constructors.
Our flight number-based constructor no longer
needs to chain up to another constructor
as well as our flight class constructor.
No matter how someone creates this class now,
the code to set up "is seat available"
will always run because it's in that initialization block.
It's a great way to share that code across constructors,
it's really useful in something we're going to talk
about later called "anonymous classes".
Another thing just to note, is that you can put multiple
initialization blocks in a class, they are executed
in the order they are encountered from the top.
I would be really careful about that
because that's really easy to get out of hand,
it's just something to be aware of.