Throughout this module, we talked about a number
of different ways we can set our field values
as part of the creation of our objects.
We have to understand is the order that those values
get set are the order that these operations occur,
as you would expect, object creation occurs in a predictable
pattern, or a predictable path.
Let's imagine we have this class here, we'll call our
"Over Initialize Class", we'll put a field in here,
called "the field".
Let's go and get it together.
One of the first ways we learned about how we can
initialize a field is through field initializer.
That is actually the first step in the creation
of an object, if we take our field here called "the field",
set it equal to one, by then in a program,
create an instance of this class and then print out the
value of the field, I'll print out the value one.
The next phase is to run the initialization blocks.
If we take the same class and now we add in
initialization block that sets the value of the field
to two, even though we still have a field
initializer that sets it to one,
when we run the code that prints this out,
it's now going to print out two.
Because the initialization block ran after the field
initializers ran.
That would overwrite that value.
The final phase is construction.
Again, we take our same class
and now we add a constructor that sets the field to three,
when we run the code to print this out,
it will now print out the value three.
Now, looking at this, you obviously wouldn't want to do
what we do here, we actually set a field to something
in a field initializer, then change it
in an initialization block, then change it in a constructor.
You're not going to do that, but as your classes
get more sophisticated, you'll find that your fields
start to depend on the values of one another.
It's important to understand this order
as you use the fields and set up the fields
inside your class.
The most common mistake I see people make
is that they'll do work in an initialization block
that gets invalidated by works that occurs later in a constructor.
So, just keep this order in mind
as you're setting up your classes.