Some of the key things we want to remember from this module.
Keep in mind that we want to make sure
that our objects are always created initially
in some useful state, we don't want to allow the user
to open an object and have it in an erroneous state.
They might not be able to do something meaningful with it,
but it should at least not be error-based
when they first create it.
In terms of how we can initialize our objects,
we saw there is a number of ways, the simplest way
is field initializers that allow us to just associate
a value with a field as part of its declaration.
As we associate code with our object creation,
then we have constructors, and every class
has at least one constructor.
If we don't provide a constructor, Java will provide one
that has no arguments on it.
We can provide multiple constructors, and remember that
once we provide one constructor, we're now responsible
to provide all of them.
If we provide a constructor that has arguments,
if we still want to allow people to create
an instance of our object using constructor
with no arguments, we then have to provide
that constructor as well.
We can chain our constructors together which allows us
to unify coding constructors so that we can pass
parameters from one constructor back to another
constructor to use that code.
Remember that when we do chain constructors together,
the call from one constructor to another has to be the
first line of that constructor.
To have code which gets executed no matter
which constructor is called, we have initialization blocks.
Remember that syntax in that is kind of weird,
it's just a set of brackets with code inside of it,
not part of any constructor or method.
Given all these different ways to initialize our objects
and get them constructed up, we want to make sure
we always keep the order in mind.
Remember that field initializers are first,
then initialization blocks
and then finally, our constructors.