Hi everyone. My name is Jim Wilson. Welcome to my course, Java Fundamentals: The Java Language.
I'm president of JW Hedgehog, Incorporated and I've had the good fortune to have been a professional software
developer now for more than 30 years.
Did you know that Java is the most sought after programming language skill among software developers?
Java is supported on everything from smartphones to servers to many of the special purpose devices that make up
the inner node of things.
In addition to being important to software developers, a recent survey listed Java as one of the five most
important skills for data scientists, those folks who work their way through all of that big data.
In this course we're going to teach you everything you need to know to get started working in the Java
programming language.
So the major topics we cover include setting up your Java development environment, language constructs &amp;
control flow, classes, class inheritance, &amp; interfaces, exceptions &amp; error handling, creating &amp; using Java packages.
By the end of this course you'll be ready to begin working in any of the many environments that rely on
the Java programming language. This is a beginning course
and therefore makes no assumptions on prior programming experience. I hope you'll join me as we learn
Java programming with the course, Java Fundamentals: The Java Language, at Pluralsight.