Welcome to the next module of our
Java Fundamentals course on the Java language.
In this module, we look at how we represent complex types using classes.
My name is Jim Wilson.
In this module we start digging into the
object-oriented aspects of Java.
So we'll first look at classes, how we create them
and how we use them.
We'll then look at the concept of classes
being reference types and how that makes them
behave differently than primitive types.
We'll look at the idea of encapsulation, other words,
how do we keep the details of our classes inside of our
classes and not the concern of those using the classes.
We'll look at the basic behavior and creation of methods in Java.
And then we'll look at how we control interaction
with the data in our classes using field accessors and mutators.