Java includes some special reference variables
that are important for us to understand.
Now one of these is the this reference.
And the this reference allows you to refer
to the current object.
So it's useful for any time you want to be very explicit
and indicate that you're referring to the current object.
And it's also used forward cases where an object may need
to pass references to itself to other methods.
We'll see this used a lot throughout the course
but let's look at a simple example.
Remember that we have our Flight class
and we had that method we just wrote called hasRoom.
Now the hasRoom method uses data from the current instance
and it also uses data from an instance passed in f2.
So we have our f2.passengers which refers to the passengers
of the instance passed in.
And then our passengers refers
to the current instances passengers
And this is completely valid the way we have this written.
But if we wanted to make it more explicit,
that we were referring to the current instance passengers
what we could do is we could actually put this in front of
the passengers on the left saying that
we're referring to this one inside of the current instance.
So it allows us to get rid of that ambiguity
and make our code more clear.
There are other cases that maybe we had a local variable
or something that maybe had a name collision
with a member field.
We could also use this to disambiguate that.
We'll see an example of that shortly, later in this module.
Another special reference is the null reference,
and this is a literal.
And null refers to an uncreated object and you can assign it
to any reference variable and you want to really just use it
to say that "Hey, this reference variable isn't pointing
"to anything yet."
So we take a look at some code here.
Remember that we wrote that code earlier
where we declared our two flights: lax1, lax2.
And then we're going to have our other Flight lax3
that if there was room we would assign
a new Flight instance to with combined passengers
of lax1 and lax2.
Well this code as it's written kind of creates a problem.
Notice that our Flight lax3, well, if there wasn't room
to combine them lax3 could end up
potentially set to nothing.
All right, we learned earlier that local variables
cannot be uninitialized so we need to initialize lax3
to something and we want to initialize it to no object.
So that's where null comes in.
So we can do here is that simply say
Flight lax3 equals null.
So now it's initialized to .2 no object at all.
So let's say that later on our program we do some work
and we want to know if lax3 was actually
assigned a flight or not.
Well we can actually compare lax3 to null.
So we're saying well if lax3 is not equal null.
In other words is lax3 no longer pointing to nothing.
Does it point to something?
Well and if it does, we know the flights were combined
so we could print that value out.