Let's revisit our CalcEngine demo and update it
to use classes and methods.
Here we are in our CalcEngine program as we left it
at the end of the last module.
Remember what we had done was create four pile of arrays.
One with the leftVals, one with the rightVals,
one with the opCodes, for the operation
we're going to perform, then an array to hold the results.
And the way we create a commonality across this arrays
was that we said that well the first member of each array
corresponds to the first member in every other array.
Same for the second, third, and fourth members.
A much better way to represent this idea of related values
is to use classes.
So let's go ahead and add a class to our project here.
Now I'm going to go ahead and use the IDEs ability
to create class for us.
All it's going to do is create a class file
and put the class definition side of it.
All the major ID support this concept
and they all pretty much do it almost the same way.
All I'm going to do here is go to my package name:
com_Pluralsight_calcengine, right click on it, say New,
take Java Class and give it a name of the class.
So let's call it class MathEquation.
Go ahead and just tell it to go and create it.
What that does is create a source file
named MathEquation.java and put a public class
decoration inside of it.
Now what I want to do inside of here is create fields
for each of the values that I need to keep track of.
So if I go back to main for just a second here,
basically, I want to create fields for leftVals, rightVals,
opCodes, and results.
Let's go back inside of here.
All I need to do is make the space to do that.
So first I'll do leftVal.
So I just made a public double, I called it leftVal,
very similar to what it was called in the old program.
Do the same thing for our rightVal, our opCode,
and our result.
So now I have the ability to store all those values together
inside this one class.
Let's head back to the main program.
Now if we look at the main program, inside of here
this is great because of switch statement.
This is kind of broken in terms of the fact that
the program has to know a whole lot about how
these operations work.
The reality is programs wants to have the work done.
So this switch statement can really be moved out of here
and let's move it in to our class and so we can wrap it up
inside of a simple method.
So I want to go ahead and cut that away.
Go back to my equation and let's add a public method on here
called execute.
And as I mark the method void
saying it doesn't return any values.
Matter of fact it's not going to take any parameters either
so it's going to go ahead
and put the code block inside of here.
What I'll do now is I'll paste that switch statement
inside of this execute method.
Now I want to do now is just update it
to work on its own value.
So the idea is on for the first one here for a,
just going to get rid of the subscripts
because I want to use opCode as declares out of class.
Same thing for result, I'm just going to make that result.
Same thing for leftVals and rightVals.
So I got my result equals leftVal plus rightVal,
that's using all the members.
Here up in the opCode I need to take that S off
so it matches.
So now the opCode matches up as well.
So I'm now using the case of an all of my member variables.
opCode for the switch, then results, leftVal, and rightVal.
I'm going to do the same thing for all the different cases
under the default down here.
So now my execute method knows how to perform
all the operations using the member fields.
Now next thing I need to do is go ahead and start creating
instances in my MathEquation.
So I'm going to back here to the Main program.
And we're going to do is get rid
of all these arrays up here.
I'm just going to comment those out
and what we'll do is instead is create an array
of our MathEquation class.
So I'm just going to declare MathEquation,
put the array indicator on there,
we'll go ahead and call this equations
and set it equal to a new array of MathEquation.
Now we've created the array of MathEquation.
Now that creates the array itself but I still need to create
the individual MathEquation instances for each array member.
So what I basically need to do is say something
like equations subzero equals new MathEquation
and then go through and set each of the fields:
leftVals, rightVals, and opCodes.
Now since we're going to have to do that four times
here's another great chance to use a method.
You can use a method to kind of encapsulate all that work
of creating a new instance and setting all the values.
So we'll go ahead and create that here
inside of my Main class.
So I'm going to create a new method here,
I'm just going to go ahead and call the method create,
so I'll mark it as public.
Let's use a modifier called static
that we haven't talked about yet.
We'll talk about that one a little bit later in the course.
Let's just go ahead and put it in for now.
What our create method is going to do is return back
a new instance of MathEquation.
So if return type is MathEquation
again we're going to call it create,
and what it will do is we accept a parameter for each
of the fields we want to set,
leftVals, rightVals, and opCodes.
We have all the parameters there, I'm just going to put
the brackets in place.
So now we're going to do inside of here
is create a new instance of the MathEquation
so we declare MathEquation we'll call equation
and then new up the MathEquation.
So that gives us our instance of the MathEquation
and what we want to do, we just go scroll it down here
so we can see a little better.
What we want to do is go through and set all the fields
that correspond to the parameters.
Say for leftVal I'm going to say equation.leftVal
equals leftVal.
So that takes whatever that leftVal parameter is
and sets the leftVal field on equation.
We do the same thing for rightVal and opCode.
With all the values set the only thing left to do
is return back our equation.
So with that all set what we can do is up here
in the main part where we create each one
rather than explicitly create them, we can instead
call that create method.
So what I'll do here is just call create and then pass in
the values I want to use.
So for leftVal and the first value is a 100.0
then I use 50.0 and then the opCode d.
Now do the same thing for the other three members.
So now we have our MathEquation array created
and then we also have the individual MathEquation instances
created in to each one of the arrays.
So I'm going to go ahead and get rid of this for statement
here, we don't need that one anymore.
What I'll do here is that where we have this foreach
where we're going to the results before, we can do now
is go to that MathEquation array.
So I'll go ahead and declare as MathEquation.
I'll call the variable equation and what it will
loop through is equations.
So now what I can do inside of here is for each one
I can simply say equation.execute, what that will do then
is when I call equation.execute
for each of these sets of values will go into MathEquation
call execute, check the opCode,
perform the appropriate operation, store that in results.
So when I get back here what I can then print out
is simply equation.result.
So now I have a much more encapsulated application here.
In a sense that I have the idea of what I want to perform
modeled into my class MathEquation.
All right so it has the fields for each of the things I need
to perform the operations.
The execute method does the actual work.
If we go back to the application,
the application doesn't care about any
of those kinds of details.
It simply creates each MathEquation instance,
loops through them, tells each one to execute
and then displays the result.
So if we go ahead and run this,
we get our appropriate results out.
Is at 100 divided by 50 is two.
25 plus 92 is 117.
225 minus 17 is 208.
And 11 times three is 33.