Most of the time we do not want to allow access
to the fields within our classes from outside of that class.
We want to hide those kind of details because the fields
are a very fundamental part, are very kind of
low level part of the way a class solves a problem.
And they're very likely to change over time.
So we don't want to have this kind of details exposed
outside of the class.
Now that doesn't mean that we don't want to allow
interaction with the information side of those fields
from outside the class.
So what we do is we generally use methods to control
access to our fields.
As you expect this is an issue that we have to address
very frequently.
So a common pattern called the accessor/mutator pattern
has a reason to deal with that.
Now if you're not familiar with the term pattern
all that means is that's just kind of a common way
we solve the problem.
Now let's take a look at our Flight class
we've been working with.
We have a couple of fields inside of here:
passengers and seats.
Let's say that we decide that we'd like to allow
interaction with the seats values.
Now, again, we don't want to give them direct access
to seats, we don't want to make that public.
So what we'll do is we'll use methods to address that.
So what we do is we use what's called an accessor
to get to the field value.
It's often just called a getter.
And what we do is we create a method normally
that has the word get followed by the field name.
So the accessor for our seats would simply be getSeats.
Notice that the return type is the same as the field itself
and also notice that the method is following CamelCase.
A lowercase g for the first word and an uppercase S
for Seats the second word.
Even though the field started with a lowercase s
that doesn't matter, we're going to use
consistent CamelCasing as we name things.
And all the accessor does is just return seats.
So easy for the consumer of the class to get to the value
but we've got control if we ever change
the way we manage seats, that will not affect
anyone using this class.
To allow the value of seats to be modified, we use
what's called a mutator, also known as a setter.
As you might have guessed the way we name that method
is simply set and the field name.
So a mutator for our seats field
this one has public void setSeats.
Notice that the return type is void because the setter
doesn't return anything back.
It has a parameter to receive the incoming value.
So now inside of setSeats, what we want to do is set
our field seats to have the value of that parameter.
Now we have an interesting challenge here.
Notice that we're saying seats equal seats.
Well because on the right-hand side we want the one
as parameter, on the left-hand side we want the one
that is the field.
This is a great time to use this.
If we're putting this in front of the seats on the left
that says that I want the field seats to receive the value
of the parameter seats.
If we go ahead and set up some code
we create an instance of our Flight.
I want to set the number of seats, I simply call
our slcToNyc reference, again setSeats,
pass in 150 that would set the value of seats be 150.
To get the value back, I simply call getSeats
against slcToNyc and returns back the value we set, 150.