In this demo we'll add accessors and mutators to our CalcEngine app.
And we'll look at how to deal with situations
where we may want to provide the ability to see a value
but not modify a value.
So here we are back in our CalcEngine app
and I'm here in the Mathequation class.
We have our four fields at the top,
they're all currently public.
Now the first thing we want to do is go ahead
and make these guys all private.
So if the value's all private now we can go ahead
and add our accessors and our mutators.
This can really be straightforward.
Let's go ahead, let's first do it for leftVal,
so for leftVal go ahead and make it public.
Return value will be the same as leftVal which is double.
We'll call it getLeftVal and all that does
is simply return back leftVal.
So that gives us an access of our leftVal.
For our mutator, again will be public.
This time it will be void though because mutators
don't return a value.
It will be set leftVal and we'll accept a parameter
of type double we'll call leftVal.
And then from there we simply assign a parameter
to our field.
That's pretty straightforward and we're going to do that
for rightVal and opCode as well.
So those accessors and mutators in place we can set
the values of any of those as well as access them.
And that makes sense for leftVal, rightVal, and opCode.
But result's a little different.
Result is the result of this class doing what it does,
executing an operation.
So it doesn't really make sense for anyone to be able
to modify result from the outside.
They certainly should be able to see it but not modify it.
So this the case where we may want to have a accessor
but not a mutator.
What it does is an effect make our result a read-only value.
So we'll do is for our result, we'll go ahead and create
that accessor but we're not going to have a mutator.
So with that we can now just go ahead and update
our application and go ahead and use
the accessors and mutators we've created.
So down here we create MathEquation instance.
We'll just update this to use the mutator,
so I'll say setLeftVal, let me pass the leftVal
as a parameter, close this parenthesis.
Do the same thing for rightVal and opCode.
So that now creates the instance of the MathEquation
setting each of the values.
Then we head up here where we access the result,
we'll change that to use the accessor for results.
Let's make this getResult.
So let's go ahead and run it, make sure everything works.
And there we have our output values.
So we've now updated our MathEquation class.
So we're properly hiding the data inside of it,
which will allow us to evolve it when effectively over time
without impacting code that uses our class.