In this module, we started introducing the object-oriented aspects of Java.
That means that we started talking about classes
because classes are the way we describe our object.
There's a template for creating an object.
That we use the class keyword to declare them,
we use the new keyword to create instances of them.
Remember that classes create reference types,
meaning that if we have a variable that's a type of a class,
the variable doesn't actually hold the class instance
itself, it holds a reference to the class instance.
That's really important because when we assign between
two variables, we don't copy the object,
we copy the reference causing the two variables
to point to the same object instance.
Really important difference from primitive types.
Encapsulation is an important part
of object-oriented programming, we don't want to have
our details exposed to the users of our objects.
We use access modifiers to control encapsulation.
We use methods to manipulate the state
and perform operations on our objects.
If we want to exit a method early or if our method
has a return type we use the return keyword to control that.
And objects have not just operations
but they also have state where we use fields to store
the object state.
Fields are generally considered a kind of low level detail
of our objects, so we generally don't want to expose
those directly to users of the objects.
So we normally do or at least most commonly do
is use accessors and mutators to control interaction
with our fields.
Basically we use methods so that if we can change
the implementation detail of the data without affecting
the usage of our class.