Java is an object-oriented language and that means,
of course, that it follows the tenets of object-oriented
programming and so objects are these things that encapsulate
the data, operations and usage semantics.
In other words, is that what you want to work on and how you
work with it or kind of package up this idea of an object.
Obviously allow the storage and manipulation details
of things to be hidden, all right, so that when someone's
working with an object, they focus on what they want to
have done, it's not their concern on how it's done.
The class implementer, or the object implementer,
actually focuses on the "how", the consumer or user
just focuses on the "what."
So that's a really powerful idea that allows us to
build more complex programs.
The way we get to objects in Java is through classes.
Classes provide a structure for describing and creating
our objects, in other words the classes are the things
that we use to be able to describe our objects
and then be able to instantiate them,
bring them into existence, to be worked with.
Basically a class is a template for creating an object.
So the idea is that we want to declare a class,
we use the class keyword followed by the class name.
Now normally when we create our classes,
we put them in their own source file and that source file
will have the same name as the class itself.
There are some caveats to that that we'll talk about shortly
but most cases, your source file name would simply be
the classname.java.
Now the body of the class is then just contained
inside of brackets.
You have an opening bracket and a closing bracket
and that's where the contents of the class are going to go,
all inside of there.
Now we mentioned that classes have both the state
and what we want to do with it so the idea is that a class
has the data inside of it and all of it's executable code.
So this captures three general ideas is that the state
itself is in what we call fields.
So we look at our class Flight we've declared here,
it's got two fields in it.
They're both integers, one for passengers and one for seats.
Classes also have methods, this is the executable code
that's going to manipulate the state
and perform any operations.
So in this case, our class has a method called
add1Passenger and, basically, when someone calls
that and makes sure that there's enough seats available, and
long as there is, it goes ahead and adds another passenger.
Then there's what are called constructors.
Constructors are kind of special case executable code.
This is code that gets run during the creation of an object,
largely to set the initial state.
So we've got here a constructor that basically starts out
by setting seats to 150 and our passengers to zero.
So basically means that when we created a Flight,
that flight has 150 seats on it.