When you're ready to use a class, as you would expect,
you would go ahead and declare a variable.
The thing we got to be aware of is that declaring a variable
simply allocates space to store what we call a reference
to the actual object we want to use.
To actually create an instance of our class,
otherwise known as an object,
we have to use the new keyword.
So what we do, we've got our variable nycToSf,
we assign that the value of new Flight.
What that then does is call the new Flight,
allocates the memory associated with that class
and then returns back a reference to it.
So what means is then that variable nycToSf is not
the object itself but a reference to the object.
Right now each instance that we create will be separate from
one another and, as you see here, that I've actually
declared the variable and then assigned the object to it
in two separate statements.
We can of course do that in a single statement.
So I've got a variable slcToDallas equals new Flight
that allocates out the slcToDallas, which is the space
for the reference, creates the instance of Flight
and assigns the reference to our variable.
So each of these are two distinct instances of our
Flight object and each of their own variables.
We can then call a method on one of those instances,
in this case we'll call add1Passenger on our slcToDallas,
which will cause our passengers to go from zero to one.
As we saw when we were using our classes
and creating class instances, these objects,
we saw that the variable wasn't the object itself.
Instead it was a reference to the object and that tells us
that we're working with reference types.
And that has some important implications when it comes to
working with objects.
So we look at some code here.
If I declare a variable flight1 that points to a new Flight
that allocates out to variable flight1,
allocates out the instance of our object and puts a
reference to that object into flight1,
I do the same thing for flight2.
That creates a separate object and slides it into a
separate variable, flight2.
So those two objects are completely separate
from one another.
So, if I call add1Passenger on flight2
the object instance pointed to by flight2
will have its passengers incremented from zero to one,
so of course if I print out flight2 passengers,
it prints out one.
Now if I assign flight1 to flight2,
that doesn't copy the entire object pointing from
by flight1 into flight2.
All that does was reassign the reference so that flight2,
instead of pointing to the object it currently points to,
will now point to the same object that flight1 points to.
So now once that object pointing to by flight2 or
previously pointed by flight2 is no longer referenced,
that object goes away and flight2 and flight1
are pointing to now to the exact same object.
If I now print out flight2.passengers, it prints out zero
because that's the value of passengers in the object
it's pointing to.
So now if I work through flight1 and I say add1Passenger,
where that increments passengers from zero to one,
of course, if I then call it add1Passenger again
on flight1, that increments it from one to two.
So now if I print out flight2.passengers,
I get out the value two, I print out the value two.
So it's important to understand that we make this
assignments we're assigning references around
not entire object.
This is very different from when we were working with
primitive types where the values were
actually copied around.
So it's really important to understand that that as
reference types, assignments cause us to point to the
same object instances as opposed to making complete copies.