Since Java is an object-oriented language, we want to use
good object-oriented techniques when we build our programs.
Remember that one of the things we talked about is that
when you consume an object or when you use an object,
you want to be able to think about the "what"
of what you're doing not the "how" of what you're doing.
Because one important idea in there is that as we build
our objects the internal representation of those objects
should generally be hidden.
The user of an object shouldn't have to know a whole lot
about the way that object is built.
So the idea of hiding this internal representation
is an idea we call encapsulation.
In Java, the way we achieve encapsulation is by using
access modifiers.
Let's talk about some of the most basic access modifiers.
Now the most basic access modifier at all is to have
no access modifier and, in fact, that's what
we've been doing up until now.
If a class or a class member does not have an access modifier
on it that's considered what we call "package private",
only usable within its own package.
We'll talk more about that one later in the course
when we spend more time on packages.
Now one of the ones we commonly see is the public access
modifier and if a class or a class member is
marked as public, that means it can just be used anywhere,
anywhere in the program.
And the last one we're going to talk about for now
is one called private.
If a class member is marked as private, it's only accessible
from within the class where it's declared.
Now top level classes, the kind of classes
that we're working with right now, cannot use the
private access modifier.
Little later in the course we'll talk about some scenarios
with nested classes where we can use the private access modifier.