Let's take a look at how the access modifiers affect
the uses of our class and its class members.
Now I have here basically the same class
we looked at earlier.
We have our class Flight, it has some fields declared
at the top, passengers and seats.
It has a constructor.
It then has a method add1Passenger and I've also added
another method to this called handleTooMany
that gets called from add1Passenger.
The idea being that when we call out 1Passenger
if there's not enough seats add1Passenger
will call handleTooMany to do whatever we want
to have happen when have too many passengers.
So now let's take this and we'll go ahead and add
a public access modifier to class Flight.
Now what that means, of course, is that we're now
allowed to access class Flight from anywhere.
So we can go out there and declare our variable
called flight1 of type Flight.
I'm going to go ahead and mark the constructor as
public as well which means I'm also allowed to now
create instances of this class.
We'll talk more about constructors shortly but the key
thing here is that we are allowed to create instances
of the Flight class.
Now let's take our two fields, passengers and seats,
and we'll mark those as private.
Now as private they're accessible from within the class.
So inside of our constructor we're allowed to access them.
Inside that method add1Passenger we're allowed
to access them, that's fine.
But if from outside the class, we tried to do something
like we did earlier like print out the value of passengers,
that's no longer allowed.
That would actually be a compile time error.
We wouldn't be allowed to have that code in our
program accessing it from outside of the class.
Now looking at our methods, let's say we mark
add1Passenger as public and handleTooMany as private.
Well, from outside the class I'm free to call add1Passenger.
That calls into add1Passenger.
Add1Passenger if it checks the number of seats,
if they're already full it actually would call down to
handleTooMany and that would be just fine because
we're accessing the handleTooMany from with the inside
of our Flight class.
But if from the outside we tried to call handleTooMany,
again, that would be a compile time error.
We're not allowed to access it from outside of the class.
Now one thing to note, now that our class is marked
as public, remember that earlier I mentioned that the class
file for class normally has the same name as the class.
Well once we mark this class as public, that becomes
a requirement; public classes have to be inside
of a source file with the same name.
So a public class called Flight has to be in a source file
called Flight.java.
Now if it's not marked as public, that requirement is not in place.
Are you allowed to name the file whatever you want.
You always want to be careful about choosing the name
the class file something different than the class.
There are legitimate reasons to do so.
But just consider that carefully.