This is a great time for us to just take a minute and look
at the rules and conventions for creating class names.
Now class names have the same rules as variable names
in terms of what characters are allowed.
And they actually even follow most of the same conventions.
They still use only letters and numbers,
the first character is always a letter,
but one of the key differences in conventions is they
follow a naming pattern called Pascal Case which says that
the first letter of every word including the first word
is upper case with all the rest being lower case.
So if we have a class name like BankAccount,
both the B in bank and the A in account
are both capital.
And if that was a variable name,
the B would have been lower case.
What we want to do is that when we're naming
our classes, we want to use descriptive nouns.
So we want to say things like a class called Person.
Or class TrainingVideo.
In general, we want to avoid abbreviations.
We want to use full words.
Now the caveat to that would be any scenario where
the abbreviation tends to be more widely used
than the word itself.
Like, people rarely say "Uniform Resource Locator".
Using "URL" is much more common.