Now we've mentioned that methods are basically just
executable code that we can use to manipulate the state
of our objects and perform operations.
Basically, each method has a name.
Now the rules for creating method names
are the same as they were with variables.
One of the things we normally do from a stylistic
standpoint, though, is use a verb or some kind of
action statement to name our methods.
Now methods have a return type and in Java there's
always a return type so if a method doesn't return
anything, then that return type is void.
And then a method can have parameters.
So parameters, start with a parenthesis after
the method name, you then list the parameters,
close the parenthesis.
Then the body of the method is enclosed in brackets
with however many statements it takes to build your method.
Now note that these brackets are not a statement block.
They're always required, even if your method only had
one statement, that statement goes inside
of brackets in a method.
So to see an example, let's create a really simple method
here and we'll have it not return any values.
We'll make it a void method and let's say we'll call this
guy showSum and let's say what we want this method to do
is maybe take two floating point values, add them up
and then it will print out that value multiple times.
So it'll be three parameters here.
So we have our open paren,
so let's have a float x, a comma to separate it
from the next parameter of float y.
A comma to separate it from the next parameter
and then an int count.
So the idea is that we'll add x to y and then print that
result out count number of times.
So we'll close the parenthesis,
we then put our brackets in place for the body
and then we'll do the work.
So we'll add x plus y to get sum,
we'll create a loop that counts from zero
and incrementing i each time as long as it's less than count
and then prints that value out.
So now when it comes down to use this method,
the first thing we want to do is let's go ahead
and just wrap it up inside of a class because all methods
are inside of classes.
We'll go ahead and make our method public
so we can access it.
And then put together some code that will first create
an instance of our object and then we're going to say
object instance name which is m.showSum,
calling the method.
And we're going to pass in 7.5, 1.4, and three.
So the 7.5 will go into x, the 1.4 goes in the y,
and the three goes in to count.
So what will happen then is that sum will become 7.5
plus 1.4, 8.9, then we're going to go inside of our loop
and print that out three times.
So we would see 8.9 printed out three times.