Looking at that method we created in the last clip,
basically we call in to the method, the method runs
until it's done and then it exits.
Well there are actually three reasons a method will exit.
One is that it reaches the end of the method
which is the case in our showSum method here.
You can also put a return statement in
to indicate that you want to exit.
And there's a third scenario which is when an error occurs.
And then we're going to talk a lot more about the way
the error situation is handled
when we get to the module and exceptions.
For now we're going to focus on these first two scenarios
reaching the end of the method or having a return statement.
So when a method is done, it returns back
to where it was called from.
So in the case of our little showSum function here,
if we have our code where we created the class instance
and then we called showSum.
If we have another instruction after that that printed out
a message like "I am back", what's going to happen
is that when we call m.showSum, that's going to pass control
into our showSum method, it will do its work
which is print out that 8.9 three times.
And the control is getting passed back up to the caller
which will pass control to that print line "I am back",
which then prints that message out.
Now if we wanted to, we could put a return statement here
at the end and would actually work exactly the same.
In that case we'll be exiting because it hit the return
instead of the end of the method.
In this scenario it doesn't change anything
but the return statement does not have to go
at the end of the method.
Imagine if we have a suddenly different call here,
is that when we call showSum, instead of passing three
as the last parameter, we pass the zero.
Well what would happen in that case?
Is we'd call in the showSum, we would do the work,
they add the numbers together
and then our print statement wouldn't do anything.
Basically our showSum method would actually have
no real results.
Now in this case we're just doing something very simple,
adding, but in many methods you may be doing a lot of work
that you end up not using.
So it's often used, want to check your parameters
at the very beginning of a method and if a certain criteria
aren't met you just go ahead and exit.
So if we actually go ahead and make a little more room
in our method here, what we might do at the very beginning
is say, well, if count is less than one, well we know
we're not going to do anything
so we're just going to go ahead and return.
So in this case what happened is we call showSum,
control is passed in to showSum.
We check count which is zero, so we simply exit back out
and print our "I am back".
Where we end up not doing all that work that we weren't
going to use anyway.
So the return statements can be placed
anywhere inside your method that makes sense for the work
that you're doing.