When a method returns that method's not void
that it actually returns a value.
Now method always returns just a single value.
Now a value can be a primitive type like a float,
a short, a Boolean.
Can also be a reference to an object,
and it can even be in a reference to an array
because in Java arrays are objects.
So let's take a look at that Flight class
we've been working with.
Now remember that it has two fields in it:
passengers and seats.
And for now, I'm not going to show the other methods
we've seen already, I want to focus on some new methods
we're going to add here.
So let's say we have a method that we want to check and see
that is there room to combine the passengers
from another flight with those passengers on this flight.
So it knows we pass in a parameter which is the other Flight
we call F2 and that return type is Boolean.
So we could say here is that we'll figure out the total
number of passengers.
So how many passengers do we have
with how many passengers does the other flight have?
And then we check and see, well if that total is less than
or equal to the number of seats we have will return true,
otherwise will return false.
In this case it's a method returning back
a Boolean variable.
Notice the code we're using for our return value here,
if total less than or equal to seats resolves to true
we then return true.
If total less than or equal to seats resolves to false
we return false.
Well, rather than actually have the if and the return
why don't we just use that value directly.
So what we can do is we can replace that if statement
by simply saying return total less than or equal to seats.
Whatever that resolves to it will be our return value.
So let's make a little more room here,
since we have covered some of that code.
Let's create another method here.
This method we'll call createNewWithBoth
and you notice that this one returns back a reference
to a Flight object.
And the idea here is that it will actually create
a brand new Flight that combines the passenger count
from the current Flight and that Flight f2 that's passed in.
So we'll do here is we'll create a new instance
of the Flight object.
We'll then say the number of seats in that newFlight
is equal to the number of seats
that our current Flight object has
and then number of passengers has to combine
of our passengers and the other Flight
and then we'll just return back this newly created Flight.
We're returning back a reference to this newFlight
that we created.
So to use this in code, what we'll do is let's go ahead
and declare one Flight instance.
That will be a Flight to LAX, to Los Angeles
that will be our Flight lax1.
We'll create another Flight to Los Angeles, lax2.
And we'll say that we just run some code that adds
passengers to both of these flights.
So at some point when we get passed this comment,
both lax1 and lax2 has some number of passengers.
So let me just create a new Flight reference
but as I'm not creating a Flight
it's just a Flight reference.
What I want to do now is check to see that
well if there's room to combine lax1 and lax2 passengers,
I want to go ahead and do that.
So what I'll do here is have an if statement in place
that says well, if lax1.hasRoom(lax2).
Well that calls over to our hasRoom method.
When we get into the hasRoom method, because we called
hasRoom against the lax1 Flight instance,
anywhere we refer to the class variables
passengers and seats whether unqualified
that means we're referring to the values
that are currently in lax1.
When we refer to passengers using the f2 reference,
that's actually lax2's passengers because that's
when we passed in to the parameter.
So when we run this method it basically adds those together
and then if there's room it will return back true.
If there's not it will return back false.
Then we can go ahead and say lax3 equals
lax1.createNewWithBoth passing lax2.
So now again, control transfers over
to the createNewWithBoth.
Again, because we called this against lax1,
anywhere we use seats or passengers unqualified
those are the lax1 seats.
f2 passengers will be the lax2 passengers.
So in this code we go ahead and create
that newFlight instance assign it to the number of seats
from lax1 to Flight reference we were called against
and then passengers are set to the value of lax1's
passengers plus lax2's passengers.
And then we return back that newFlight.
So lax3 we receive a reference to that newly created
Flight instance returned back
from the createNewWithBoth method.