To wrap up, remember that we use
the Java command to execute our
Java programs from the command line.
All right, the key thing there is that
it allows us to run our Java programs
without having to have a full IDE, right?
That's actually our Java execution environment.
When you run the program, we specify
the Class name, including its full package name.
In other words, we're not running a file.
We're actually running the Class.
On Windows in order to access the Java command,
what you want to do is make sure that you have
your JRE's Bin folder in your Path Environment Variable.
As we saw, programs are made up of statements, right?
Statements and with semicolons.
And, the parts of a statement are separated
by zero or more whitespaces, right?
That gives us a lot of flexibility in how we want
to format our source code.
As we saw, though, in some of the examples,
that can get really ugly,
especially if you start using too many new lines.
You want to be careful about how much
whitespace you use.
But, use enough to keep things clear and easy to read.
Comments are a useful tool
for adding notes to our source code,
as well as hiding statements that we don't
want being seen by the compiler.
For example, if we just want to take some code
out to test something, or maybe preserve
some code for later.
And as we saw, packages provide organization, right?
They help us assure uniqueness in our class names,
and we also saw that most IDEs
will actually tie the source code file structure
to the package name, so that each part
of the package name is a separate sub-folder.
As I mentioned earlier, packages are a really
important part of Java.
And, we're going to talk a whole bunch more
about those later. In fact, they get their own module.