Let's go ahead now and create our very first Java project.
And, we'll go ahead and just use
the IntelliJ IDE to do this one.
I have a shortcut to IntelliJ on my Desktop,
so let's go ahead and double-click that guy to start up.
So once IntelliJ starts up here, okay,
it takes you to this initial window,
and what I want to do is create a new project.
So, I'll click on that.
Now, it takes me into the Wizard to create the project.
Now, one of the first things we have to do
is, of course, choose we want to have a Java project,
because we were, IntelliJ worked for a variety of things.
And, we also have to associate the JDK version
we want to use.
Now, you only have to do this step once.
What we do here is where it says Project SDK,
and you'll notice that there are none now.
There's none to choose, all right.
So, what we're going to do is click on this New
button here on the right,
we're going to choose to set up a project in SDK,
which is the JDK,
and what we're going to do now is navigate to
where we installed the JDK.
All right, it's for me, it's on Program Files,
scroll down, Java,
and then, make sure you choose JDK, not the JRE.
All right, you want the JDK, say OK.
And now that we've done that,
we can create projects with that JDK.
So now, one thing that's just a little bit of a challenge
is that this Wizard screen doesn't render well
on the resolution that we record at.
So, I'm just going to pull that up here just a little bit.
Notice that, the buttons across the bottom.
All right, so what I'm going to do is click
the Next button to move onto the next step of the Wizard.
So, I click on the Next button.
So now, it says what template do you want to use,
or do you want to use a template at all?
We're going to say, yeah, go ahead
and create it from a template.
And what that does is just creates
some initial file layouts for us.
Sets things up, so we can go ahead and get started easily.
And, we're just going to create a regular command line
application, which is just the most basic kind
of Java application, okay?
If I pull this dialog up, okay,
I'm going to click that Next button
down there at the bottom.
So now, we go ahead and want to name things.
So, kind of in the lifelong tradition
of programming and programming courses,
we're going to create a Hello World app.
Let's just go ahead and call this project name Hello World.
So, I've named the project Hello World.
I'm going to go ahead here and where it says,
Base Package, I'm going to go ahead
and delete that away for now.
We'll come back to that a little bit later.
And, I'm just specifying where I want it to go.
So, I was going to put it into a folder
under my Demo folder for this module,
called Hello World.
If I pull this guy up,
notice down at that bottom, now there's actually a Finish
button, so that's what I'm going to select this time
is the Finish button.
So as it starts up, it brings me into the project.
One of the features of IntelliJ is it actually has
kind of the Tip of the Day.
Just kind of show you different fact about working
in their environment, and so forth.
I'm going to close that up.
You notice here it's generated a source code file for me.
And up on the left here, I've got my Project Explorer.
It just kind of shows me the hierarchy
of the files it's created.
If I expand Hello World in this Source folder here,
there's the Main, and that's the Class file
that goes with the Class I've created.
I'm going to talk a whole bunch more about Classes
later in the course.
This is basically just becomes the start of our application.
Now, IntelliJ always creates this initial Class
as Class Name Main.
That Class Name doesn't actually matter.
We'll talk a lot more about Class names a little bit later.
What does matter is inside of your, there's what's called
a Method, right?
That's where our code runs.
And for Java applications, the startup of your application
must be in a Class that has a member called Main,
that looks just like this.
So, it has to be public.
I mean, just publically accessible.
We'll talk more about that modifier later.
The modifier's static, void.
It has to be called Main and it has to look just like this.
So whenever you run your code in Java,
it's going to look for this as an entry point.
All right, so what I'm going to do is delete
this line away here,
and we'll do the classic Hello World application.
So, I'm going to use an object here,
which I've called System.
And, I'm going to use something called Out and Print Line.
All right, and this is just a mechanism in Java
we use to print things out to the console.
Then, we're going to say, Hello World.
So, we have that there.
So, this is kind of the most fundamental application
we can build, all right?
Now, the way we run this in IntelliJ is that we go
up here to the Run menu, click on that,
and we choose Run.
When we do that, we'll see that IntelliJ
will go ahead and compile our code for us,
and then, down here at the bottom, it shows
a Console window, and actually shows
the output of our application.
So in this case, it says, Hello World.
Now, our focus here is on Java,
not on the development environment.
But, just to show you a couple things
that makes it easier.
We saw how to run it from the menu.
Once we have this window down here,
if say, we want to change something,
(mumbles) say, Hello World,
we'll just say again.
If I want to go ahead and rerun the code, I can go
down here on the bottom where I have this
little green arrow, click on that.
And, we'll just run the code over again.
Compile it and run it for us.
And now, we see Hello World again.
So, we've successfully run our very first Java
Hello World program.