Let's walk through a demo now of running
our program from the command line.
In other words, what we want to do is
look at how we can run our program
without having to use a developer tool
like IntelliJ to do it.
In the previous demo, we when we wrote our application,
where we did all of the work here
inside of a developer tool, in this case, IntelliJ.
All right, and as did our compile.
And, even that ran it for us.
Now as developers, we have that tool.
But, how end-users run our program,
or how does an end-user execute the program
without having one of these developer tools?
And, that's what we want to look at now.
Now, the thing we want to remember is that
the Main Class for our application here is called Main.
All right, it didn't have to be,
but that's what it's called here.
And, we're going to have to remember that
when it becomes time to run our program.
Now, remember that we say that end-users
have to install the JRE, right,
the Java Runtime Environment.
And, let's take a look in there for a second.
Here I am on the C Drive of my Windows computer.
And what I'm going to do is go down to here
to Program Files, and inside, there's a folder
called Java, right?
And inside there, that's the JRE, all right?
That's the execution file, right?
The Java Runtime Environment.
And, we said that that's what actually runs
our programs, right?
Java programs don't run directly.
They run within the Java environment.
If I go inside of this folder, you see there's
another folder called Bin.
And, you'll notice inside of here,
if I scroll down a little bit, there's actually
a program called Java.
That Java program is what actually runs our program.
All right, now if you're on Linux or Mac,
you can basically use that Java program directly.
If you're on Windows, you want to make sure
that it's actually in your Path, right, so that you can
actually type just the word Java, and it will
find it in this folder.
So, what we want to do is keep track of this location
where we found the Java exe.
So, we're going to just copy this.
And again, what we want to do is put that
into the Path of our machine.
So, what I've got up here is Control Panels.
So, I'm going to go ahead and open up the Control Panel.
In your Control Panel, I'm going to find the System entry.
Open that guy up.
And, what I want to do is go to Advance System Settings.
And from here, I want to go to Environment Variables.
And, what I want to do here is I want to
go ahead and add that to my Path, right?
So, I'm going to add it to my User Path.
Now, I happen to have no current User Path set up.
On your machine, you may already have
an entry in here that says Path.
If you have an existing one, you're going to
highlight it and say, Edit.
I want to create a new one,
because I don't have Path yet.
So, I want to call it Path.
And, all I'm going to do is paste in that location
where that Java exe was, all right?
And when I say OK, now we see Path listed here.
All right, and so just kind of to clarify it,
if when you open Environment Variables,
if you already saw Path, you would highlight it and click Edit.
Because I didn't have it already, I had clicked New.
All right, and so we're going to say OK.
And, OK.
And, close these guys up.
And so now, I have the folder where my Java program's
located in my Path, so I can just type it
from the command line.
So, now what we want to do is run our program.
So, what I'm going to do now is go to the folder
where I created our application's project.
So, when I create our application's project,
I created it in this Demo folder.
And, remember I called it Project Hello World.
So, I go in here into Hello World.
You see a series of folders.
Now, the exact layout of these folders is specific
to the way IntelliJ does it.
But in any environment your using,
you're going to see something similar to this.
So, what we want to do here is go to our Out folder.
Alright, again, the name Out is specific to IntelliJ.
Whatever tool you're using will have something like that.
And so, we go to Out.
And you'll see Production, is another folder inside there.
And then, inside of here, we see Hello World.
All right, if I go inside of there, we can see,
in this case our Class file.
This Hello World folder under Out and Production
is the result of compiling our program.
And again, the names Out and Production
are specific to IntelliJ.
But, whatever environment you're working
from, you'll have some folder structure like that.
The key is we want to have wherever the output
was placed, which is our Hello World.
All right, now that we're here,
we can actually open up a command line
and run our program.
So, what I'm going to do is,
let's go ahead and jump up here.
Just type CMD to open up a command prompt
in this location.
So, I've got a command prompt here.
And, what I'm going to do is just type,
Java hyphen version.
I mean, there's there it outputs that it's
the, it gives me, the version number of Java.
And, basically what this really tells me is
that my Java command's working.
If that doesn't work for you, if you get something
like command not found or you get a version
different than the one you were expecting,
what you may have to do is just log out and log
back in because user level Environment Variables
don't take effect right away.
All right, so if you get, again,
if you get like program not found when you type Java,
just log out and log back in.
It should then work when you open your
next command prompt.
If it doesn't, just go back and make sure you've
got your Path Setting to the right location
to where that Java dot exe was located.
So now to run our program, what we're going to do
is say, Java, and what we want to do
is give it the Class name that actually had
that Main entry point in it.
Remember, in our case, our Class name
was actually Main.
So, let's go ahead and hit Enter.
And, there we see Hello World again.
All right, so we see that we actually successfully
ran our program without having to use any fancy IDE.
All right, this is how it would run
in an end-user environment.
They would have your Class file,
the thing we produced when we built the program,
and just using the Java command, goes ahead and launches it.