Java programs are made up of statements.
Now, a lot of different things can
go on in a particular statement.
And, we'll talk about those things throughout this course.
But fundamentally, programs are made up of statements.
Now, each statement ends with a semicolon, right?
Java's a language where the new line and the Enter key
doesn't really create a new statement, right?
It actually (mumbles) on the semicolon.
If you're going from any of the C-based languages,
that's something you're very familiar with, right?
Other languages, like Visual Basic, actually use
the end of the end of line to mark a statement.
In Java, it's the semicolon.
And the parts of a statement can be separated
by zero or more whitespaces, right?
So, and a whitespace can be many different things.
It can be the Space character.
It can be a Tab.
And because statements don't end with new line,
even the new line itself is just a whitespace in Java.
Java's a language that gives us a lot of flexibility
with whitespaces.
Because, remember we said that the parts can be
separated by zero or more whitespaces.
So, it allows us to format things in a way
that works well for us, right?
So, I can have a statement like this where all of the parts
are pushed all together with no whitespaces
between them.
But then, I can have the same statement
where I just put a space after the Print line,
and a space after the parenthesis,
and a space before the other parenthesis.
That will do the exact same thing.
I can even put multiple spaces in there, right,
and that still does the exact same thing.
And, remember that because the new line
is considered a whitespace, I can even format
it like this, right?
Now, this is kind of a crazy way to format it
and I wouldn't suggest you do this.
But, it's all just whitespace, all right?
So, after that Print line, we've got a new line,
followed by a bunch of the Space characters.
That's fine.
All right, after that parenthesis, we got a new line again.
After Hello World, we got a new line, another new line,
and then, a whole bunch of whitespaces.
All right, so (mumbles) a whole bunch of Space character.
And so, it just shows us that the whitespace allows us
to indent, format, put line breaks
in a way that works for us, right?
The whitespaces are just separators.
And, it's that semicolon that marks the end of the statement.