Java, like most programming languages,
has the ability to include comments, all right?
And, comments are basically text inside of your
source code that the compiler doesn't see.
All right, and there are really kind of just
two general uses for comments.
One is that it allows you to add human-readable notes
to your source code.
It allows you to type things in the source code,
so that when you look at it later or someone else
looks at it, you're just leaving notes
to understand what you were doing there.
It's also useful for hiding source code without deleting it.
Maybe you're testing things out, so you want to just
kind of take some things away and type some new stuff,
or there's something you don't want to do anymore,
but you think you might want to do it again in the future.
So, comments allow you to take that stuff out so that
the contents in your source code, but the compiler
doesn't compile it.
There are three types of comments in Java.
One, which is called line comments.
If you basically put a double slash,
basically the compiler ignores everything
until the end of the line.
And, when I say by the end of the line,
it's actually until you hit the Enter key,
the new line character.
It's not like other statements where it relies
on the semicolon, all right.
So, the compiler just skips everything
until the next new line.
(mumbles) called block comments,
where you use a slash, star to begin the comment,
and a star, slash to end it.
So, compiler skips everything between those notations.
They can be, happen in the middle of a line,
or they can span multiple lines.
And the last kind is a special kind of comment
called a JavaDoc comment,
which starts out slash, star, star,
and it ends star, slash.
There's a utility called JavaDoc
that allows you to generate documentation
using this special comment format.
That allows you basically to write your code
documentation right inside of your source code.
And then, when you run the JavaDoc utility,
if you follow the appropriate structure in your comments,
that utility will generate documentation
right from the source code file.
The details of JavaDoc are outside the scope
of this course, but I've got that URL
up there on the screen for you if you want
to dig into JavaDoc and learn more about it.