Let's take a quick look now at using
comments in our code.
Here I am back in the program we wrote earlier.
And, let's just take this line we write out
Hello World again, let's copy that
and put it back in a couple more times.
Let's just say Hello World one, two, and three.
Now, if we go to run our program down here,
we'll see that all three of those lines get written
out for Hello World one, two, and three.
So, using comments, we can add information
into our source code.
First, I'll use a line comment,
so I'll just do a Slash, Slash.
I'll say, this is a comment.
And, this comment only exists until I get to the new line.
All right, you notice that even the IDE is using
a different color text just to make the comments stand out.
However, if I run this, it's had no impact
on what our program does.
All right, it still says Hello World one, two and three.
All right, but if I go down to the next line here
and put a double slash in front of that,
all right, that line is now ignored by the compiler.
Right, so if I go ahead and run this,
I get Hello World one, Hello World three.
All right, so it allows again to just kind of have this
comment only exists for a single line.
All right, and of course, these comments can
also be on a line by themselves.
If I had a line here, I would just type something like,
this is a standalone comment.
All right, and go ahead and run this guy again.
All right, and no change in the output,
because again, the comment lasts until the end of the line.
All right, now block comments actually
have distinct starting and ending points, right?
So, if before this message here, if I put a slash, star,
that comment exists until the star, slash.
Right, so I can say, this is the first line of the comment,
all right, and I can even add another line and say,
this is the second line of the comment.
And, I can have as many of these lines here as I want to
because a comment doesn't end until it gets
to the star, slash.
Using that same technique, block comments can start
and end in the middle of the same line, all right?
So if I just wanted to change this text here,
but not delete it, so I do a slash, star,
and I put a star, slash at the end.
And now, I put in here, this is different text,
everything between the slash, star and star, slash
is ignored, but then once we hit the end of the block
comment, compiler looks at it again.
Or, I should say the compiler sees the text again.
All right, so if I go over here and I run this now,
I get my Hello World one, but then,
I get the, this is different text.
All right, and so the really key thing is that
the slash, slash comment just exists
until the very end of the line.
The block comments have distinct starting
and ending points.
One thing to be aware of block comments
is that you cannot nest them, all right.
So, I got a block comment here at the top
but this is the first line of the comment,
this is the second line of the comment.
If I put a slash, star in here,
you notice that at that second star, slash,
the one at the bottom now shows up as an error,
because the compiler doesn't have a distinct
idea of for every starting block comment,
there is an ending block.
Basically, as soon as it sees the very first encounter
of star, slash, all the comments are ended.
So, you cannot nest block comments.
Now, it is okay to put line comments
inside of a block comment.
So, if I put a slash, slash line comment in here,
all right, that's not an error.
You wouldn't intentionally do that really,
because you're already in the comment block,
so why put a line comment in there?
But, if you happen to have an existing line comment
and you wrap it in a block comment, that's still safe.
The bottom line here is that comments allow us
to put text inside of our source code
that we don't want to be seen by the compiler,
all right, whether it's notes to ourselves
or another human being, or we just want certain
source code to be ignored for some period of time.