Let's talk briefly about Java packages.
Now, packages are a very important concept in Java
and we actually talk a great deal more about them
later when we have a whole module dedicated to them.
We want to look at just a couple simple things
about packages right now to get us started.
Now, if we look at our source code,
all our source code we've written up until now
has just kind of our Class definitions,
and that's kind of by itself.
But if you look at most source code out there,
you'll see that at the top of each source code file,
you'll see the word package, followed by some name.
And, what this does when we add this package concept,
it provides organization within a Java program.
Now again, there's a lot of aspects of that,
but we want to look at just two basic
aspects of that to get us started.
One is that these package names follow
a standard naming convention, and they
actually affect our source code file structure.
Now in terms of the naming convention,
one very simple rule is that package names
are all lowercase.
All right, that's just a convention (mumbles)
actually allow it not to be all lowercase,
but that is the convention that package names
are all lowercase.
And, one of the things we're trying to do
with package names is create a sense of uniqueness.
So, one aspect of uniqueness is on the global scale,
throughout the entire world.
So, in order to assure package name uniqueness
on a global scale, what we generally do is use
the reversed domain name, all right?
So for an example of that,
Pluralsight owns Pluralsight dot com, right,
and there's actually an authority out there
that makes sure that no one else
buys the name Pluralsight dot com.
So, what we do is that we start all of our package
names using that domain name, right?
So, any package created by Pluralsight would actually
use the name com dot Pluralsight.
Right, again, it's reversed.
So, the top level of its com, and then, Pluralsight.
So, that now assures that as long as everything
we do at Pluralsight starts with that naming structure,
no one else will name a package like that.
And again, there's nothing that enforces this rule,
it's just a convention we all follow to keep things
form colliding with one another.
And then, what we want to do is that
we add further qualifiers beyond that to assure
uniqueness within an organization, right,
in the case of a company or some group.
If we're creating packages that belong to
com dot Pluralsight, each of our individual
packages would have another part to it
that just identifies some project.
So in this case, it's My Project.
And, that's kind of the simplest way
to assure uniqueness, right,
is that each project can have its own
kind of last node part to that, or last part
of the package name and it stays unique.
As organizations get larger, you may have to get
a little bit more sophisticated about your package names.
All right, because if you have multiple development
groups within an organization, if you only have these
three parts, right, the top level, com dot Pluralsight
and then that last part, all the groups would have to
coordinate to make sure they didn't collide
with one another.
So, what often happens is that as you get into larger
organizations, you'll add another standardized part to it.
So, maybe you have com dot Pluralsight,
but if Pluralsight had their own development group
for the Accounting Department, you might
agree that, well, everything created by the development
group in the Accounting Department
is com dot Pluralsight dot accounting.
And then, say if there was another group
inside of Pluralsight, and say that was
the group that took care of course management.
If that was their own development group,
they would then agree that all the packages they
create are com dot Pluralsight dot course management.
And then, there's no concern about colliding
because when they name their individual projects,
even if they named them both My Project,
there is no package name collision
because the earlier project was qualified
by their group, created the uniqueness.
And again, these are all conventions.
There's nothing enforcing all this.
But, these are rules that we follow
to make sure our package names don't collide.
Now as we put members into a package,
those members, of course, become part of that package.
All right, and that package becomes part
of the member's name.
And so, if we just build a Class called Main,
well, the name of that Class is just Main.
But now, once we put that Class inside of a package,
all right, the package name become part
of the overall Class name.
So, the Class is no longer known as just Main.
The Class is now known as
com dot Pluralsight dot My Project dot Main.
All right, and that becomes a unique name.
And, because we all follow these naming conventions,
we now know that anyone else in the world can
create a Class called Main, but because it's qualified
by a package that follows a convention.
The Class name itself is actually unique
when qualified fully by the package.
Now, one of the most significant things that affects us
about packages at this early point
in talking about Java is that it turns out these
package names actually affect the source file structure.
Now, what's interesting is that
Java itself requires no correlation between your
package names and your source code file structure.
In other words, it doesn't care how the packages are named.
It doesn't force you to position or structure your
source files in any given way.
That's Java itself.
The things is, most IDEs do require your
sub-folder structure to match up to
the parts of the package name.
So, the things is that even though Java doesn't
require it, we kind of can almost ignore that
because in practice, most tools that you work
with are going to require that your source file
structure match up to your package names.
So, what does that look like?
Well, if we build a Class, as we have earlier,
where we didn't put it inside of a package,
well, the way the IDE expects it to go is that
you've got your source code folder,
and then your Java Class file just goes
right inside that same source code folder.
That's exactly what it expects.
But, if we now have a package definition
in our source code fie,
the presence of that package name
now enforces structural rules on the way
the IDE expects the source code to be laid out.
And basically, is that each of the parts of that package,
need to be there, I should say,
each of the parts of that package name
need to be their own sub-folder.
So, under source, the IDE expects a com sub-folder
to match the first part of the package name.
Then under that, expects a Pluralsight sub-folder,
and then, an example sub-folder.
And then finally, our Main dot Java is expected
to be inside of there.
All right, so as you have different package names,
this hierarchy is going to have to match up to all of those.
Okay, this is true in IntelliJ, it's true in NetBeans, it's true in most IDEs.