Let's take a look now at how packages
affect our application.
So, here we are in IntelliJ.
Let's go ahead and create a new project.
It'll, of course, be a Java project.
Again, remember that the buttons
at the bottom are off the screen here
at this resolution.
So, we'll go ahead and click that Next button,
just accept the defaults here.
I'm going to go ahead and create the project template
as a command line.
Okay, I'll go down here and click the Next button.
So now, I'm going to create my project.
My project name is going to be Organized.
We'll name that as the project.
But now, I'm going to go ahead and give this one a package name.
All right, so we're going to follow
the rules we talked about.
Com dot Pluralsight.
And then, I'm going to go ahead
and add our file qualifier.
And, let's just call this one Get Organized.
So now, our project name Organized
is a IDE concept, or it's just what we're calling
the project in the IDE.
But, this package name,
com dot Pluralsight dot Get Organized
is the package name we're using
within a Java sense.
And very often, the packaged,
the last part of the package name is
the same as your project name.
But, I just wanted to make them different
in this case to show that they're not directly related.
So, let's just go ahead and finish this.
So, here we are in our application now.
All right, we got our source code,
or excuse me, our Class in place,
just like we did before, but now we have
that package declaration at the top.
All right, what I want to do here is
go ahead and delete this line away,
and let's go ahead and write some output.
But this time, we'll just say something like,
hello, get organized.
All right, let's just go ahead and run this, make sure everything's fine.
So, we'll run it just like we did it before.
Run, Run.
And, we see there in our output,
that our Console window shows,
hello, get organized.
So, everything run, just like it did before,
except within the IDE, nothing's really any different.
Let's take a look now about how that change
to a package affected our source code file hierarchy.
So, I create a project called Organized.
So, this is the folder I created it in.
So, it's inside of there.
Our SRC, our source code area.
But, now notice that we have
a com Pluralsight,
and then, a Get Organized.
All right, as so that's where our Main dot Java is.
So, it created our folder just like we thought it would.
But, let's see how it affects our Class name now.
So, I'm going to go back up here to the Organize level.
I'm going to the output folder, so Out,
Production, and then, Organized.
So, I'll go in there.
Let's go ahead and open up a command line here.
Now, you notice right away that
you don't see the Main dot Java in there.
In fact, the Main dot Java is actually buried
down again under this com folder structure.
But, I don't want to focus on that.
We'll talk about that aspect of it later in the course.
But, what I want to do now is open
up the command prompt right there.
So, we've got our command prompt,
and we're going to go ahead and run the program.
Now, remember when we said we run our programs,
we (mumbles) identify the Class name.
All right, so I'm going to say Java,
because we run a Java program.
I'm going to say, com dot Pluralsight dot Get Organized.
All right, that's our package name dot Main.
So now when I run that,
we get our hello, get organized.
Because remember that we said by putting it
in the package, our Class Main, real name is
now the fully qualified name within the package.
Com dot Pluralsight dot Get Organized dot Main.
So, by running that Class name,
qualified with the package,
our application ran correctly.