Up to now, we've done all of our IDE work inside of IntelliJ.
So, let's take a quick look at using NetBeans
to create and run a project.
I have a shortcut to NetBeans right here
on my Desktop, so let's go ahead and start that up.
So, here we are inside of the NetBeans IDE.
So, let's create a new project.
So, I'm just going to say File, New Project.
And when you come over here, it just asks me
what kind of project I want it to be.
So, I want it to go ahead and be a Java project.
It's going to be a Java application, so that's all fine.
So, just click Next.
So now, it comes in here and it
first wants the project name.
So, we'll go ahead and call this.
We'll just call this our
Hello NetBeans project.
And so just like IntelliJ, the project name
is really an IDE concept, all right.
So, what we want to do now is go through it,
identify where we want it to go,
so I'm just going to put it in the same
Demo folder I've been using for the other parts,
for the other demos.
And, I'm down here to create a Main Class, all right.
So, remember that we have our Main entry point
into our application.
Now in NetBeans, you actually specify the package name
and the Class name all together, all right.
And so, we're going to follow the same rules
of com dot Pluralsight.
So, I've the top level of the package name.
I'm just going to make the next level, just say Example.
And so at this point, that's still my package name.
And then, we'd give it that initial Class.
And, remember we said although IntelliJ
always called it Main, we can call it anything we want.
So, I'm going to go ahead and call it App Main.
So, what this is really saying is that my initial Class
is called App Main and it's in the package
com dot Pluralsight dot Example.
So, let's click finish.
So, here we are inside of the source code.
I went ahead and closed this output window for now.
Just to get it out of the way, so we can see more.
So, notice that over there on the left,
there's our source packages and that's our
App Main dot Java, which is the source code file
we're in right now.
Notice there at the top, it creates our package declaration,
com dot Pluralsight dot Example,
and we see our Class definition.
We've got our Main entry point, which is the public
static void Main, right?
So, that's where our code will run from initially.
And, you notice also that NetBeans even puts
some initial comments in.
All right, if it's a block comment up at the very top there,
it's just telling us a little bit about working
with the IDE itself.
If you notice there's the slash, star, star
above the App Main, all right.
That's actually a JavaDocs comment.
So, it's even initially laying it out so that we have
JavaDocs in place for the App Main,
and even for our Main entry point.
So, let's go inside of here, and let's just add
a little code to output something.
So, we've added the code now just to print
out, Hello NetBeans.
So, let's go up here and try running it.
So, I'm going to go up here to my Run menu,
choose Run Project.
So, we can see that Output window,
that we've got the Hello NetBeans printed out,
so we were able to run.
Or, I should say compile and run
our application that easily, right?
Very much like what we did in IntelliJ.
We saw that there were some basic differences
in terms of how we created that initial Class name
and created the project, but fundamentally,
all the IDEs work in very similar ways.
And now, let's take a look at if we wanted to actually
run this application from the command line,
where we would actually find the folder,
so that we could actually run it.
All right, because remember I mentioned earlier
that each of the IDEs kind of sets up its output
folder structure a little bit differently.
So, here I am in my Demo folder,
and here's our Hello NetBeans folder
that we created for this project.
Go down inside of there.
And, you'll notice here that
in NetBeans, instead of having an output folder,
we actually have this Build folder.
So, let's go in there,
and then, there's a Classes folder.
All right, an that's where we're going to run
our application from in the command line
here in a NetBeans project.
So, we're going to go ahead and just open
up the command prompt.
And just like before, we're going to say,
Java to run it, and we're going to, again,
give the package.
Call it, excuse me, package qualified Class name.
So, com dot Pluralsight dot Example.
All right, and then our Class name,
which in this case, we call it App Main.
If we hit Enter, we can there see our output,
Hello NetBeans.
All right, and so we've still ran it exactly the same.
The only difference was that the IDE for NetBeans
created a slightly different output file structure
than IntelliJ had.