Let's do another demo, we'll call it our CalcEngine demo.
And what we'll do in this demo is, we're going to create
a simple application that can go through various just
mathematical calculations.
As we're starting it in this module, but we'll be using it
throughout the course and enhancing it with the various
things we've learned.
We'll start out by creating a brand new project.
I'm going to use IntelliJ for mine, but you can use whatever
you prefer.
We'll create a new project.
And remember that as I mentioned earlier, just because the
screen resolution we're recording, you can't see the very
bottom of this wizard screen, so you scroll up here, and
notice there's a Next button down there at the bottom.
I'm just going to go ahead and create a Java project by
clicking Next.
Going to go ahead and create a command line project.
Again, down there at the bottom there's a Next button,
so I'll go ahead and click that.
So I'm going to call this project CalcEngine and then for my
packaging, I'm going to be com.Pluralsight and I'll call
it .CalcEngine so I've got my project name and my packaging.
Now I'm going to click the Finish button down there
at the bottom.
So now we have our application created.
I'm going to go in here and just
get rid of this comment line,
take that out of the way.
Throughout this project, throughout this course as we
build this project, we're going to just do some mathematical
operations and have the program just do kind of smarter
and smarter things for us.
We're going to initially start off very simple, just doing
very two member calculations, you know, adding two
numbers together, multiplying two numbers together,
that sort of thing.
So what we're going to do is declare a couple of variables
up here at the top first of all.
So we're going to declare two variables that are double,
val1, val2, got those two variables.
Let's go ahead and have another double for result.
So now I have the ability to have two variables to operate
on, store the result, and what we'll do is have, we use a
concept called an opCode.
We're just going to use a one letter code to indicate the
mathematical operation we want to execute, like a for add,
s for subtract, that sort of thing.
We're going to create a char variable called opCode,
so that sets up my basic ability to set the values of what
I want to do.
I'm going to go through now and just set up if statements
to perform those operations.
So first one would be add so that's going to be the opCode a
so I'm going to say if and then opCode equals a,
so if the opCode is a, what I want to do in that case
is add the two numbers together and assigns a result.
So it's that simple.
So I've got the a in place now for add and I want to do
an s for subtract, so I'm just going to do an else if,
in this case opCode equals s and of course in that case
I'm just going to subtract value 2 from value 1
and we'll do the same thing for d for divide and
m for multiply.
Finally what we want to do is just print out the value
of result.
Notice here that throughout the program, the ID is
underlining all of my variables.
It's showing me that there must be something wrong.
And what it is is that we're trying to use all these
variables without having initialized them, right?
So what we need to do is go ahead and initialize them.
So let's go ahead and set val1 to 100 and val2 to 50.
So we've got those initialized.
Let's set our first opCode here, let's just make that
a for add.
So now we've got all the variables we're using initialized.
Right now we're going to assign result, but you know it's
possible that maybe we set the opCode wrong.
Instead of it being a proper value like a, s, d or m,
maybe we can actually put some like x or whatever.
So what I'll do is at the end of our else if, we'll add an
else, because if it's not any of the values we expect,
we're just going to get it to set the result to zero.
All right so now we have a very simple program in place
that we can actually set an opCode set two values and get
the result, so right now I'm set to add 100 plus 50.
So let's go ahead and run it.
And we display 150, so it did the math correctly.
Of course all I have to do now is change this from an a
to a d, and now it'll divide instead so if I run it,
I get two. 100 divided by 50 is two, so we're off to a good
start here.
Now we can make things a little better here.
We can get this bottom window out of the way.
Now when we have this bad opCode, just showing a result
of zero could be confusing, right?
So what we probably want to do is maybe put an error
message here, right?
So it's going to print out an error message that says,
"Error invalid opCode".
So now if we put in a bad value, it would actually just
display our message and make sure something useful
so I currently have a good value here, though.
The opCode is d so that's still fine.
Let's go ahead and run it and make sure everything's okay.
And you'll notice that when I ran it now, I didn't get the
proper answer, 2.0, I got zero, right.
And that's because I need to make this a block statement
with this else, because remember the else only ties to the
one line here.
So by actually adding this print statement here,
I'm forcing it to always result to zero, no matter what's
done before that.
So I'm going to make this a block statement and now
of course it'll do the right thing because it only sets
result to zero if we're inside the else block.
Of course now if I run it,
I get my 2.0 displayed again.
Okay, now one other thing.
We're still exposed in our divide to a divide by zero.
So a good programming practice of course is to always
check to see if the bottom value, the divisor, is zero.
So what I'm going to do here is say that if val2 is not
equal to zero, then in that case I'll do the division.
Otherwise, I want to set the result equal to zero.
So now if I run it, leaving val2 as 50,
it displays 2.0 but if I change val2 to be zero and run it,
now I get the zero, so it's doing the right thing.
Now one thing to note here is that in the if statement like
this where you simply do a condition and then set a result
to one thing or another, that's a great time to use that
conditional assignment I do.
So what I can do here is instead of that if else like that,
I can simply say result equals val2 not equal to zero
and if it's not equal to zero then go ahead and divide
val1 by val2, otherwise return zero.
So that one line replaces all of this.
So I'm going to go ahead and comment that out.
So now if I run it, it still runs correctly.
It shows zero because val2 is zero.
I change val2 back to 50, run it again.
It's now 2.0 and one thing to note here is that
it appears that we have multiple lines under this else if
for opCode equals d, but remember that those last four lines
are commented out, so it's still treated as if there's only
one line under the else if, so we didn't need to make
that a block statement but a situation like this where
I've got code hanging around that can be confusing
because it just makes it seem odd that I've got all
these statements there and they all seem to apply to the
else if, it's often useful to go ahead and use a block
statement, just to make your code more readable.
So what I'm going to do is put this in a block.
Even though it's not necessary for the program to run
correctly, it makes the program much more readable.