Let's take a look now at the three basic ways to write loops in Java.
First is a while loop, then a do-while loop and then the for loop.
The while loop is really the simplest way to write a loop.
It allows you to just repeatedly execute some statement
as long as the condition is true.
The while is structured so the condition is checked at the
start of the loop, so basically use the while keyword.
We have our condition, and then we have the statement
we want to repeatedly execute.
Now because the condition is checked at the start
of the loop, it's possible that the statement never executes.
Let's look at an example.
Let's write a simple bit of code that we'll use to do a
factorial function.
Factorial's just you multiply a number times each number
below it, right?
So five times four times three times two times one,
that sort of thing.
So we set it up with our while and we want to say that
our value, kval, is greater than one.
So kval starts out at five and we're going to keep inside
this loop as long as kval is greater than one and then say
our factorial is equal to itself times kval.
So the first time into this loop, our factorial is one.
kval is five, so factorial becomes five, right?
Five times one.
Then we reduce kval by one, kval minus equals one,
making kval four now.
It goes back up to the while statement,
so now it checks four is greater than one.
Do the factorial times kval, so now that's five times four
is 20, kval becomes three, we go back to the loop, right?
Three's still greater than one.
Factorial is 20 times three, which is 60.
kval becomes two, two's still greater than one.
Factorial then is 60 times two, 120.
kval now decrements down to one, then we check our
while loop, one is not greater than one, so it falls
through and then it would print out the value 120.
Notice we're using a block statement here in our while loop.
The while loop itself will only execute one statement unless
you put it in a block.
To give you an example of that, there's a way we can
actually write this same code to do the work without
using a block statement.
If we set this up, again kval is five, factorial is one.
We do our loop, kval greater than one and then the statement
we execute is simply factorial times equals kval minus minus
the decrement operator.
In this case we're now performing the exact same work,
but we didn't have to use a block statement because
now we can just go ahead and print it out.
So repeatedly execute that factorial times kval
minus minus, until kval gets down to one.
Another form of loop is a do while loop.
The do while loop repeatedly executes a statement
as long as the condition is true, but unlike the while
loop, it checks the condition at the end of the loop.
So we look at the layout for it.
We have the do keyword, the statement we want to execute,
the while keyword, and then the condition.
Now because it checks the condition at the end of the loop,
the body of the do while always executes at least once.
So let's see some code here.
If I set this up and I have some integer value
iVal, set to five.
Put my do in place, now I'm going to execute multiple
statements so I'm going to set up a block.
Then inside of here I'm going to go ahead and print out
iVal, you'll notice now, most time up until now, we've
called Print Line, println, in this case we call it just
print, and what that does is when we print the value out,
it prints it and doesn't go to a new line.
So now if I print out, after that, star two equals, it'll
actually put that on the same line.
So now I go ahead and calculate iVal times equals two,
which now makes iVal 10.
When I print line that, now I get 10 displayed.
The next thing I print will be on a new line,
so I'll go ahead and close my loop here.
Now I can just kind of walk through this loop over and over again.
The last thing I need to do of course is include the
condition, so I'm going to stay in this loop as long as
iVal is less than 100, so we know currently iVal is 10,
so the next pass through the loop, it's going to print out
10 times two equals twenty, so iVal's now 20, so less than 100.
20 times two is 40, 40 is still less than 100.
40 times two is 80, 80 is still less than 100.
Now 80 times two equals 160, but now iVal is now not less
than 100, it's greater than 100, 160, so our code ends.
Now the key difference here from the while loop is that
it will always execute at least once, right?
So if I initialize iVal, instead of being five, do something
like 150, it will still go through the loop one time,
printing out 150 * 2 = 300
The last of the basic loops we're going to look at here is
the for loop, just like the others it repeatedly executes
a statement as long as a condition is true and the
condition is checked at the start of the loop, right?
Very much like the while loop and really what it is is the
for loop is where the convenience layout for a while loop.
Let's look at a very common while loop behavior.
So if we want to set up a while loop the first thing we do
is initialize some value, in this case it's iVal, then that
while loop we would check the condition, in this case
iVal less than 100.
We would then do some work inside that loop
like print something out.
And then we would update our loop control variable.
All right, we would actually, in this case, times equals two
that's something we do very, very frequently so the for
loop provides a simplified notation for this scenario.
We use the for loop, the for keyword, then within the
parenthesis, we initialize things, we have our condition for
being in the loop and we have a place to update the
loop control and then of course that executes our statement.
So to see an example of that we start out with our for
keyword, in the parenthesis we do the initialization
iVal equals one.
We have our condition, iVal less than 100.
Notice that each of these sections are separated by a
semicolon, and then we have our update,
iVal times equals two, and then in the body of the loop,
we print out iVal.
So this while loop and the for loop both do the exact same thing.
The for look just makes that standard behavior of
initialization, condition, and update a bit more simplified.
Just as all the loops, if you want to actually execute
multiple statements, you can put it in a block.
So just here for notation we can have an opening bracket
and a closing bracket and we can put as many statements inside there as we need to.