Arrays are a really important part of Java.
Their formal definition is that they provide ordered collection of elements.
What that really means is that they allow us to store
multiple values of a common type under a single name.
So if we do something like float, theVals, but you notice
that we've got that square bracket right after float,
that indicates that we're declaring theVals as an array.
So that allocates out a name now, again, access an array,
and then we use this keyword new and then float three.
What this says is actually, "Allocate space to store three "float values."
And they're all accessible under this one name, theVals.
Now each of the members or elements of the array are
accessed through an index and the index is zero-based,
so basically the indexes run from zero to one less than
the number of elements, so in this case, we'd have our
first one as zero, then one, then two.
So using that, we can now put values in and get the values from the array.
So if I say theVals subzero equals 10, that stores 10
in the zero's position.
Then theVals sub one is 20, puts 20 in the one position.
And then theVals sub two is 15, puts 15 in the number two position.
So that's how we want to do something like go through this
array and add everything up, well if we're going to add them
up, we'll allocate some space to store the result, called sum.
The beauty of arrays is it makes it very easy to move
through these values using loops.
And one of the questions of course is, we have to know
how many spaces to walk through.
Well arrays expose a value called length to tell us
how many elements are in there so I can write a loop
like for int i equals zero as long as i is less than
theVals.length, well that will walk through each element as
long as I increment i by one each time as we've done here.
So I can sum up the values in this array by simply
sum plus equals theVals sub i, each pass of this loop
I'll go through a different element, the zero first and
then the number two element and then I can of course
print out that sum.
Now you notice here that this process of allocating the
array and initializing it is pretty cumbersome, right?
It takes a lot to do that and that's something we might
want to do very often in a program, so Java makes it very
easy to create a shorthand for that is that after we declare
the array name, you can use an open bracket, and just list
the values and enclose it and that has the same effect.
It automatically allocates the right number of spaces,
in this case, three, and initializes a value in each one of those spaces.