One of the most convenient ways to walk through the
members of an array is the for each loop, also known as the
enhanced for loop and what it does is takes care of just
executing that loop or the statement within the loop once
for each member in the array.
Basically, it's just the for keyword, and we have
parenthesis, but rather than having an explicit conditions
or array initializations, we actually just put the array in
there, preceded by a colon and then we declare a variable
to hold an individual array member, and then we can walk
through the body of our loop, we'll go through once for each
member of the array.
And it takes care of handling the details of getting the
length of the array as well as accessing each of the values.
Later in the course we'll see that a for each loop can also
work with other special data types other than arrays,
but of the types we've talked about so far, arrays are
the only thing that works with it.
Now to see it in action, imagine we have this scenario
again where we've got an array of values, in this case
we've got three values: 10.0, 20.0 and 15.0, and we
want to sum them up, just like we've done before.
Well, rather an array than the explicit for loop, where we
set up an index variable, incremented it ourselves, keep
testing its condition, with the for each loop, you can just
set up the for, say that, "Well, I know that array has
"floats in it."
Add the colon, and then we have theVals.
We simply have the array name there.
And now inside the body of our loop here, we can simply say,
sum plus equals currentVal
and what'll happen is that the first time through that loop,
currentVal will have a value of 10.0, which would make
sum 10.0, next time we come around the loop, currentVal
will have a value of 20.0, making our sum 30.0, next time
through the loop, currentVal will have a value of 15.0,
making our sum 45.0 so we would print out 45.0.