Switch transfers control to a particular statement based
on the value and really what its purpose in life is is to
simplify the idea of testing against multiple matches.
So we set up the switch keyword, you put in the value
you want to test.
This is not a condition; it's the value you want to test.
And then you go through inside a set of brackets, the word
case and the different values you want to match against
and then the statement you want to run if it matches against
that value, then the word case again and another value you
want to match against, and those statements.
Repeat that as many times as you like.
Now of the primitive types we talked about, only char
and integers can be used with a switch.
Later in the course we'll learn other types that may
work with a switch, but of those we've talked about so far,
only char and integer types can be used.
One thing to note is that a match can execute more than one statement.
Notice that under the case there, I don't have the word
statement, I have statements, plural.
But you can list many statements underneath of that
case keyword, and in fact the way a switch works is that
once it matches against a case, it will keep running all the
statements from below that case all the way to the end
of the switch statement.
So we have to use the break keyword to prevent what
we call falling through and that's falling through from
one case to the next.
We'll see an example of that in the next slide.
Now in addition to matching against specific values,
we can also put in a default keyword if we want which'll
handle any unmatched values and all we do is we put that at
the end of the switch.
We use the keyword default followed by a colon and any
statements we want to run there.
So let's see an example of using switch.
So we have some code here and we have an integer field,
iVal, which is set to 10.
And in our switch, I'm going to put iVal modulus two,
which says take iVal, divide it by two, and give me
back the remainder.
Well, if you divide a whole number by two, it's always
going to be either zero or one, right?
So it's a great way to just test if a value is odd or even.
So what I'll do here is I'll have a case for the value is zero, right?
So all even numbers will have a value of zero,
so I'll print out that, whatever the value is, is even.
I'm also going to put in a case for one, so that would
be our odd values, and then I'll go ahead and put a
default in place, and I'll say, "Oops, it broke" because
we should certainly never see this, the value of this
default, because all whole numbers are either going to be odd or even.
So if we run this code now, it'll go through, it will
say 10, we'll divide it by two, the remainder will be zero,
so it'll match the case for zero, so if I run it, it'll
actually print out "10 is even" but what would happen
then, it would then print out "10 is odd" and then
"oops it broke" because what's happening is that once
it matched on that case of zero, it's now running all the
statements below that, so all those different print lines are being run.
The way we prevent that is with the break keyword.
So what we can do is that at the end of each case block,
or each case section, we'll put in the keyword break,
which says, "Run until you reach this point and then jump
"out of the switch statement."
So we'll do that for our case of one, and we're also going
to do that even for the default.
The default is the last section, so technically you don't
need to have a break there, but it's considered good
programming practice, especially useful for situations
like if you refactor your code and that default becomes
an actual case or something later, so it's just a good
programming practice for each of those sections to put
a break at the end.
So now if we run this, we'll take our 10, and 10 mod two
is zero, matches on the zero, and it prints out just the "10 is even".
We take that iVal there, and say we change it to something
like 25, well now we run it, 25 mod two is 1, it'll match on
that, and it prints out that "25 is odd".