Let's revisit our CalcEngine demo and now we'll actually
add arrays in a loop so that rather than processing one
value at a time, you can process multiple values.
We'll also use a switch statement to take that complex
if else we have in there and make it much cleaner.
To update our program to process multiple values at a
time, what we'll do is we'll take each of these four
declarations at the top and convert them into arrays.
So we'll take the first one, so our first one there, val1,
let's make that a double array, and instead of calling it
val1, we'll call it leftVals, and then we'll initialize it
with say four values, so we have that.
So now what we'll do is we'll replace val2 with something
called rightVals and we'll initialize it with the same
number of values, and now we'll have opCode, instead of
calling it opCode, we'll call it opCodes, so this will be a char array.
So now we have each of those initialized with four values,
and of course we want to store those in our result,
and we'll do that as an array, so we'll make our result
a double array as well.
In this case, I'm calling it results, plural, because it can hold multiples.
Now I don't want to initialize this one with a value, right?
I want to initialize it with space to hold the different
results, so what I'll do is use the new and say double,
and when I put the size, I can set it as a fixed size of
four, but really I want it to kind of be the same size
as opCodes is, so what I'll do is I'll use opCodes.length
and that now sets me up with the results being the same
size as opCodes, and what we have here is these four
arrays are what we call parallel arrays and that idea
is that when you set up multiple arrays where the first
value in each one works together, the second value in each
one works together and so forth, right, so we'll have 100
from leftVals, we use with 50 from rightVals, we'll use the
d from opCodes, then store that in the very first position
in our results array.
So I'm just going to comment that out, these other ones
here, the ones we're not using anymore.
Okay, so they're all gone, now what I want to do is loop
through these values and use them, right?
So because I'm using the same position from each one
of these, I'm going to use a for loop where I actually
increment an index, and I use that same index for each one
of the arrays, so we're going to set up a for.
I'll just say int i equals zero.
I'll run while i is less than opCodes.length
and then I'll want to increment i each time.
I want to include the whole if statement under here, so I'm
going to go ahead and put brackets around that.
Now I need to go through and update each one of these,
so instead of saying opCode, I'm going to use opCodes sub i.
So we compare that against a, and then of course result
will be results sub i, and that's going to equal
leftVals sub i plus rightVals sub i.
I'm going to do the same thing for the opCode of s.
Now when we get to d for the divide, initially that's the
same, right?
opCode sub i, but now we just want to make sure that we
change everything we need to, because we actually check val2
as well as use it, so we want to make sure we make val2
under rightVals sub i throughout this whole thing, and of
val1 is leftVals, and of course our result is results.
So now we have our results sub i equals rightVals sub i
not equal to zero then it's leftVals sub i divided by
rightVals sub i, otherwise it's zero.
Then we get down here to our opCode m, it's going to be
just like it was with a and s and then the last thing is
just to make sure that our else statement uses results sub i.
All right, so now we have our for loop here set up to go
through each one of the arrays, execute the operation,
store the value in results, so now that we've done that,
let's go ahead and set up another loop to print out the results.
Now in this case, what I want to do is just go through
that results array, and I'm using just that one array
in this case, so this is a great time to use the for each
statement, so I'll just say for double the result colon,
and then I'll just say results and I can update this
print statement down here to use the result.
If I want to get fancy, I can go ahead and make this guy
a block statement.
And maybe I'll print out something like result equals.
All right, so we have that all set, so let's go ahead and
run it, make sure it works.
And we go through and we get our values out, right?
And so we've got our values of 2.0, 117, 208, and 33.
If I go up here, 100 divided by 50 is two,
25 added to 92 is 117,
225 minus 17 is 208 and 11 times 3 is 33.
So it works just fine.
So now let's go in here and take a look where we have this
if statement, we have this big if else here.
This is a perfect example of a good time to use the switch statement.
If we're checking opCodes sub i each time each time,
exactly what switch is meant for.
And what I'm going to switch on is opCodes sub i.
We're going to put brackets at the end of the switch.
I'm going to put it down here at the end of this else.
We got a lot of errors showing up here, but we'll go ahead
and clean that up.
So what I want to do here now is that in each one of these
ifs, that becomes a case statement, right?
So here for a, I'm just going to make this case.
Jump to the end and take that last parenthesis,
make that a colon.
Do the same thing for s,
as well as d and m.
And then where we have our else here, we're going to go
ahead and make that the default.
And we end up with an extra bracket here because that's
left over from the old else block that was here, so we'll take that off.
So now we have this set up to use a switch statement,
so we come through and check opCodes sub i,
and we say, case, well if it's a, do the add,
case s, do subtract, d is divide, of course m is multiply.
If they don't match up, we print out our error message
and set result to zero.
Let's go ahead and run this.
Notice what happens, we see that error message invalid
opCode print out each time and result is set to zero each time.
That's because we're falling through our case statements.
Remember that once there's a match, it then runs all the
statements after it, so in the case of when a matched, it
ran the proper instruction of adding them but then it
dropped down to the s and ran the subtraction, dropped
down to the d, ran the divide, dropped down to the m, ran
the multiply and then dropped down to the default, print
the error message, so what you do here is you go to each
one of these, and add a break statement.
So we now have our break statement for all the cases, and
scroll down, let's go ahead from just a good style stand
point and add a break to the default as well.
So now when we go ahead and run this, we get
the right answers again, because the break made sure we
only ran the code we wanted to run and then broke out of the switch statement.
And so now we have our application enhanced quite a bit
here: we can process multiple values, it's much more
readable with the case statement, so we're definitely moving
forward and making this a much richer application.