We covered a ton of stuff in this module.
Let's take a look at some of the highlights.
Remember that we used the if else statement to provide
conditional logic in our applications, that relied on things
like relational operators and logical operators and remember
that we can chain if else's together if we need to work
through multiple possibilities.
We rely on block statements a lot.
They use brackets to group statements together,
so they're really key for working with things like the if
statement or the loops.
Remember, though, that any variable declared inside of a
block is not visible outside of that block.
Both the while and the do while loops execute as long as
a condition is true.
The difference is when they test a condition.
While checks at the beginning, do while checks at the end,
as a result do while loops always execute their body at
least once.
The for loop provides a simplified notation for dealing with
loop initialization and control.
The for each statement goes even further because it
handles all the details of executing the body of the loop
once for each member of an array.
And then finally the switch statement is really useful for
those scenarios where you want to test against multiple possible matches.
Remember though that, of the primitive types we've talked
about, it can only be used with char and integer types.