Adding conditional logic is one of those
simple things we do in our programs,
but they're really central to them behaving well.
When we talk about adding conditional logic,
all we're saying is that our program will behave
differently based on differences in data values.
And there are four things we need to understand to do this.
One is relational operators that give us
the ability to test different values.
Something called conditional assignments, which allows
us to assign values differently based on conditions.
The if statement, which allows us
to change our code path in our application.
And then logical operators, that allow us
to combine different conditions together.
Looking first at relational operators.
These allow us to test values against one another.
These are very familiar if you are coming from
any other programming language.
We'll just go through them quickly.
The first one is greater than.
Is the first value larger than the second value?
Look at an integer example, five is greater than four.
We get into character data values.
What this does is this uses
the different Unicode code points.
So if the code point is larger, then the
comparison is considered larger.
So c is greater than a
And there's no way to do a greater than with a Boolean.
Okay, then there's greater than or equal to,
which says that if they are the same
or the first one is larger.
Okay, so five is greater than or equal to four
but four is also is greater than or equal to four.
Because it's the same.
Our character ones,
c is greater than or equal to a
and a is greater than or equal to a.
Less than, is the first one less than the second one?
Four is less than five, a is less than c.
Less than or equal.
Four is less than or equal to five
and four is also less than or equal to four.
Now, we get to equal to.
Alright, now equal to is the equivalent,
or the value is the same, right?
We use two equal signs to do that, right?
So five is equal to five, and c is equal to c.
That makes sense.
When we get to the Boolean,
basically, they are equal if both sides are the same.
So, true is equal to true.
So that makes sense.
But also, false is equal to false, right?
So, if you have two false values compared for equal,
that resolves to true, because those values are the same.
And then finally, not equal to is simply, are they different?
Four is not equal to five, a is not equal to c,
and true is not equal to false.