A conditional assignment
allows us to assign a value to a variable
based on the result of some condition.
So if we look at setting up an assignment here.
We're actually going to divide things into multiple parts
where we have a question mark and a colon.
What that lets us do is have a condition,
and then when we test that condition,
if the condition is true we return the value
immediately after the question mark.
But if the condition is false,
we return the value after the colon.
So let's see that in action.
I have some simple code here
where I've got two variables, all right.
v1 is seven and v2 is five,
and now I set this up so that
my vmax equals v1 greater than v2.
So we're doing that condition.
We test that condition.
Is seven greater than five?
Since it is, vmax gets back the first value there,
the v1, which is a seven.
All right, it's a true value.
Look at another example.
I set this up where I have students as 30
and rooms as four.
Now if I say that students per room equals the condition
is rooms equal to zero?
Well if it was true we return zero,
but if it's false, which it is, we go into the equation
of dividing students by rooms.
So the value in students per room is 7.5,
the result of that equation.