The if else statement allows us to conditionally execute
another statement, so rather than just returning a value,
we can execute an actual statement.
Basically we start out with just the keyword if, followed by
parenthesis, and inside of those parenthesis, we add our
condition and then following that we add the statement we
want to execute if that condition is true.
If the condition was false we would just skip over that statement.
All right so to see that in action, I have some code here
where I have two variables.
v1 is 10, v2 is four.
I say if v2 is greater than v2, print out "v1 is bigger".
So basically it just evaluates that condition as long as
it's true, which in this case it is,
it prints out "v1 is bigger".
If statements can optionally have an else clause added
to them, which says, "What do you want to do if the
"condition is false?"
So if we put else, followed by whatever you want that
action to be on the false side.
So our code here, we're just going to say else, print out
"v1 is not bigger".
Oftentimes you'll have more than simply, if this condition
is true or it's false.
You may have multiple things you need to evaluate, so you
can actually chain if else statements together and when you
do that, the system will just keep evaluating them until one is true.
So we set that up with our regular if statement just like we
did before, followed by the else, but after the else we can
put another if and another condition, and if that condition
is true we have it's true statement.
And we can repeat this as many times as we want, all right?
We can have 20 or 30 of these in a row if we wanted to.
That probably wouldn't be good coding practice but it's
completely legal and you can optionally have just an else
at the end to say, "Well if none of those were true, what
"should I do in that case?"
So to see that in code, here we have our v1 is 10, v2 is 40.
We say, "Well if v1 is greater than v2,
"print out 'v1 is bigger' else if v1 is less than v2,
"print out 'v2 is bigger' and if neither of those are true,
"then print out 'v1 and v2 are equal'."
So in this case the system would first evaluate the
"is v1 greater than v2?"
It's not so it jumps on to that next condition,
"is v1 less than v2?"
Oh, it is, go ahead and print out "v2 is bigger".