Thinking about our if statements.
Remember we said that if our if statement conditionally
executes another statement, and if you think about it,
we never saw any kind of end if, or anything like that.
So how do we execute multiple statements conditionally?
Well that's where a block statement comes in.
A block statement groups individual statements into a
compound statement, so if we have a series of statements
that we want to group together what we can do is wrap
them in an opening bracket and a closing bracket and
that now makes them a compound statement and enables
them to be treated as a single statement.
So we look at this in code.
I have some code set up here where I've got v1 equals 10,
v2 equals four, and a variable diff.
And I say, "if v1 is greater than v2" and I put in
diff equals v1 minus v2, print out "v1 is bigger"
and then diff, the way this code is currently written,
the assignment of diff equals v1 minus v2 is conditional
on whether v1 is greater than v2 but their two print
statements there, v1 is bigger and diff, will print every
time because only the single statement of the assignment
of diff is tied to the condition, so that's where block
statements come in.
Putting an open bracket after the if and then a close bracket
after that print of diff.
Now that becomes a block statement and so the if now
condition is tied to those entire three statements.
Similarly I can do that with an else if.
All right, so I've got an else if v2 is greater than v1.
Although, by the way, I have my code indented, it looks like
all three of these statements, the diff assignment and the
two print outs are tied to that v2 is greater than v1,
currently only the diff assignment is tied to the condition.
Again, I need to put an open bracket and a closed bracket
to bring those into a block statement.
And then I add an else.
Now the thing to note is that block statements are kind
of independent from one another, right?
So if you have an if and an else if and an else, if you want
to have block statements on part of them, like I do on the
if and the else if, with just single statements on other
parts, like we do with the else, that's just fine.
Just one other thing I want to bring note to as well
in this code: notice the very first line of code.
I'm doing variable declarations in a way
I haven't done before.
Notice that on one line, I'm declaring multiple variables
of type int.
Normally in our other code we've done them
as individual lines, and I just wanted to show you here that
you can actually do multiple variable declarations on the
one line like that, so we're saying that v1 is an int that
has a value of ten initially, v2 is an int, has a value of
four initially and diff is an int that's not yet initialized.