Let's take a look at a demo where we nest one if statement
inside of another.
We have a simple program here where we have two variables
declared, students, which is set to zero, and rooms.
Next thing we want to do a very simple bit of code.
We're going to say if students is greater than zero,
if that's true, I want to print out the average number of
students in each room and then if students is not greater
than zero, I just want to get it to print out the fact that
there are no students.
Okay so that's pretty simple, right?
So let's go ahead and run it and when we run it
we get the message we expect, all right,
no students prints out, so that code's working well.
Now if we look at this code, you know, I realize that,
you know, I'm dividing students by rooms.
What would happen if rooms was zero?
Well just like in real mathematics, you can't divide by zero
well in Java, you can't divide by zero either.
All right, so if we were really going to be, you know,
good defensive programmers here, we would actually
check to make sure that rooms was not zero before we
actually tried to do this division, all right, so what I'm
going to do here is just add a line here that says, "Well,
"only do this if rooms is greater than zero."
So I've got that test in there.
Let's go ahead and indent this so that it matches up
with our style here of indenting underneath the ifs.
Let's go ahead and run this now.
And you notice that when we run it, we don't see our
no students message.
What happened? That worked before, why is it gone now?
Well, because the else is matching up to the closest if
to it, all right, so in this case, the else is matching up
to the test for rooms being greater than zero even though
we really want it to match up against
students greater than zero.
So how do we fix that?
Well we can use the block statement style.
What we can do is take the if here, put an open bracket
before it, and then another open bracket here, and now
that closes up that if block, right?
So that prevents the else from matching up to the if for
rooms; we've closed that if for rooms within a block
under the if for students, that way the else matches up
to the if that we want it to.
All right, so if I go ahead and run this now
our program now performs correctly, printing out the no students message.