Because we used these block statements, what happens
if we declare a variable inside of a block?
Well it turns out that variables that are declared inside
of a block are only visible within that block.
They're not visible beyond the scope of that block.
In fact, this idea of where are variables visible is known
as the variable scope.
Let's take a look at some code.
So I've got code set up here where I've initialized
students to 30 and rooms to four.
So I put an if statement in place where I want to just
make sure that rooms is greater than zero.
I open it up with my bracket, meaning I want to create a
block, so I have a closing bracket, the closed block.
And inside of that I print out students and rooms and
then I declare a float called average, which has a result
of students divided by rooms.
Now if I then, outside the if block, attempt to print out
average, I actually get a compile error, because once I
leave that block, average no longer exists.
But notice that variables can come into the block.
All right, I've got students declared before the block
started, and students is valid to use within the block.
Same thing is true for rooms.
So the way it works is that variables that are in scope
when the block starts remain
in scope, but variables that are created within the block
go out of scope at the end of the block.
So the way I would have to fix this code is
I would have to do one of two things.
I'd have to declare average before the start of the block,
so move it up before the if, or I can move the print
statement inside the block while average is still available.