Logical operators are useful for arriving at a true or false
value by operating on other things to provide true or
false values.
They could be Boolean variables or more commonly,
logical operators are used to work on the results of other
relational operations.
There are basically four fundamental logical operators.
And, or, exclusive or, and what we call negation.
And we look at this is that the and allows us to take
two things and resolve to true or false, and if both of
those are true, then the and returns true.
So we look at a little bit of code here.
If I have three variables declared, a, b, and c.
And I say, "If a is greater than b, and b is greater than c,
"print out 'a is greater than c'."
What this does is that, first we did the comparison
of a being greater than b, in this case it is, right?
20 is greater than 14, so a greater than b resolves to true.
Then we operate on b greater than c.
14 is greater than five; that resolves to true.
And then we add those two trues together and true
and true equals true.
So an and resolves to true only if both sides of it are
also true.
Then we have an or.
Or compares two sides and only one side needs to be
true, all right, so if the first one's false and the second
side is true, then that resolves to true.
If the first side is true and the second side is false,
that still resolves to true, and even if both sides are true
the or resolves to true.
Now that's different than the exclusive or.
In the exclusive or,
exactly one side needs to be true.
It can be false or true and then true or false.
In the case of the exclusive or, it just can't be
true or true.
And the last one is negation.
Negation basically reverses the result.
So basically, when you use negation, not false is true.
So we just look at that in code.
Got a little Boolean variable, done.
I say done is false.
Well if I go, if not done, print out "keep going".
When we look at done, done is false
but then the not of done, or the not of false, is true.
There are two special logical operators called conditional
logical operators.
There's a conditional and and a conditional or.
Now conceptually, these resolve the same way as the other
ands and ors we looked at.
The key difference, though, is that they only execute
the right side of their test if they need to do that to
determine the result.
So in the case of an and, all right, both sides have to
be true, so a conditional logical and only executes
the right side if the left side was already true.
All right, so if the left side was false, we know the and's
going to fail anyway, so there's no reason to even run
the right side of it.
In the case of the conditional logical or, it only executes
the right side if the left side is false, because if the
left side were true, in that case, we'd already know we
were done, so we wouldn't need to execute the right side.
So looking at the conditional and, we still need both
sides to be true for that to resolve to true, but
when doing a test, if the left side had resolved to false,
it would never even run the right side because we already
know the result of the and would be false.
Looking at the conditional or, the left side is false,
or that with a right side of true, that resolves to true.
If you do a conditional or and the left side is true,
it never even runs the right side because we already know
the result's going to be true.