Let's take a look at a demo comparing the behavior
of a logical and to that of a conditional logical and.
We have a simple program here where we have
two variables declared at the top,
students equals 150 and rooms equals zero.
And let's say I just want to put in a condition here
where I want to print out the message "crowded"
if there are more than 30 students to a room.
So I'm just going to run my if statement.
I'll just take students, divide that by rooms, and if that's
greater than 30 I'll go ahead and I'll print out my message.
So if the result of students divided by rooms
is greater than 30, I print out that crowded message.
Now of course one of the issues I have is that, what if the
rooms is zero, right, and you can't legally divide by zero.
So what I really want to say is, "Well, if rooms is greater
"than zero AND students divided by rooms is greater
"than 30, then I'll print out that message."
So what I'll do here, is just put in your rooms greater than
zero and then and students divided by rooms greater than 30.
All right, so that way we'll do both tests, right?
Rooms is greater than zero so we have valid division
and then the result of the division.
So let's go ahead and run this.
And notice what happens there, I'm getting an error message.
Because it's not legal to divide by zero.
Because what happened is that it first did rooms
greater than zero, now that tested to false, right,
because rooms is not greater than zero, but then it
tried to do the right hand side of the and as well.
It tried to do the students divided by rooms, which created
the error because you can't legally divide by zero.
But now, if I go ahead and change this to the double
ampersand, making it the conditional logical and, now
we'll only do the right hand side if the left hand side
was true, or conditionally, right?
It does the right hand side conditionally.
Now if I run it, I don't get the error message.
It ran successfully.
Now it didn't print the message out, right, because the
combined value of the test was false.
Rooms was not greater than zero, but we ran successfully.
So we were able to conditionally execute the right hand
side of the and based on the left hand side, so if the
left hand side had been true, we would have also run the
right hand side to see if it was true, but once the left
hand side was false, we never even bothered running the
right hand side.