A critical aspect of building a successful application is
good error handling.
If you build a program that doesn't have good error
handling, it doesn't matter how cool it is.
If it crashes all the time, no one's going to want
to use it.
So, we need to make sure that handling errors appropriately
is really kind of implicit in our application development.
Now, traditional mechanisms would use things like
error code that had to be checked, or flags that had to be
checked, and that's really intrusive, right?
Having to put if statements all over the place to deal with
potential errors really going to close up your code,
it's really kind of awkward, and very often, as developers,
we just kind of never get around to doing it.
So, we need a way that makes it really easy
to manage errors.
And that's where exceptions come in.
Exceptions provide a non-intrusive way to signal errors.
So, with exceptions, rather than actually having to check
for errors all of the time, we can write our code so that
we expect things to go well, but if an error occurs,
an exception is, what we call, thrown.
So when an exception's thrown, we can handle it.
And that's where try/catch/finally statements come in,
is that try/catch/finally provides a structured way for us
to handle exceptions.
The try portion of the statement contains all of
the normal code, it's the thing we expect to go well.
And, if all goes well, the try block will simply run
to completion, and nothing special will happen.
But, if there is an exception, control is then handed off
from the try block into a catch block.
So, our error code is all inside of a catch block,
and a catch block is only called in the event of
an exception being thrown.
And then, we have what's called a finally block,
and finally block is for those scenarios
where you need clean-up.
The finally block runs after your try block finishes or
after a catch block finishes.
So, if there's anything you want to have done after
the process is over, you put that in a finally block,
because it's assured to run, whether the try block finishes
completely, or the catch block had to step in
and deal with an error.
So, let's see what this looks like.
Let's look at a really simple case here.
So, I have a couple of integers declared here:
i has a value of 12, and j has a value of five.
And, all we want to do, is we're going to take the value
of j, subtract two from it, then divide that into i.
We'll store that in result, and simply print it out.
Alright, so in a real simple case we have here,
if j has a value of five, and subtract two from it, right,
of course, I have three.
So I divide 12 by three, I'll print out the value, four.
Right, very simple.
Now, let's make a really small change here.
Let's change j from a value of five to a value of two.
Well now, if I subtract two from two, I end up with
a value of zero.
It's not legal to divide by zero.
So, we're having in this code is that as soon as
I try to divide by zero, the program would just crash.
What we want to do is code our programs up so we can recover
from scenarios like this, and that's where
exceptions come in.
We can wrap this code up so that we can handle the exception
that occurs when we try to divide by zero.
So, we take our core code here, which is where we do
the math, and print it out, we wrap that in our try block,
and then, we add a catch block to it.
And, notice that the catch block receives an exception.
In the case of an error, that variable e will receive
a reference to the exception that describes
the error that occurred.
We can do a number of things with the exception.
The simplest thing we can do is we print out a message
that goes with it.
The getMessage method gives us back the appropriate message
for that exception, and, if we want to, we can even print
out a stack trace, showing exactly what went wrong.
Now, our program will continue running just fine from here.
But, if we didn't handle this exception when that
divide by zero happens, again, we would have crashed.
And, the user would have just been left
kind of wondering what happens.
But, in this case, because we have proper
error handling in place, when we try to take that zero
and divide it into i, that raises an exception,
so control was immediately passed from where
we try to do the arithmetic that failed,
to our exception block, and then,
we can simply print out the value of that exception,
the message for it, which says, Error, divide by zero.
And then, we would see the stack trace underneath of it.
So, that's really kind of our simplest try/catch scenario.
Let's look at a little bit more involved one.
Let's say we have a text file that has
a series of numbers inside of it, and we want to
go through and just total them up.
So, this text file, Numbers.txt, has the set of numbers
we want to get them add up.
Let's write some code to do that.
So, we're going to take advantage of one of the built-in
Java classes called BufferedReader.
And, BufferedReader provides an efficient way
to read content.
We'll also have a variable called total that'll hold
the total of the numbers that we add up.
So, go ahead and create an instance of our
BufferedReader, and notice your BufferedReader
uses a FileReader.
A FileReader is a built-in class that takes care of
the details of reading content from a file.
BufferedReader is something that adds some buffering
on top of that to make reading from a file more efficient.
It also provides some helper methods.
Another thing to notice here is that, when we identify
the name of the file, notice we're putting \\ in there,
in Java, back-slash is used to identify special
characters, so \\ says, No, I really want a \.
Now, when this is done, we have an instance of
our BufferedReader, with a reference to it assigned
into the variable reader, and then from there,
we going to declare a local variable called line.
It will hold a string.
And then, we'll put a while statement in place here that
actually reads from the BufferedReader.
So, a couple interesting things are going on here.
Notice that we're actually assigning to line directly inside
the while statement, right?
So, reader.readLine is defined to say, they will return back
a null when you hit the end of file.
So, we take whatever we get back from readLine,
assign that into line, and then we check line against null.
So, as long as line does not contain the value null,
we know we still have content.
So, here we're just going to say, total plus-equals,
and then we use of the primitive type wrapper classes,
Integer, and call its valueOf method to convert the string
contained in line into a number, right?
So, for the first line in our file, we would then be adding
in the number five into our total.
When the while loop completes, we'll go ahead
and print out our content.
And so, that's our core effort, that's what we're doing now.
We're reading from a file, getting each line from it,
converting it into its integer value, adding it to a total,
and printing it out.
Now, there's a lot of things that could go wrong here.
Maybe the file doesn't exist, maybe just some kind of
system error occurs when we try to read from the file,
maybe there's bad data in the file, someone put the letters
X, Y, Z in there instead of numbers, so that could go wrong.
So, there're a lot of things that could happen here.
So, we certainly want to wrap this into a try block.
We'll go ahead and put our catch block in here as well,
handle the exception, and we'll print out the error message.
But now, something to note here.
We've explicitly opened our file.
When you open up a file, you need to make sure
you close it when you're done.
And, we want to close the file whether the try block
completes without any problems, or, if an error occurs,
and we have to go to the catch block.
So, that's where finally comes it.
We put a finally here at the end, and we're going to
put inside of there is, reader.close.
So, we'll be sure to close the file whether we have
a problem or if everything completes fine.
Now, something to note here.
Notice that, when we declared BufferedReader,
we declared that before the try block, rather than declaring
it inside the try block.
The reason we did that is because we need to have access
to the variable reader down in our finally block.
Had we declared reader inside of the try block,
we wouldn't be able to see it in the finally block.
So, remember we talked about, earlier in the course, that,
when a variable is declared inside of a block,
it's not visible outside of that block.
So, that's why we declared that before the try block.
Now, another thing to note.
As we mentioned, there can be different kinds
of errors here.
So, if we run into a problem reading the file, if there's
bad data there or some error occurs in the process of
reading the file, our reader would still have a valid
reference to BufferedReader.
But, what if the file we identified there, Numbers.txt,
if it didn't exist?
Well, an instance of BufferedReader would have never been
created there, for reader would still be null.
So, one of the things we generally want to do inside of a
finally block is, any time we're going to clean up
a resource, make sure it actually has a valid reference.
So, we check reader, and make sure it's not equal to null
before we close it.
Now, another thing we have to think about.
The method reader.close is defined that it itself can
throw an exception.
Something could go wrong in the process of trying
to close that file.
So, we actually need to protect the close of the try/catch.
So, we can go ahead and wrap that up with a try block,
and then have a catch which will print out
that error message.
Now, chances are you're not going to run into a problem
closing the file, but it could have happened.
So, you see here that, this idea of try, catch and finally
can actually become pretty sophisticated, taking care of
a lot of different scenarios for us, but still allowing us
to keep our code very structured in how we deal
with each aspect of it.