As we introduced in the last clip,
errors are represented by exceptions.
Well, each exception is actually an object.
So, each exception type is described with a class.
Now, as with all classes, the root of the class hierarchy
for exceptions is the Object class.
When an exception occurs, it is thrown,
and, of course, you use catch to handle it.
Well, in order for a class to be able to be thrown,
it has to inherit from the base class, Throwable.
Now, one of the classes it inherits from Throwable
is the class, Error.
And there are a number of classes that, in turn,
inherit from Error, but any error that occurs,
that inherits from this class Error, is generally one
we don't have to think about too much in our code,
because it generally represents some kind of problem
directly inside the Java virtual machine.
So, because of that, we don't really handle those
very often.
An example of one of these might be like a linkage error.
A linkage error occurs when you try to load a class,
and it's not able to load that class up for some reason.
Now, the errors we tend to interact with much more
inherit from a class, Exception.
Now, one key class that inherits from Exception
is the class, RuntimeException.
And, there are many other classes that, in turn,
inherit from RuntimeException.
Generally speaking, those classes that inherit from
RuntimeException represent errors in your program,
not always but very commonly.
An example of one of those might be
a null pointer exception, right, so you're trying to use
a reference variable that you never assigned to, right?
So, that's kind of a programming error.
We'll see, though, that there are times that you do want
to handle certain runtime exceptions.
Now, the area where we work most commonly
are the classes that inherit more directly
from the Exception class.
And these are things we want to actually watch out for
in our programs.
An example here might be something like an IOException,
where you're trying to interact with a file
and you're not able to, something like that.
Now, these exceptions on this side here are so important
that we actually handle them correctly, they're considered
checked exceptions.
A checked exception means that the compiler actually looks
and anytime one of these exceptions is thrown,
the compiler looks to see if you actually handled it.
If you do not handle a checked exception,
the compiler will raise an error, in other words,
it won't let you build your program.
So, you have to handle all checked exceptions.
Now, the exceptions here under RuntimeException
are considered, unchecked exceptions, meaning that,
you can handle them but the compiler doesn't require that you do.
So, even if the compiler knows that it's possible
for that exception to be thrown, if you don't handle it,
it's not going to raise an error.
The way you can tell a unchecked exception from a
checked exception: any exception class that inherits from
RuntimeException is considered an unchecked exception.
Any class that inherits from Exception
but not RuntimeException is considered a checked exception.
Now, the virtual machine-related errors, those are treated
as unchecked exceptions, in other words, the compiler
does not require that you handle those.
Now, with exceptions being typed, what that means is that,
in our code, we can actually handle exceptions by type.
So, when we have our try statement, we can have
multiple catch blocks, which each catch block
handling a different kind of exception.
When an exception occurs, Java environment
will start testing your catch blocks starting at the top
and walking down each one.
The first catch block that it encounters that is assignable
for this exception is used.
And what we mean by assignable is that the catch block
handles an exception that is either
the type of the exception thrown,
or the base class of the type of exception thrown.
Now, because a base class can satisfy the catch statement,
we want to make sure our catch blocks start with
the most specific exception types first,
and get more general as we go down.
Now, to see this in action, let's take a look at the code
we wrote in the last clip.
Now remember that, what we do here is that we're reading
data from a file, and then we're simply totaling it up.
But in order to do that, we have to open the file,
we have to read each line in the file, we have to convert
each line from a string into a numeric value.
And so, there's a number of things that can go on there.
Let's focus in on the catch statement itself here,
so let's go ahead and just kind of move the const,
the try and the finally out of our way
so we can see the catch statement.
Now, right here, we catch exception,
but that's a very general handling.
Remember we said, that one of the things that might happen
is that, if there's bad data in the file,
and we try to convert it to a number,
that could throw an exception.
That actually throws a NumberFormatException.
So, we'll say we want to handle that guy.
So, I'm going to add a catch in for NumberFormatException.
Now, of course, the problem here is that, because
NumberFormatException inherits from Exception,
we'll never reach the catch block for NumberFormatException.
Now, there are times in my code where I handle
Exception directly, but that's not very common.
So, let's go and just get that guy out of the way there.
So, now we have our NumberFormatException.
So, if that happens, we will catch it, but, of course,
we won't catch any other exceptions.
Alright, so let's go ahead and just move that up
a little bit, we've got some room here now
to handle some other exceptions.
But, let's look at the tree hierarchy of the exceptions
that might happen here.
Now, we're now looking at the NumberFormatException.
Now, that's going to inherit up through some other classes
up to RuntimeException, which, of course,
inherits from Exception.
Now, notice that NumberFormatException inherits from
RuntimeException, mean that it is an unchecked exception.
So, the compiler doesn't require that I handle this one.
But, even though the compiler doesn't require it,
I know it might actually happen in my code,
so I'm going to go ahead and catch it anyway.
Now, other exceptions might happen, or things like
IOException, where I have a problem interacting with a file,
and there might even be a FileNotFoundException,
if I try to open a file that doesn't exist.
So, to deal with these exceptions, I can add in
a catch block for the IOException, I'll just write out
the error message there, and that would satisfy any problems
interacting with the file, as well as
the inability to open the file.
But, you know, not finding a file is
a pretty specific issue, much more so that just some kind of
general error interacting with the file.
So, in this case, I want to go ahead and handle
FileNotFoundException in addition to IOException.
Now, the important thing is that I put that before the
IOException, so, in that case, when I encounter
a file not found, I can just write out the fact that,
Hey, you know, that file wasn't there, as opposed to
a general file issue message.
And so, as we set up our exception handling, again the key
thing is to understand that the, use a type hierarchy as we
do this, and you want to handle your most specific
exceptions first, getting more general from there.