So far, we've been looking at how exceptions work within
a specific block of code.
Let's look now how they work when we call down
from multiple methods.
Let's say we have a method here, we'll call it methodA,
and methodA does some work, and, as we know,
whenever we use methods in a computer program,
it works with a stack, alright?
So, methodA gets a spot on the stack,
and it takes up some space on that stack.
Let's say, methodA calls methodB, and let's go ahead
and wrap up that call to methodB in a try/catch block.
So now, of course, we're going to have methodB's
implementation, which does some work.
So, again, it's going to get a spot on the stack
and take up some space there.
So then, methodB calls methodC, right, methodC again
does some work, gets a spot on the stack,
takes up some space, again, D does the same thing.
So, let's say now we're down here inside of D,
and D does something that throws an exception, alright?
So, now that exception occurs, and now something
has to try to handle that exception.
So, what happens is, the system starts trying to see
if it can be handled.
Since methodD doesn't handle it, it went to start looking
up the call stack to find some code that can actually
handle this exception.
Well, remember here in methodA,
we put that try/catch in place.
Well, that catch puts a marker on the stack.
So, what happens now is that Java looks up the call stack,
and when it finds that marker, it says,
Oh, you can handle this exception.
The call stack is cleaned up, and then, control is passed
to that catch block.
So, that means then, of course, that exceptions propagate up
the call stack, meaning that they can actually
cross method boundaries.
So, the question is that, how could methodA know
it had to be responsible to catch an exception
that occurred all the way down in methodD?
Well, in Java, the exceptions that a method throws
are actually part of that method's contract, just like
its return type would be, or the list of parameters
it accepts.
So, in Java, a method is responsible for
any checked exceptions that might occur.
And, it basically has two choices for dealing with them.
One is, it can catch the exception,
but it doesn't have to catch the exception.
But, if it doesn't catch the exception,
then it must document that that exception might occur.
The way that's documented is that a method can have
a throws clause on it, and that throws clause needs to list
any checked exceptions that might occur within that method
that it doesn't handle.
Let's look at some code and get a sense of how that works.
So, let's think about our Flight class.
Let's say we want to add some functionality
to our Flight class that allows passengers
to be added from a text file.
So, the format of our text file will be that,
the first thing on each line is the number of people
in a given party, a space, and then a name associated
with that party.
So, we'll have our Flight class here, and remember,
we have our passenger's field.
I'm going to add a method on here called, addPassengers.
This implementation of addPassengers accepts
a string parameter which is the filename to read
the passenger information from.
So, whoever calls this method is going to pass in
the name of the file they want us to read
the passenger information from.
The code we use to deal with this passenger information
is going to be very similar to the code we used earlier
to total up the numbers from inside of a file.
So, we're going to need a BufferedReader, so go ahead
and create an instance of that BufferedReader, that wraps
a FileReader that uses the filename that was passed in.
We need a variable to hold each line that's read in,
and all we have to do is, read in each line.
Now since there's two values on each line,
and we want the number of people in the party,
we're going to use the split method on the string
to go ahead and get that first field, and then we use
our integer.valueOf to convert that initial value
from a string into an integer, and simply add it
to our number of passengers.
Now, we know from the work we did earlier,
totaling up values inside of a file, that exceptions
can be thrown in this code.
Now, in this case, we don't want to catch them.
We certainly could catch them here,
but it probably makes sense that those exceptions
propagate up to the caller, because that filename
came from the caller.
So, if there's anything wrong with it,
they might know what to do with it based on the exception.
So, rather than catch the exception here,
we're going to document that it gets thrown.
So, on our method declaration here, we're going to add
a throws clause, and we say, throws IOException.
Now, the reason we know that we throw an IOException
is because, if we were to look, the FileReader constructor
is documented to throw a FileNotFoundException,
and the BufferedReader readLine method has
a throws that says it throws an IOException.
And, since a FileNotFoundException is also
an IOException, we can simply say, throws IOException.
And again, the key thing here is that, if we didn't catch it
and we didn't put the throws on, the compiler would
actually complain that we weren't dealing
with the exception.
So, by saying that we throw it,
that's our responsibility in dealing with it.
Now, we have another thing we have to think about.
We process this file, but we've opened it up,
there's nothing to close it.
Now, we want to make sure that file gets closed
whether we succeed or not.
But, we don't want to actually handle any errors.
But, we can still use try to make sure the file gets closed.
We can wrap this code up in a try,
and then, put the finally afterwards which closes the file.
Now this way, if we go through and process everything
and we succeed, then, the finally will run and it'll close.
Also, if we go and process things and an exception occurs,
the finally will still run, close the file,
and then, let the exception call up the call stack.
Now, since exceptions are part of a method's contract,
how does that work when one class overrides
a method from another class?
Well, when you override a method, the throws clause
of the overriding method must be compatible
with the throws clause of the method being overridden.
So, say, for example, we have our CargoFlight class
that extends Flight, and it wants to override that
new addPassengers function we just put in there.
Well, it need to be compatible with the throws clause
of Flight's implementation of addPassengers.
Now, there are three ways to be compatible.
One is to simply not throw the exceptions, and so our method
as it's written right now with addPassengers
is considered compatible, because we're not generating
any exception that wasn't already defined in the base class.
And, we can also have a throws clause that throws
the same exception, so if we say on the end here,
throws IOException, that's compatible as well, because it's
the same thing as the base class said.
But, we can also indicate that we throw a derived exception,
so, for example, FileNotFoundException derives from
IOException, therefore it's okay for us to say,
throws FileNotFoundException.
Alright, and the reason this makes sense is because
we have to be compatible with our base class, right?
Because, remember that, somewhere there might be code
that has a reference to an instance of
our CargoFlight class, but might be using
a variable declared as Flight, right?
So, that code would only know about the capabilities
of addPassengers as implemented in Flight.
So, any try/catch they put in place there,
they're going to catch the exceptions that are defined on
Flight's implementation of addPassengers.
We want to make sure that our derived class
doesn't start throwing exceptions that the user of our class
didn't know they were responsible to handle.