In addition to being able to handle exceptions,
as we've done up until now, our code can actually
throw exceptions as well, and that would just be in any case
where we want to signal that an error had occurred.
So, we might throw an exception because our code has
identified something wrong with the data we're working on,
or it might even be that our code has caught an exception
and wants to throw a different exception
to provide more information.
Now, the way we throw an exception is quite easy,
we simply use the throw keyword and to provide an instance
of the exception we want to throw.
Now, remember that, exceptions are objects, so they have to
be created before they can be thrown.
So, we just create them with the "new" keyword,
and one of the most important things to remember when
throw exceptions is that you want to be sure
that you provide meaningful detail.
We want to make it easy for whoever has to handle
this exception to be able to figure out what was wrong.
Now, most exception classes provide a constructor
that accepts a string message or some other detail.
So, you want to make sure you put
as much meaningful information into that as you can.
Now, as we said, sometimes we'll throw an exception
because our code caught an exception,
and we want to add some more information to it.
Well, in that situation, you want to always make sure that
your new exception that you throw includes
the original exception, you don't want to lose that detail.
This idea of tying one exception to another is
very fundamental to the exception classes.
All the exception classes have a method called,
initCause, that will allow you to associate an exception
with an instance of another exception.
This idea of associating exceptions together is
so fundamental that many exception classes actually provide
a constructor that will accept the other exception, so you
can actually create the new exception
and associate the original, all in one step.
Now, in most cases when you're throwing an exception,
you're going to want to throw
one of the existing exception types.
But, it is possible to create your own custom
exception types, and throw those as well.
Now, to really (speaks too fast), in most cases,
you're going to want to use
one of the existing exception types.
But, if you really have a situation where you've got
something you need to provide information on
that doesn't really fit one of the existing exceptions,
you can define your own.
But again, that's going to be one of these situations where
you've got some real information, some real value to provide
that you can't with the existing exception types.
Now, if you do define your own custom exception type,
you're generally going to inherit from the Exception class.
But, that has an interesting implication.
Remember that any exception that inherits from
the Exception class, but not the RuntimeException class,
is a checked exception.
So, exceptions you define will become checked exceptions.
The process of implementing a custom exception type is
generally pretty easy.
In fact, very often, the only members
that your exception type will have will be constructors.
And the reason for that is that, most of the required
functionality is inherited.
The base classes have the ability for you to associate
a string message and have the receiver of the exception
access that message.
The bass class provides things like stack traces,
so you generally don't need to provide a lot more than that.
I mean, there may be some situations where there's some
extended error detail you might want to add.
In those cases, you might have some additional
getter methods to access those,
but there's not going to be a lot of that.
Now, when you define your custom exception type,
you'll generally want to have at least two constructors.
You'll have one constructor that accepts
whatever the required detail is.
That may be a simple string message,
it may be some meaningful fields.
You'll generally also want to have another constructor
that accepts that same detail along with
an originating exception, again, so that,
if this exception's thrown in response to
a different exception, they can be tied together.
And, you could, of course, have more constructors, then,
if you want to.
You can have a no-argument constructor,
you can have whatever you need,
but you'll generally have at least these two.
Now, in the next clip, we'll take a look at
how we can actually define a custom exception in code,
and how we actually throw it.