In this demo, we'll add exceptions to our CalcEngine app.
We'll create a custom exception class, which will then throw
in cases where we find we have invalid data, and then,
of course, we'll add a try/catch block to our app
to handle those exceptions.
Here we are in the source code for our CalcEngine app,
and the app's exactly as we left it at the end
of the last module, except I've added
three statements for us to process.
Remember that each statement we process is supposed
to have three parts: a command, and then the two numbers
we want to operate on.
Well, each of these three statements I've added
have a different problem.
The first statement contains only two parts, the command
and a single numeric value instead of having two values.
The second statement has non-numeric data, the xx.
And then, the third statement I added has
an invalid command, addX.
So, what we want to do is update the app so that we can
properly handle this invalid data.
So, the first thing we'll do is,
add our own custom exception class.
So, I'm going to create a class, just like I always do,
because, remember, exception classes are just classes.
And, let's call this the InvalidStatementException.
And we'll say, OK.
Now, remember that, all of our exception classes
will generally extend the class, Exception,
so let's go ahead and do that.
And, as I mentioned in the previous clip, in most cases,
any custom exceptions really only have constructors
inside of them, right?
So, let's go ahead and add a public constructor for this.
And this constructor will take two arguments:
the reason that the statement is invalid,
and the statement itself.
So, they'll both be string parameters, and then,
all we need to do here is go ahead and call
our super-class constructor.
So, say super.
And when the super-class constructor accepts a string,
which is a message, so what we'll do is we'll take
these two parts, the reason and the statement,
and combine them into a single message.
So, that's our first constructor.
Now, remember we said that normally there are
two constructors, one that accepts the information
that we need, which we have here, and also one that
let's us associate another exception with it.
So, what I'm going to do here is grab this first
constructor, just copy that, I'll paste it in,
and what I'm going to do on this second constructor here
is add in a throwable cause.
So, we've got the cause there, and all we're going to do is
pass that to our base class constructor.
And, we now have a custom exception, because, remember
that all the real work of being an exception we're inheriting
from the base class, right?
So, we're really ready now to have our own custom exception.
So now, what we need to do is add in
the appropriate error checks into our code, alright?
So, let's go to our CalculateHelper class here,
and here we are inside the process method.
Remember, the job of the process method is to take
that string statement, break it into its parts,
and then, do the right work under the covers.
So, remember that we said, there are three things
we're going to start checking for.
The first one was to make sure that we have enough parts
to the incoming statement.
So, the right place to check for that is right here
after we call split, because when we call split,
we get back an array with all the parts, right?
So, what we want to do is make sure that array
has exactly three members in it.
So, let's put an if statement in place.
We'll just check to see that the parts.length
is equal to three, or I should say,
if the parts.length is not equal to three.
And then, if it's not equal to three, what we're going
to do is throw an instance of our exception,
so we want to say, throw, we're going to new up
an instance of our exception, and remember,
our exception is the InvalidStatementException,
and, remember that, we want to pass this one
two parameters: the reason that something is wrong,
and then the statement itself.
So, the reason we'll say is, Incorrect number of fields.
And then, we'll pass our statement in.
And so now, we're throwing an exception there.
So, that takes care of the not having enough parts to it.
Now, the next issue was that of non-numeric data.
Now, the way we're going to find out we have
non-numeric data is that, when we call these parseDouble
methods, they'll actually throw a NumberFormatException
if that data is not numeric.
So, we'll do in this case here where we actually
convert the strings into doubles, let's wrap that in
a try/catch block to handle NumberFormatException.
So, we've got that there, so let's go ahead and complete
our catch block, and again we'll throw our
InvalidStatementException, this time our reason will be,
Non-numeric data.
So we've got our reason and the statement, but this time,
we want to add a third parameter,
which is the original exception, alright?
So, we don't want to lose the fact that this was actually
triggered by another exception.
So, we've got that there, so that takes care of
our non-numeric data situation.
The last thing we need to check for is an invalid command.
Remember, the command is set by this
setCommandFromString method.
Let's scroll down and look at that.
Remember that setCommandFromString actually
takes that string value, goes through and tries to compare
it with each one of the enumerations, and when it finds it,
it sets the appropriate enumeration to our command field.
So, if we leave setCommandFromString, and the command
field is still null, we know it was an invalid command.
So, what we'll do is, we'll scroll up here, right after
we get back from setCommandFromString, we'll check and see
if that command field is null.
And if it is, we'll again throw our
InvalidStatementException, with the reason being,
Invalid command.
So, now we have all of our error checking inside of our
process method, and we raised all of these exceptions,
but you notice that each one of these throws is
underlined in red by my IDE.
Well, the reason is, it's complaining that I haven't
handled this exception.
Now, of course, I could put a try/catch block to handle
these exceptions, but, obviously, I don't want to do that,
because I want the caller to get the exception.
So, what I need to do, then, is go up here to my method
declaration, and add a throws clause for
InvalidStatementException because, remember, our custom
exceptions are checked exceptions, right?
So now, we've indicated that we throw that exception.
So now, if we go back to our main program, you'll notice
that where we call process is now underlined in red,
because we're not handling the exception, right?
The method declares that it throws it,
so we have to handle it.
So, we'll wrap this is a try/catch block.
And, what I'm going to do is put the try/catch block inside
the for statement, because I want to make sure that,
if I get an error on one statement,
I still process the next statement.
If I put the entire for loop inside the try block,
as soon as there was any error, it would jump out
of the try block and into the catch, and I wouldn't
process anything else.
So, let's put a try block right in here, so we'll wrap
the body of our for in the try, then we'll catch
the InvalidStatementException, so we've got that there,
and, of course, put our catch block in place.
Let me just scroll a little bit so we can see
a little better.
And, what I want to do, of course, is print out
the error message.
And, the way I get to the error message is,
I just go to the exception and I call its getMessage method.
And then, I'll write out the message for that exception.
And that message for our exception was set when we called
the base class constructor.
Now, remember that, in some cases, we'll have not only
our exception, but another exception.
What we want to do is look inside of this exception,
and see if there's another exception
that was a cause inside of there.
So, I'm going to put an if statement here again.
I'm going to say, e.gotCause, and that checks to see if
there's a cause associated with this,
which is the other exception.
Okay, well, if the cause comes back as non-null,
that means that we know that there was a cause.
So, if the cause comes back as nun-null, that means that
there's another exception here.
So, what I'm going to do in this case is,
write out the message from that exception.
So, I call e.getCause to get the original exception,
and then call getMessage on that one.
And, so now, when I go through here, any time we get an
InvalidStatementException, we'll write out the message
for that InvalidStatementException.
If there was another exception inside of it,
we'll write out that message as well.
So, let's go ahead and run this guy
and see what it looks like now.
Alright, so we ran to completion.
I'm going to make this window a little larger
so we can see everything.
And, you notice here, everything worked that we expected.
Alright, the first statement had an invalid number
of fields, because it only had two fields inside of it,
the add and 1.0, so we see that there.
The next one had non-numeric data, right, the xx,
so notice we write out our message, Non-numeric data,
and show the statement, then even we show the original
exception, which pinpoints the fact that it was the xx.
So, that xx came from the NumberFormatException
that was raised.
And then, our last error on this one had that addX,
which was an Invalid command,
which it wrote out appropriately.
And then, for the next four, which are all actually correct,
those processed just fine.
So, we've now used a custom exception to signal our error,
provide the caller with adequate information,
so they could then handle in their try/catch block.