To wrap up, remember our focus in this module
is on exceptions.
And exceptions provides an non-intrusive way
to signal errors.
And, when we're working with exceptions, we use try, catch
and finally to provide a structured way
to handle those exceptions.
The try block is the work we want to perform normally,
the catch block is what we want to do
if something goes wrong, and finally gives us a common place
to put our clean-up code.
And remember that exceptions are typed, and can be caught
by type, so you can have a separate catch statement
for differing exception types.
So, you can provide a very specific handling for each type.
Remember, though, you want to catch from most specific type
to least specific, because the system checks from the top
down of catches, and the first catch it encounters
they can assign that exception type to it will use.
So, if you've got a more specific handler, you want to
put that before your more general handler.
Remember, exceptions are raised using the throw key word,
but remember that, if a method has any checked exceptions
that it doesn't catch, then it must declare those exceptions
can occur by using the throws clause
on the method declaration.
And normally, when we throw exceptions,
we want to choose one of the build-in exceptions, but,
if we need to, we can create our own custom exception types.
And normally, those exception types will inherit
from the exception class, which makes our custom exceptions
checked exceptions.