Welcome to the next module of the Pluralsight
Java Fundamentals course in the Java language.
In this module, we're going to take a look
at creating abstract relationships with interfaces.
My name is Jim Wilson.
Throughout this module, we'll look
at a number of issues related to interfaces.
We'll start by just defining what an interface is.
We'll then look at implementing an interface,
and we'll do that by taking a look
at some of the interfaces that are provided by Java.
We'll then look at how we can have a single class
that implements multiple interfaces.
We'll then take a look at declaring our own interface.
We will do that by adding some features
to our calc engine app that we've been working
on throughout the course.