In Java, an interface is a type that defines a contract.
The key difference between an interface
and a class is that interfaces do not
provide any implementation,
they simply provide the contract.
Classes that implement an interface,
indicating that a class conforms to the contract.
The key thing is that
by implementing an interface,
it doesn't limit other aspects of the class.
The class can do whatever it needs to,
in a general sense, as long as
when it's implementing features of the interface,
it conforms to the contract defined by the interface.
The easiest way to see this is with an example.
So let's take one of the built-in
interfaces called Comparable.
The Comparable interface is used
for determining relative order, how does
one instance of a class compare to another instance?
And so it has one method called compareTo,
and basically, inside that compareTo,
it's passed in another instance.
And the return value of compareTo
indicates how the current instance
compares to, in sequence,
to the other instance that was passed in.
So if compareTo returns a negative value,
it says, well, the current instance should come
before the one that was passed into it.
If we return a positive value,
it says the current instance should come
after the one that was passed to it.
If they're actually equal, it returns zero.
Let's look at our Passenger class.
Now, our Passenger class has been used
for a lot of things throughout this course.
Let's say we want to add the concept
of, like, a frequent flyer program
so that we can give people premiums.
So we'll have a concept of a member level.
So the highest level is level three,
the lowest level is level one.
You might think of this as, like,
level one might be like a silver member,
two might be a gold member,
and three might be like a platinum member.
So any premiums we hand out
we want to give to the level three folks
before we give them to the level two,
before the level one.
We also want to keep track of how long
someone has been a member.
So what we'd like to be able to do
is compare two Passenger instances
based on this idea of a frequent flyer program
and have the people who have
the highest priority come first,
people who are lower come later.
So what we'll do is we'll go ahead
and add the implements keyword
and then the Comparable interface.
We're going to say that our Passenger class
implements the Comparable interface,
or conforms to the Comparable contract.
So we'll have that one method, compareTo.
It accepts a reference to another instance.
Array as defined to accept an object.
So one of the first things we'll want to do
is go ahead and cast that object
into an instance of Passenger,
and then we want to kind of
go through the test we have to do
to determine who should come first
and who should come after.
So first I can see, well, if our member level
is higher than the one that's passed in,
we return a minus one, saying that
we should come before that one.
So if we are a level three,
and the one passed in is a level two,
we should come first, we'll return minus one.
On the other hand, if we're something
like a level one, and they're a level two,
we'll return a positive one, say that
we should come after them.
But now what if it's a tie?
Well, you figure that if an airplane
might have 200 passengers,
there's only three levels of membership,
there's a high probability that there are ties.
So what we'll do is that, in the case of a tie,
we'll check how long they've been a member.
So put an else block here,
and then we'll say that if our number of days
are greater than the one passed in,
again, we'll return minus one,
saying that we come before they do.
Then we'll say, well, if we're less than them,
return a positive value, we come after.
And then if they're the same level member
and theyve been in for the same number of days,
that's actually a tie, we'll return zero.
So now the value of implementing this interface
is that we can take advantage of features
that know how to work with the comparable contract.
So let's put together some code here.
So we'll declare an instance of Passenger,
we'll name Passenger bob.
We'll say that he is a level one member,
and he's been in for 180 days,
so he's like a silver member,
and he's been around for six months.
We'll have another member, Jane.
Jane is also a level one member,
she's been in for 90 days.
Then we'll have Steve, who's a level two member,
like a gold member, and he's been
in for 180 days, or about six months.
And then finally we'll have Lisa,
who's a level three member,
so maybe like a platinum member,
she's been in for 730 days or about two years.
What we'll do then is declare a Passenger array,
and then load that array up
with Bob, Jane, Steve, and Lisa.
We can then use a built-in method
called Arrays.sort
and pass in passengers.
Because we conform
to the comparable contract,
that sort method can now go through
and do an efficient sort
and order these based on the rules
of our Comparable implementation.
So after we return from sort,
the first member of passengers
is going to be Lisa,
the one with the highest status,
the level three status, like our platinum status.
Then it would be Steve, who has the next highest level,
then we have Bob,
because even though Bob and Jane
tie on the level, Bob's been
a member longer, at 180 days
and then finally Jane.
So now, simply by implementing that comparable interface,
and conforming to that contract,
we're able to take advantage
of the efficient sort capabilities
provided by Java.
Let's look at another example.
So we have this Flight class
we've been working with throughout the course,
and let's say we're going to have our flights
start tracking the time that they fly.
And for simplicity, we'll just track
that time as minutes past midnight.
All right, so a flight takes off
at 12:15, then it would have a flightTime of 15.
A flight takes off at 1:30 am,
it would have a flightTime of 90,
right, 90 minutes past midnight.
And we want to be able to sort these flights
based on the time they take off.
So what we'll do is we'll implement
that Comparable interface
and we'll come in our compareTo.
Now, in this case, we're going to order them by time.
So we'll first, of course, want
to cast that object that's passed in to a flight.
Then we can say, well, if our flightTime
becomes before the passed in flightTime,
return minus one, say that we should be sorted first.
If ours comes after, we return one,
saying that we should be sorted after.
And of course if there's a tie, then return zero.
But it's interesting, if we look at this,
if we look at the definition of the comparable interface,
it says a compareTo uses the sign to determine order.
It doesn't say it has to be minus one or positive one,
it simply says that negative says it should come first,
positive says it should come after.
Well, if we think about this,
if I have a flightTime of, say, 15, or 12:15,
and I compare that to another flightTime of 45,
well, if I subtract 45 from 15, I'll get minus 30.
All right, so that would still be negative,
saying, I should come before.
All right, so I can actually simply take
all this code we have here with these comparisons
and boil it down to some simple arithmetic.
If I simply subtract the passed
in flightTime from my time,
if I'm before, the value will be negative,
so I'll be sorted before.
If I am after, the value will be positive,
I'll be sorted after.
So that's a very simple implementation of compareTo.
So, again, I can do that sorting idea.
So I have a flight, say, lax045.
It takes off 45 minutes past midnight.
I have another flight, slc015,
that takes off 15 minutes past midnight.
And finally New York's 30-30,
that takes off 30 minutes past midnight.
I take the array, put those guys inside there,
and sort it, I'll now get again that sorting ability.
All right, the 12:15 one will come first.
12:30 will come second,
and 12:45 will come after.
And see, the key thing there is that
Flight has a really, really simple
implementation of Comparable,
Passenger had a much more involved implementation,
but simply by conforming to that contract,
we are now able to take advantage
of the very same features
and get the very similar results
while still having the ability to define
the right way to conform to that contract
within the features of our type.