When working with interfaces,
you'll notice that some interfaces
require additional type information.
This uses a concept known as generics.
Now if we were to go in and take a look
at the declaration for the Comparable interface,
you'll notice that after the name Comparable,
there's this less-than symbol,
T, and then a greater-than symbol.
This is saying that Comparable interface implementation
can be tied to a type.
So if we take a look now
at the way it declares the compareTo method,
you'll notice it has that same T.
So we can specify in our implementation
what type we want to expect to receive
in that compareTo method.
If we take a look at here in our Flight class.
Now, right now our Comparable doesn't specify type,
which is why our compareTo is accepting an object.
But if we instead, after the Comparable,
put in the less-than symbol and Flight and greater-than,
we're now saying that we want to implement Comparable
using the Flight type.
So our compareTo method then,
rather than having an object as parameter
would have a parameter of type Flight.
That would allow us to get rid of this cast
from object to Flight.
It would also give us all the type safety
of having typed parameters,
so we're not dependent on receiving things
as an object and then having to convert them.
We know that by the time they reach our code,
it's already the appropriate type, in this case, Flight.
So, similarly, if we take a look at our Passenger class,
rather than our compareTo for Passenger
accepting an object, we can specify
that our Comparable should be tied to the type Passenger.
So then in that case, our compareTo would
instead accept a Passenger parameter,
and we can get rid of again that cast that we have in place.
Now one thing to note is that
when you implement the interface,
the type that you pass in doesn't have
to be the same type as the class that's implementing it.
In some cases it makes sense to, in other cases it doesn't.
We'll see an example in the next clip of a time
where we don't actually have to use that same type.
Also, I want to note that generics are not
something that's specific to interfaces.
Generics are this kind of generalized concept in Java.
It's a very, very powerful concept.
Once you've had a chance to work
with the basics of Java a bit more,
I would encourage you to check out
the Pluralsight class on Java Generics.
I have the URL for that class up on the screen now.