One of the real values of interfaces
is that classes are free to implement multiple interfaces.
Remember that a class can
only extend one other class,
but a class can implement as many interfaces as it needs to,
so that means that a class can conform
to as many interface-based contracts as it needs to.
So let's take a look at something.
We've got our Flight class here,
and we know it's already implemented,
the interface Comparable,
but let's say we want to extend
our Flight class a little bit more.
Remember that, up until now,
we've kind of kept a count of
the number of passengers we have.
Let's say we want to extend our Flight class
to actually keep a list of actual passengers.
So we create a member variable called roster,
it's an array of Passenger.
Let's also go ahead and create
a CrewMember array we'll call crew,
so we can keep track of all the people
that are actually on the flight.
Since we have all these people on the flight,
we'll probably want to be able
to list them all at some point,
both crew members and passengers.
Let's look at those two types.
First we have our Passenger class.
Now, it implements an interface Comparable,
but it doesn't have a base class,
so its base class is object.
Of course, CrewMember doesn't have
a base class either, so its base class is object.
So the only thing that's common
about CrewMember and Passenger at this point
is the object class, and that's not really useful
for us in terms of trying to treat them as kind of people.
So it probably makes sense for us
to go ahead and create a class
called Person that has the common
characteristics of a person.
Let's say each person at least has a name.
There's probably other characteristics as well.
And then we'll take our CrewMember class
and we'll have it extend to Person class.
We'll also have our Passenger class
extend to Person class.
So now crew members and passengers
have a commonality, they're each
considered an instance of a Person.
So what we'd like to be able to do here is
use a for each statement to walk through
every person on the flight and be able
to print out their information
or interact with their information.
So we look at the for each statement,
it would actually tell us that, in order
to be able to work with a for each statement,
you have to implement an interface called Iterable.
So if we take a look at that interface,
so the Iterable interface is really simple.
It's a generic interface, it has a type associated with it,
and it has one member, Iterator.
So we'll take our Flight class
that already implements the interface Comparable,
we'll go ahead and have it implement
the interface Iterable.
Notice that this one is based on the type Person.
I just want to mention that earlier, we said that
sometimes we implement interfaces,
the type associated with them is the same as the class,
like it was for Comparable, it used Flight,
but for Iterable, we're using Person,
which is different than the class Flight,
because we want to keep passing back a person
each time we go through the list.
So the interface Iterable has one method,
so, again, that's the iterator method,
and it returns back a type called Iterator.
Well, the type Iterator is also an interface.
It has two methods on it,
has one hasNext, which tells
you if there's more to come,
and then a method next
that returns you back the next thing,
in this case, it'd be the next person.
And when we implement iterators,
we generally implement a separate class
to actually manage the iteration.
So what we need to do then
is implement a class here
that actually implements the interface Iterator.
So let's go ahead and set that up,
and we'll call this class our FlightIterator.
As we said, we'll implement the interface Iterator,
again, each time it'll return back a Person.
We'll have the two methods, hasNext
and then the next method.
So of course what we want to do here
is walk through the list of every person
on the flight, whether they're
a crew member or a passenger.
But of course we'll need those two arrays.
Let's have member variables for each of those,
one for the crew and one for the roster.
We'll have a single index that will
walk through the entire combined list,
and let's create a constructor that we can
use to actually accept those arrays.
So we have a crew and roster
and we'll assign those to our member variables.
And so now let's look at our implementation.
Well, first we have hasNext.
How do we know if there's more information to come?
Well, if we haven't walked through
the entire combined list of crew and roster,
there's more to come.
So as long as our index is less
than the combined length of the crew array
and the roster array, there must be more to come.
And our next is going to return back
each individual person.
So first we'll walk through the crew array,
and then we'll walk through the roster array.
So basically, we'll have our Person p,
and we'll actually say, well, if the index
is less than the crew length,
we'll simply return back the crew member
that corresponds to that index.
All right, so if there were three crew members,
indexes zero, one, and two,
we'd walk through the crew array.
Once we get to three, we now
want to switch over to the roster array.
So in that case, we'll just use roster
with the index minus the crew length.
All right, so if we're on index three,
well, three minus the length of the crew array,
three is zero, that gives us the first one in the roster.
So once we have the Person, we'll increment the index,
and then we'll return back that Person.
So now we have our FlightIterator class
that managed the iteration itself.
What we want to do now is return an instance
of that back from our Flight class's Iterator method.
So let's return that back, that new instance.
So now we actually have everything we need
to be able to walk through every person
that's on a flight, both crew and passengers,
using our for each statement.
Let's take a look at some code to do that.
So go out here, we'll create a flight,
our lax045, let's say
we'll add some crew members to it,
Pilot Patty, CoPilot Karl, and Marshal Mary,
and then we'll add our Passengers to it,
Bob, Jane, Steve, and Lisa,
and then we'll create our for each statement,
so for Person p:lax045,
that's going to say use the iterator
to go through each person that's on that flight
and we'll write them out.
So of course we run this code,
we would see each of the crew members first,
and then each of the passengers.
Now this may seem a little bit abstract
because, you know, we wrote all that interface stuff
but nothing we're looking at here in the code
actually shows the interface stuff.
Well, that's because the for statement
actually expands out to actually work with the interfaces.
So the code I'm going to show here
is kind of conceptually what happens,
it's not the line-by-line detail of what actually happens,
but it gives you an idea of what's
actually happening under the covers.
When we create that for statement,
what effectively happens is it
takes the flight, the lax045,
casts that into its iterable interface,
then using that, we get the iterator,
so here we're putting that in
something we're calling persons,
and then basically we loop over that.
So we have a loop in place to just make sure
that hasNext is returning true, saying there's more to come,
then we use the next method to get
whatever is next, the next person,
all right, first the crew members, then the passengers,
and then finally whatever is the body of our loop execute,
in this case, printing out the name.
And so you see now the power of interfaces
is that the for each statement is useful
for many, many, many, many different types,
and those types have very little
or basically nothing in common.
But because, as long as a type conforms
to that iterable interface's contract,
it can take advantage of the power of the for statement.