Up until now, we've been looking
at implementing existing interfaces,
but we can also declare our own interfaces.
Now, declaring an interface is
very similar to declaring a class.
You use the interface keyword to define an interface.
Now interfaces support a subset
of the features that are available to classes.
Interfaces can have methods, but when
we provide the methods to an interface,
we simply list the method name,
its parameters, and its return type.
Remember that interfaces do not have an implementation,
right, they're just defining a contract.
Now the methods of an interface are implicitly public.
Now, interfaces can also have constants,
and basically we're just saying that
that is a typed named value.
Now the constants we put on an interface
are always considered public, final, and static.
We don't have to use those keywords,
but they're treated that way.
What that means is that
any constant you associate with an interface
has the same value for implementers of the interface,
there's no concept of a per-instance constant
in interfaces, right, it's always interface-wide,
or true for all implementers of that interface.
Also, interfaces can be extended.
One interface can extend another interface.
What that means, of course, is that it can
add additional methods and constants to it.
So in a way that you can extend classes,
one interface can extend another.
And what's neat about that is that,
when you extend an interface,
you're kind of adding an additional contract to it.
So any class that implements
an interface that extends another interface
is automatically considered
to implement the base interface.
In our next clip, let's take a look at declaring our own interface inside
of our CalcEngine program, and what it's like
to work with that interface once we declare it.