In this demo, we'll be using interfaces
to dynamically extend the capabilities
of our CalcEngine app.
As you'll recall, earlier in the course,
we add the ability of our CalcEngine app
where we could type in things like this,
where we say, "add 1.0 2.0,"
and the CalcEngine app would then
do the calculation and then write back the result
in a more traditional format,
"1.0 + 2.0 = 3.0."
What we want to do now
is make this more dynamic.
Currently, the way the app is written
is that the code that actually does all the work
to take things apart and produce results
is tied to a very particular class.
What we want to do now is make that more abstract.
With the core work, behave in terms of an interface
and have specific calculation abilities
implement that interface so we can easily
plug in new abilities into our CalcEngine app.
Here we are in our CalcEngine app,
and we're picking up our code where we left off
at the end of the last module.
What I've done, though, is that all the code
that was in our main function
is now in this function that is called useCalculateHelper.
And I've put in a call to that
function but commented it out.
Then what I've done is I've stripped it down
so we have just one statement,
you see the "add 25 and 92,"
and then a simple for loop to walk through
that array of statements.
So what I want to do now is, again,
take that functionality that we have
in CalculateHelper but make it more
dynamic by using interfaces.
Now, if we look at our CalculateHelper class,
go inside of here, basically when
we process a statement,
we do a few fundamental things.
We, first of all, we split it apart
based on a particular character,
which is the space character,
and then once we split it apart,
we have to identify the command we'll execute.
If I scroll down here, currently the list
of commands we support is hardcoded, right?
Add, subtract, multiply and divide,
so we've got to work through that list.
And then what I want do do is,
do the operation, but our operation
is done in terms of a base class, CalculateBase,
and then we produce output.
And the output relies on having
a symbol for each operation.
If we go up top here, you see that
each symbol is hardcoded, a plus sign,
a minus sign, an asterisk, and a slash for divide.
What we want to do now is take these ideas
and implement them more generically using an interface.
So let's go ahead and create an interface now
that represents the parts of doing this work.
So we go out here, im going to go ahead
and add an interface, so I add an interface,
in IntelliJ very similar to a class,
just do a right-click and New.
And the way it is in IntelliJ is
I still have the New Class dialogue,
but we change this from Class to say Interface.
But we'll see that we can
actually just type it in very easily.
And we'll call our interface MathProcessing.
So go ahead and create that.
And you can see the declaration is very simple,
it looks very much like a class,
it just says interface instead of class.
So we want the interface to represent
the parts of what we need to do.
Let's go ahead and add those in there.
So first thing we'll do is we'll add
a constant called SEPARATOR that has a value of space,
that's the character we use to split statements apart.
And then we want to model what we need to know
for anything that implements operations
that do these calculations.
Well, one thing that we need is a keyword,
so let's add a method called getKeyword.
So that would give back a keyword
that a particular implementation knows how to handle.
So, for example, it might be something like add,
if there's implementation that knows how to do adding.
The next thing we need to know from any implementation
is what symbol it wants to use in the output.
So we'll have another method
called getSymbol that's of type character.
For something that did addition,
that would be the plus sign.
And the last thing we need to do
is actually perform the operation,
so let's create a method called doCalculation
that returns a double, and accepts two values,
a leftVal and a rightVal that are both doubles.
So that's our entire interface.
Again, there's no implementations,
it's just a contract, right,
classes that implement this
will conform to the MathProcessing contract
which means they have to identify
the keywords they know how to work on,
return back a symbol that will be used
to produce the output, and then
do the calculation that goes with that keyword.
So what we can do is go ahead and use
our existing Adder class to implement this interface.
So I go over here to my Adder class.
I'm going to go ahead and have it
here implement MathProcessing.
And of course we have to go ahead
and provide the methods for that,
so I'm going to let the IDE do that for me
by saying Implement Methods.
I want to implement all the methods for that interface.
So we'll say OK.
And so that now provides those methods.
So we just have to do the work associated with each method.
Well my Adder, the keyword it handles is add,
so I'll return back the word add.
The symbol that it uses is plus sign.
And then we have to do the work.
Our Adder is written in terms of
this Calculate base class, so we'll do the addition
using the Calculate base class way of doing that.
All right, so first thing we'll do
is we'll set our left value,
then we'll set our right value,
then we'll call our calculate method,
and then finally we're going
to return back the result.
Scroll so you can see everything.
So you can see now, that's everything
Adder has to do to conform to this interface.
Now, just one thing to note, if I scroll up here,
Adder extends CalculateBase,
so we could have had CalculateBase
implement the MathProcessing interface
if we wanted all four classes that inherit from it
to implement the interface.
But basically, just had CalculateBase
say it implements MathProcessing,
make all the interface methods abstract
in a derived class would then implement it themselves.
We're going to focus in here now
just on having Adder do it.
So this gives us now a class that implements that interface.
In the next clip, let's do a code
we need to write to now use this interface.