So we have this interface, MathProcessing,
that models a concept of a class
being able to identify a keyword it operates on,
do the operation, and tell us what symbol
to use when producing the output.
Adder implements it, what we want to do now
is write a class that does that same work
that CalculateHelper did but do it
in terms of handlers that implement the interface
rather than a set of hardcoded operations.
So let's go ahead and add another class to our project,
we'll call this our DynamicHelper.
So we have our DynamicHelper class,
and what we'll do is store a list of handlers,
so we'll do that as an array.
So I'll declare an array here
of type MathProcessing called handlers.
So that'll be the list of handlers that a given
instance of DynamicHelper has access to.
We'll then have the constructor accept an array
of handlers and store it inside of our class variable.
So whenever we create an instance of this class,
we just pass in that array that contains
all the handlers we want to use.
And then from there, we'll add a method called process
that accepts a string statement to operate on
and returns back a string result.
Right, so the idea is that what would come in
would be something like "add 1.0 2.0"
and then what goes out would be
the traditional math representation
of that, showing the result.
So the same work we did earlier in CalculateHelper,
but again, we're doing it
this time in terms of the interface.
Now we still have to do some of the basic work,
like one of the things we have to do
is split the statement up using the string split method.
So when we split it, we'll use the constant that was defined
on our MathProcessing interface called SEPARATOR,
and that constant was a space,
we're still going to go ahead and split it based on a space.
And then of course our keyword
is the very first part of the statement.
So in this case, that might
be something like the add keyword.
So now, what we need to do
is loop through the handlers to find
the handler that knows how to handle add.
So what I'll do here is I'll first of all
declare a local variable called
theHandler of type MathProcessing,
and then what I want do now is
loop through that array of handlers
to try to find a handler that knows how
to handle the keyword that was in the statement.
So down here, I'll create a for loop,
let me just scroll down a little bit
so we can see everything a little better.
So again, we'll have that for looped
that will go through the handlers.
So inside there, let's add an if statement.
We'll say our keyword,
we'll use equalsIgnoreCase.
And what do we want to do?
We want to take the current handler
that we're looping through,
and we'll call it getKeyword method.
In other words, is the keyword in the statement
match the keyword that this handler knows how to handle?
Okay, if it does, we'll take the current handler
and assign it to our local variable, theHandler,
and then we'll just go ahead
and we'll break out of the loop.
Okay, so we get out of this for statement now,
we know that we have a handler that knows
how to handle that particular keyword.
Now we still have a little bit of housekeeping to do.
We want to get our left values and right values
and convert those into a double,
so we'll use the same mechanism
we used earlier in the course,
so I'll declare a local variable
called leftVal of type double,
I'll then use the double class's parseDouble method,
and I'll do that for parts of one.
So that would be something like our 1.0 value.
Right, now we'll do the same thing for rightVal.
So now we have both values,
so what we can do is we can have
a local variable we'll call result,
and then we'll call the handlers doCalculationMethod.
And we simply pass in leftVal and rightVal.
So when this returns, result now has
whatever the result of the calculation was.
So what we want to do now is
build that string output value,
again that idea of "1.0 + 2.0 = 3.0".
Now the code to do that is going to be
almost exactly the same as the code
that we used in CalculateHelper.
So I'm going to go over here to our CalculateHelper class,
scroll down to its two string method.
I'm going to grab the code here
where it actually builds the output string.
So let's copy that.
Go back to my DynamicHelper.
Paste that in, and of course
I've got to make sure my variable names match,
so instead of leftValue I have leftVal,
rightValue is rightVal,
but now the one for the symbol, like the plus sign,
well how am I going to get that?
Well, I'll go to the handler
and I'll call this getSymbol method.
So I'll get back whatever symbol
is appropriate for this handler.
Right, so, again, if we look at our Adder implementation,
right, our keyword is add,
our symbol is the plus sign,
and doCalculation does the appropriate arithmetic,
it adds them together.
Let's go to our DynamicHelper,
we have here now is all set to go.
So let's go back to our main program now
and create our dynamic helper.
So we'll create a local variable here of type DynamicHelper,
we call the variable helper,
we get a new DynamicHelper,
I'm going to pass in a new array of MathProcessing.
And what we'll do is we'll just
initialize the array in place,
and what we do is put in
the implementations we have for math processing.
Now, currently the only one we have is Adder,
so I'll just new up Adder.
And so now what we want to do is
loop through each of the statements,
passing them into our helper.
So we'll go through here,
we'll declare a string to get our output.
And then we simply say helper.process,
and we pass in our statement.
So when that returns, the variable output
should have whatever our helper produced,
so let's go ahead and write out output.
And so, with that, we should have
all the code in place that we need at this point
to handle that one statement that does the add.
The key thing here is that
our DynamicHelper is doing all the work
in terms of the MathProcessing interface.
So let's go ahead and run our program
and see if everything works as we expect.
And it does, if we scroll down here,
when we add 25.0 and 92.0,
we get back 117.0.
So everything worked just as we expected it to,
but it did it in terms of the interface.
So now, in the next clip, let's see
what it's like to add another handler
into our DynamicHelper and see that we can get
new processing capabilities without making
any changes to our DynamicHelper.