Here we are, back in our CalcEngine app,
and remember, we have our DynamicHelper class
that knows how to parse apart a statement,
find a handler that knows how to deal with a keyword,
ask the handler to do the operation,
and then our DynamicHelper can build the output.
Now, again, we've done all of this in terms of the interface
so we can actually extend the ability
of DynamicHelper very easily.
So let's imagine that we want
to have another statement in here,
something we've never done before.
Maybe we want to support a statement
that can actually raise values to a power.
So we'll use the keyword power,
I want to say something like 5.0, 2.0,
that we're going to square
the value of 5.0, 5.0 times itself.
So the result of that would
be something like 5.0, let's say
use the caret for power of, 2.0
equals 25.0, so we want to build
a handler that can do that work.
So what we'll do is we'll add a new class
to our project called PowerOf.
Create the class, and we're going
to have it implement our MathProcessing interface.
We'll go ahead and add all the methods,
say all three of them.
So we want out PowerOf implementation here
to do the work necessary to plug into our DynamicHelper.
We'll have a getKeyword, we'll have
the keyword it understands is power.
The symbol that it returns is that caret.
And then to do the actual work,
we'll use one of the built-in
math libraries called pow, p-o-w.
And to pow, we'll pass in a leftVal and a rightVal.
So we now have a class, PowerOf,
that knows how to raise values to a power
and conform to our MathProcessing interface.
So now to add that into our DynamicHelper,
all we have to do is go back to our Main,
and here we new up the Adder, we're going
to go ahead in that same array we passed in there,
we'll now new up PowerOf,
and that's all we do, create an instance of the class
that implements the interface,
and then make DynamicHelper aware of it.
Now when we run this,
we should see that both the add statement
and the power statement get handled.
And you see there that we do.
The add statement adds the numbers together correctly,
the power statement raised 5.0
to the power of two, producing 25.
And you see, that's where the power
of interfaces really shine through.
That ability to take a problem,
abstractly model it in terms of its individual pieces,
model the contract to fulfill those pieces as an interface,
and then you can very easily just
build implementations of the interface
that focus on a very specific set of work.
And then you can leverage a lot of that existing work
that you've already done to get very powerful results
with only a little bit of incremental work each time.