To wrap up, remember the key things
you want to remember from this module
is that an interface defines a contract.
It does not provide any sort of implementation,
all right, it's simply the contract.
That contract can consist of methods and constants.
So the way interfaces are implemented are by classes.
Right, classes implement interfaces,
and what that means is
that any class that implements the interface
conforms to the contract defined by the interface,
right, and that allows us to have classes
with very different features and capabilities
but then can conform at times when they need to
to specific contracts.
One of the key things is that,
whereas a class can only extend one class,
a class is free to implement as many
interfaces as it needs to, so it can conform
to as many contracts as it needs to.
And remember that interfaces can also extend one another,
so you can define an interface
that extends another interface.
And remember that whenever you implement
an interface that extends another interface,
by implementing the extended interface,
you implicitly implement the base interface.