Welcome to the next module of the Pluralsight
Java Fundamentals course on the Java Language.
In this module we discuss class inheritance.
My name is Jim Wilson.
We have a lot of great content to talk about in this module.
First we'll take a look at the basics of
class inheritance in Java.
The idea of member hiding and member overriding.
The object class, the base class of all classes in Java.
Object equality, what happens when you compare two objects
to see if they're equal. And what does equal actually mean?
We'll look at the super keyword, a useful tool for accessing
base class behaviors in a derived class.
We'll look at how to control class inheritance
and member overriding behavior using final and abstract.
Then finally we'll look at how constructors work
when inheriting one class from another.