To wrap up, our focus in this module was on inheritance.
Inheritance allows us to create a class that has the
characteristics of another class. In Java, we use the
extend keyword to identify that one class is deriving
from another. Derived classes can override base class
methods, in other words we can provide our own definition
of those methods' behaviors. In Java, methods are
automatically overridable, but you can optionally include
the @Override annotation which just causes the compiler
to verify that there's a base class method with the
signature you're trying to override. The Object class
is the roof of all class hierarchies. Every class in Java
inherits from it either directly or indirectly. It gives us
the idea of a universal reference type, and it also provides
us with a set of known characteristics that all classes
have. By default, when we compare two object references
for equality, they're only considered equal if they both
point to the exact same object instance. But this is a
scenario where the Object class comes in handy.
The Object class defines an equals method that we can
override and provide a more specific definition of equals
for any given class. When we're overriding methods, we'll
often need to have access to base class behaviors.
Using the super keyword we can access our current object
instance as if it were an instance of the base class.
That allows us to get to those base class behaviors.
We will sometimes want to have tighter control
over inheritance behaviors, and that's where the
final and abstract keywords come in. If a class is marked
final, you're not allowed to inherit from it. If a method
is marked final, it can't be overridden. If a method is
marked abstract, it must be overridden. It doesn't
actually have a body, and any class that contains an
abstract method is itself abstract, meaning that that class
must be inherited from. And finally, remember that
constructors are not inherited. Every class is responsible
for providing its own constructors. But constructors can
call into their base class constructors, again using the
super keyword, with the parameter list of the base class
constructor they want to call into.