As an object-oriented language, Java allows one class
to inherit from another class, also known as
having a class derived from another class.
The way we do that is, when we're declaring a new class
we use the extends keyword and identify what class
we are extending or we are inheriting from.
What happens is that that derived class has
the characteristics of the base class,
and then can add its own specializations to create
more capabilities. To see what this looks like,
say we have a class here, we're going to call it our
CargoFlight class. What we want it to do is have all
the same basic characteristics as our Flight class,
so we simply say extends, and then Flight.
And so now the CargoFlight class will have those
characteristics that come from the Flight class, then can,
of course, add its own. So as a CargoFlight, one of
the things we want to keep track of is how much
cargo space we have.
So we'll say our CargoFlights have a thousand cubic feet
of cargo space. Of course, we want to keep track of
how much of that we're using, so we'll just go ahead and add
some methods to this. So we'll say that we'll have a method
to make sure that we have enough space for whatever the
size is of what we're trying to add, so we just make sure
that if we add that to how much space we've already used,
make sure it doesn't exceed our maxCargoSpace.
We'll have a method for handling when we do try to exceed
that, in this case we'll just display a message saying
there's not enough space. And then, of course, we'll have
a method here that says add1Package, and that method
will accept the dimensions of the package, the height,
the width, and the depth of that package.
So what we need to do then, inside this method,
is that when we receive a package, we'll calculate the
total size, simply multiply the height times the width
times the depth, and then we'll call our hasCargoSpace,
then if that returns true, we'll go ahead and add the size
of that package to how much space has been used,
otherwise we'll go ahead and handle the situation of
not having enough space, which again just prints out a
message. To use this, we can go out here and just declare
a CargoFlight reference, and new up a CargoFlight,
then we can of course add a package to it, and in this case
we're adding a package with a height of one foot, a width of
two-and-a-half feet, and a depth of three feet, giving us
a total size of 7-1/2 cubic feet. We add that into our
CargoFlight. Remember that since our CargoFlight extends
Flight, it's going to have access to the characteristics of
the Flight class, so our Flight class has this
addOnePassenger method, so with a CargoFlight,
we can go ahead and new up an instance of Passenger,
in this case, Jane, and still add one passenger, Jane,
to the CargoFlight. So we've got these extended capabilities
as well as the base class capabilities. As we work with a
derived class, instances of that derived class can be
assigned to references of the base class type.
So if we take a look at some code for that,
remember that we still have our CargoFlight here that
extends the Flight class, well we can go ahead and
create a reference of type Flight f, and then new up a
CargoFlight and assign it to that reference. What that means
is that as a Flight reference, it can use the Flight
capabilities, so we can new up a Passenger, and of course
add1Passenger.Jane to that Flight. The thing is that
we only have access to capabilities that are visible
to the Flight class. So if we try to do f.add1Package,
even though CargoFlight knows how to add1Package,
a Flight doesn't. So that wouldn't be a valid call, because
we can only access methods that are visible to the
reference type. The value of this capability, though,
it allows us to perform Flight-based actions without
being concerned about the specific type of the instance.
So if we think about a situation like this, say we create
an array of Flights, we'll call it Squadron and make some
room for five Flights, we could have the first member
of that be an instance of the Flight class, the next member
a member of the CargoFlight class, and keep mixing that up
so we have another CargoFlight, a Flight, and another
CargoFlight. And again we can loop through this doing
all the Flight-based stuff. For the CargoFlight ones
we may want to do some extended things for CargoFlights,
but it allows us to very easily group these actions.