When we're adding behavior to a derived class, that
derived class can of course have fields, as we've seen.
The thing is that if the derived class adds a field,
that has the same name as the field in the base class,
it will actually hide the base class field. Let's see
what that means. Take a look at our code here. Remember
that we have our Flight class, and as we've seen, our Flight
class has a method called add1Passenger. Now inside of
our add1Passenger it will check to see if we have enough
seating, if so we add the passenger, if not we handle
the case of too many. And the way we check and see if
we have enough seating is that we have a method called
hasSeating. What hasSeating does, it looks and sees that
as long as the number of passengers is less than the number
of seats, then we'll say we have seats. So our Flight class
has a field called seats with a value of 150. So if we
create an instance of our Flight class and it to a
Flight reference called f1, we print out the value of
f1.seats, we will of course get 150. If we take our
CargoFlight class that extends the Flight class,
we inherit from it, if it adds its own field called seats
with a value of 12, which would make sense, right?
If a plane is a cargo flight it may have fewer seats.
If we then go out here and create an instance of the
CargoFlight class and assign it to a reference of type
CargoFlight called cf, if we print out the value of cf.seats
that gives us a value of 12. The CargoFlight seats field is
hiding the Flight seats field. But now something unexpected
can happen by doing that. If I now create an instance of the
CargoFlight class, and I assign it to a reference of type
Flight, that we've called f2, when we print out f2.seats
what we will actually get is the value 150. Because the
seats value of 12 is only visible when the instance is
being worked with as a CargoFlight. Because the reference
here f2 is of type Flight, it doesn't know anything about
the seats value of 12. It only knows about the seats value
of 150. That becomes really important as we start using
methods from the base class. So if I take f2.add1Passenger,
when that calls into the method to add1Passenger, which
that in turn calls hasSeating, when it checks the value of
seats, it's going to use the value of seats that's defined
inside the Flight class, which is 150 - which would allow us
to add 150 passengers to a plane with only 12 seats.
Now this is not limited to the scenario where the reference
is of type Flight. If we were to say cf.add1Passenger,
cf is of type CargoFlight. Again, because add1Passenger
calls hasSeating and hasSeating is implemented inside the
Flight class, it would still use the value of 150, because
within that method it only knows about the fields defined
within Flight. So you can see this idea of hiding fields is
a very dangerous thing, so I'm going to go ahead and
highlight that in red. Now, when we work with methods
it's a little different. Methods can override base class
methods, so if you have a derived class that has a method
with the same signature as a base class method, it will
override it. Remember the signature means it has the same
name and the same parameter list. Let's see how overriding
differs from hiding. So we have our class here, CargoFlight
deriving from Flight, same exact code we saw before.
What we're going to do here is that when we set seats
equal to 150 as a field, what we're going to do is
get rid of that field, seats, and we're going to change it
to a method called getSeats that returns a value of 150.
Of course that means that our hasSeating method has to be
changed to get rid of seats and instead call getSeats.
And then our derived class, CargoFlight, will get rid of
its field seats, and add in a method called getSeats
that returns 12. So now if we work with this, we go out here
we have our Flight reference f1, assigned the value of a new
Flight instance. Of course when we print out getSeats, it's
going to print out 150. If we have a CargoFlight reference
cf pointing to a new instance of CargoFlight, when it prints
out getSeats, it will print out 12. But here's where we see
the difference. If I now have a Flight reference called f2
assigned to a new instance of CargoFlight, when we call
getSeats, because the getSeats method from CargoFlight
overrides the getSeats method from Flight, we will now
get the appropriate value of 12. So the method in the
derived class has overridden the base class method.
And that really important as we start to do further work.
So if I take my f2, a reference of type Flight, and
call add1Passenger, it calls into the add1Passenger method.
Inside of add1Passenger, we call into hasSeating. When we
get into hasSeating, when it calls getSeats, because the
instance is of type CargoFlight, the implementation of
getSeats inside of CargoFlight is actually what gets called,
returning the appropriate value of 12. So it would only
allow us to add 12 passengers. And that works whether we
have a reference like f2 of type Flight, or a reference cf
which is of the appropriate type CargoFlight. The method
in the base class is actually being overridden, assuring
that the appropriate method implementation gets called
based on the type of object created, not the type of
reference used. If you come from other object-oriented
languages, like C# or C++, something that may stand out
to you here is that you'll notice that we didn't have to do
anything special to be able to override that getSeats
method. In Java all methods are automatically overridable
unless you do something special to say that you don't want
them overridden. We'll talk about how to do that a little
later in this module. One of the things that may come to
mind, though, is that how do you make sure that you haven't
accidentally made a mistake in terms of maybe not matching
the signature correctly. What Java provides is the override
annotation. and what this tells the compiler is that it is
your intention to override a method from the base class.
So the compiler will actually check and make sure that the
base class has a method with that signature. So it's kind of
just a sanity check to make sure that the method you're
declaring really does replace a method in the base class.
Has no impact on run time, it's only used at compile time.