One of the built-in classes that Java provides is the Object
class. The Object class is the root of the Java class
hierarchy. What that means is that every class in Java,
whether it's a built-in class, or one you create, has the
characteristics of the Object class. What that means is that
using the Object class, we can declare references that can
point to any class type. So it can be variables, fields,
parameters, and because arrays are classes, objects
can even point to arrays. So it's really this kind of
universal reference type. But it's more than that.
The Object class actually has methods that are defined
on it. So that means that there are specific characteristics
and capabilities that are common to all classes. So if we
look at the idea of inheriting from the object class,
every class inherits either directly or indirectly from the
Object class. Let's look at some of the classes we've
written throughout this course. We have our Flight class.
If we were diagramming this, we might just kind of draw
a box representing the Flight class. Then of course we have
our CargoFlight class, so we'll draw a box for that.
Now remember that when we declared the CargoFlight
class we said that it extends the Flight class. So the way
we diagram that is we draw an arrow up to Flight, saying
that CargoFlight inherits from the Flight class. Now,
looking at the Flight class, there's nothing about it
extending anything, but what's implied in that class
declaration is that
class Flight extends the Object class.
So by not saying what it extends, it implicitly extends the
Object class. So to diagram that, we would have the Object
class, and Flight inherits from that. You could actually
write extends Object after Flight class, it just wouldn't
change anything. Having nothing there has the same
effect. So if we look at our Passenger class, we don't say
it extends anything, but when we diagram it it still extends
object. So what we see here is that, whether classes are
related to one another or not, they always extend the
Object class, meaning that we can treat any class as an
Object. So to put that into practice let's declare an array
we'll call stuff, it's type is Object, and we've created
three spots in it. So maybe the first element holds a
reference to an instance of Flight, the next one holds a
reference to a Passenger instance, and we could even add
another one that's a CargoFlight. To see what it's like to
work with Object references, let's go here and declare
Object o, to point to an instance of Passenger. Once we do
that, that same variable o can also be used to point to
an array of Flights. Now to be very clear, on the left we
made an Object array that's pointing to lots of different
class types. On the right here, we're simply saying that
because arrays are classes, we can assign an array to a
variable of type Object. Now we wouldn't have access to
any of the array characteristics of it but we can hold the
reference. We can now take that same o and point it to
an instance of CargoFlight. But again, to reinforce that
idea, remember that when we have a reference of a given
type, we can only access the capabilities that are visible
to that reference. So if I was to try and take o and call
add1Package, a method that's specific to CargoFlight,
that's not going to work, because the reference o doesn't
know anything about this idea of add1Package. Now,
does that mean that the object we created, CargoFlight,
is any less CargoFlight because the reference o can't get to
the CargoFlight capabilities? Of course the answer is no.
Let's see what this means in terms of what's happening here.
Remember that we declared our reference o of type Object,
we newed up a CargoFlight, and of course o then holds a
reference to CargoFlight. So even though o only knows about
Object capabilities, it's still pointing to a CargoFlight
object. So we should be able to get back to those
CargoFlight capabilities. So we can actually do that.
So we can declare a variable, we'll call it cf, and assign
it what's in o. Now if we tried to use this code as it is
here, we would actually get an error, because the compiler
would look at that and say, wait a minute, o can point to
many different types. There's no way for the compiler to
know that there will actually be a CargoFlight in there.
So what we can do is add an explicit cast that says
"I know there's a CargoFlight in there." And we want to
make sure that's true, because if it wasn't true we'd
actually get an error at run time. So what happens
when we make this assignment, we've got our reference cf,
but cf understands CargoFlight, and it ends up pointing to
that same object that was in o, CargoFlight. So now using cf
we can call add1Package. And again, to reinforce this point
here, we want to make sure when we made that assignment
that there really was a CargoFlight in o. If there's any
about that, we can verify it in code. We can wrap this in
a condition that says if(o instanceof CargoFlight).
What that'll do at runtime is it will actually look at the
object pointed to by o and make sure it actually is
a CargoFlight. If it wasn't, we wouldn't have run the code
in there that assigned it to the CargoFlight cf. Now looking
at our Object class, the Object class is not just for
references, it actually has characteristics, it actually has
methods that are built-in. Now we're not going to go into
all these in detail right now, but I just want to make you
aware of them. One of the built-in methods for the Object
class is the clone method. That allows an Object to create
a duplicate of itself. There's some caveats to working with
that that we're going to talk about later on in the course.
Another method that's available to the Object class, and
therefore to all classes, is hashCode. It returns back a
hash code that's useful for working with things like hash
tables and other types that rely on hash tables.
The getClass method returns back type information about
an instance. The finalize method is part of resource
cleanup. In most cases you won't do very much with the
finalize method. Then we have the toString method that
returns back a string of characters representing the
current instance. We're actually going to talk about that
one more in the next module. And the last one is the
equals method, which is used to compare one Object
instance to another. We're actually going to talk about
that one in the next clip.