Let's look at the issue of equality. When we have two
references to objects, what does it mean when we ask
are they equal? And the answer to that is actually,
well, it depends. I'll show you what I mean. Let's have
some code here. Let's first create an instance of the
Flight class, we'll give it a flightNumber of 175 and
assign it to the reference f1. Then we'll create another
instance of the Flight class, give that one a flightNumber
of 175 as well, in this case we assign it to the
reference f2. So f1 and f2 point to two separate instances
of the Flight class, both with a flight number of 175.
So if write the code to say, if(f1 == f2) using the
equivalence operator, equals equals, the comparison
there will resolve to false, because the equals equals
operator performs what's called a reference equals test.
In other words, do both of these references point to the
exact same object instance. So when you use this equals
equals operator, it only resolves to true with reference
types if they're both pointing to the same object.
Remember that we've been talking about the Object class,
and we mentioned that the Object class has an equals
method on there. So maybe that's the answer to how we
compare these to see if they're equal. So we'll do an
if(f1.equals(f2)). If we run this code, what we'll get is
false again. The default implementation of the equals
method, in other words the one that we get from the
Object class, also performs a reference equals test.
In other words, it does the same thing as the equals equals
operator. It only resolves as true if both references point
to the exact same object instance. But the good news is
that, because our Flight class, like all classes, inherits
from the Object class, we can override the equals
method. So let's bring up our Flight class here. Remember
that our Flight class provides two different ways to
identify a flight. A flight can have a flightNumber, or
it can have a flightClass. We don't set both of those,
we only set one or the other. And so the way it would
work is that we would have a flightNumber with no
flightClass, or a flightClass with no flightNumber.
So we're going to say that we're going to consider
two flights to be equal if their identifying information
is the same - they both have the same flightNumber,
without a flightClass, or they both have the same
flightClass without a flightNumber. So what we're going
to do is override the equals method. Now the equals
method returns back a Boolean, so I have a Boolean
return type, our equals method name, and if we look at
the definition of equals in the Object class, the equals
method has one parameter, which is an Object.
Now what we're going to do here is we're going to mark
this with the override annotation, just so the compiler
will double-check us and make sure we've gotten our
signature correct for the equals method. So now when we
call f1.equals(f2),
f2 will be passed into that parameter o.
Now remember that because o is declared as an Object,
it will only have access to members that are known by
Object. It won't have access to the Flight members.
So what we need to do is take that o, cast it to a Flight,
and put it into a reference of type Flight. So that'll be
our other variable here. So now other will have access to
the flight information from f2. So what we're going to do
here then is have the test is that, well, if the
flightNumber for the current instance, which is f1
matches the flightNumber from the one passed in,
which is f2, and the flightClass from both of those match,
we're going to consider them equal. So the idea is that,
if the flightNumber was set, they'll both have the same
flightNumber. The flightClass will have the default value,
which is the null character. If the flightClass was set,
they'll both have the same flightClass, the flightNumber
will have the default value, which will just be a zero.
So we're just going to return back that value, so that now
when we call equals we are now comparing the two Flight
instances based on their identifying information. Now, this
is how we've defined equals in this particular situation.
In your individual programs, you're going to have to
identify what equals means. Because we might have decided
that, for two flights to be equal, not only does their
identifying information have to be the same, but maybe
the number of checked bags also has to be the same.
It's up to us as we define our problem space, and the
problem we're trying to resolve. So now, relying on this
idea that as long as the identifying information is the
same in our equals, if we go back now and look at the code,
first the if(f1 == f2), that's still going to resolve to
false, because that's still a reference equals. It's only
true if both f1 and f2 point to the exact same object.
But now our if(f1.equals(f2)),
that now resolves to true,
because f1 and f2 have the same flightNumber.
But now let's look at another situation. What if we go off
and create an instance of Passenger, and then we say
if(f1.equals(p))?
Since equals accepts an Object as its
parameter type, it's valid for p to be passed into that
parameter o. But what's going to happen now when we try
to cast o into a Flight? It's going to go ahead and create
an error. So one of the things that we have to do is make
sure that in our equals method, we don't try to compare
against any type we can't validly be compared to. Well,
we know that we can take that o and check to see if it's
an instance of the Flight class. What we want to do here
is say that, if it's not an instance of the Flight class,
we just want to get out of here. So what we'll do is just
go ahead and wrap that instanceof comparison in the
not operator, and then if o is not an instance of Flight,
we're just going to go ahead and return false. So our
comparisons that compare two Flight instances won't be
changed, but this situation where we're trying to compare
a Passenger, who can't really be compared with a Flight,
that will now return false. The key thing to understand here
is that we need to override equals to provide our definition
of equal, and the specific definition of equal is going to
be specific to your problem space.