From our discussions in previous modules, we know that Java
offers references that have special meaning, like null
and this. Another one of those special references is the
super reference. Like this, super provides access to the
current object. But where super is different is that super
treats that object as if it's an instance of its base class.
That allows us to access the features of the object as if
our current class has not overridden any of those features.
This comes in really handy when we're implementing
something in our current class and we want to get to the
features or a method exactly as they behaved in the base
class. Let's take a look here at our Flight class.
As you'll recall from the previous clip, we've overridden
the equals method to compare two Flight instances based on
the flight identification information, the flightNumber and
flightClass. Let's look at some code here.
Let's say we go ahead and we create an instance of Flight
with a flightNumber of 175 and assign that to f1. And then
we declare another reference, f2, and assign it f1. So now
f1 and f2 are pointing to the exact same Flight instance.
So now if we say if(f1.equals(f2)), that's going to call in
to our equals method, and now what's it going to do?
It's going to go through everything we've written inside of
equals. It's going to first make sure it's actually
an instance of Flight, it's then going to cast the flight
passed in, and then we're going to compare the values
of flightNumber and flightClass. Now in this case,
the work that we're doing there is not that substantial,
but in some cases an equals method may have to test
a lot of things. In a complex object, there may be a number
of fields to compare, and other operations that you have
to go on. The thing is that we know the base class Object
implements a version of equals that just checks to see if
two references point to the same object, and reference
comparisons like that are actually really inexpensive.
So it would be great if inside our equals method, maybe what
we could do is say well, if the reference passed in points
to the same object that we currently do, we know they
must be equal because they're the same object. Let's just
get out of here. So let's update our equals method to do
that. So let's go ahead and make a little room inside our
equals method here, and what we'll do is put an if at the
very beginning, and we'll simply say equals(o)
and if that returns true, we'll then, in turn return true.
Now of course the problem here is that as we've written this
when we call equals inside this if statement, what are we
going to do? We're going to call back into our own equals
method, which will then again call back into our own equals
method, and just do that repeatedly, actually until we crash
wth an error. What we really want to do is, at this point,
call equals as it was implemented in our base class,
and that's where the super reference comes in. So we go
ahead and move that equals over and we put super in front
of it. What will happen now is that when we call into the
Flight implementation of equals, the first thing that we do
inside of that implementation is call into our base class
implementation, which compares to see if both references
point to the same object. If they do, we just exit out of
here. If we didn't, we would go through and then do the
other tests that we've built inside our equals
implementation. So we've been able to access that base class
behavior when we wanted to, but still have our overridden
behavior when we needed it.