As we've seen, Java makes it
very easy to extend classes and override methods. In fact,
by default, all classes can be extended, and when you
inherit from a class, you have the option of using the
methods as they were written in the base class, or
overriding them. But sometimes that may not be what you
want. Maybe you want to put more controls on that.
It turns out that a class can change these defaults. It can
control whether it's allowed to be extended, and how
overriding methods works. One way it does that is using
what's called final. Final allows us to prevent inheriting
of an entire class, or the overriding of certain methods.
Let's take a look.
Let's say we have our class here, our
Passenger class we've seen before. And let's say we've
decided that, you know, we don't want to allow any
specialization of the passenger class. We don't want to
allow anyone to extend this class. Well, all we have to
do is take the Passenger class and mark it as final.
By marking it as final, simply put, you cannot inherit
from it any more. You're not allowed to extend that class.
One thing to note, though, is that the order of public and
final here doesn't matter. If we want to we can switch the
order of those, it still has the exact same effect. So
marking classes as final is a very simple thing. It
simply blocks extending that class. But very commonly
what we want to do is allow a class to be inherited from,
but have certain methods we do not want to allow them to
change. Let's take a look at our CargoFlight class here.
Say we want to go ahead and allow people to inherit
from CargoFlight and specialize CargoFlight, but we want
to make sure that they don't change the way that adding
a package works. So what we can do is take our add1Package
method and just mark that method as final. By marking the
method as final, now you can inherit from CargoFlight, but
you cannot override add1Package. You can go ahead and
override other methods that might be in the class if you
have access to them, but in the case of CargoFlight,
there are no other methods that you can override because
add1Package is final, and hasCargoSpace and handleNoSpace
are both private, so a deriving class couldn't change those.
Now, methods that are inherited from Flight could be
overridden. So we're just very selectively blocking what
can be overridden. In the case of final, you'll generally
either mark the class as final, or an individual method
as final. Once a class is final, there's no reason to mark
individual methods as final, because you can't override
anything if you can't inherit from it. So final is a method
or class situation. Now there may be another situation
where, instead of trying to prevent inheritance, you want
to go ahead and require inheritance. That's where abstract
comes in. Abstract allows you to require that a class be
inherited, and require that a particular method be
overridden. Let's see what that looks like. Let's create a
new class here. We'll call it Pilot. So we'll have our
Pilot class, and we'll go ahead and, a pilot can fly a
flight, so we'll have a currentFlight field. And we'll add
a method called fly that accepts that flight. And what we'll
say is well, if the pilot can accept that flight, we'll go
ahead and assign the flight to currentFlight. If they
can't, we'll go ahead and just handle that case if they
can't accept it. For handleCantAccept, we'll just do what
we've been kind of doing, simply printing out a message.
But when it comes down to the idea of whether the pilot
can accept the flight or not, that's going to depend on
what kind of pilot it is. And we want to leave that to the
classes that inherit from pilot. So what we'll do is we'll
go ahead and mark something as public and we're going
to say now, abstract. And then we provide our standard
method signature. And so it's a public method called
canAccept, returns a Boolean. But by saying it's abstract
we're saying that we're not going to provide an
implementation. Now since we're not going to provide an
implementation, what we do is that, rather than providing
a method body, we just put a semicolon at the end.
So we're just simply saying that, the class Pilot has a
method called canAccept. We don't know what the
implementation of that method is, but it has that method.
What that allows us to do is to use canAccept in other
methods in the class, like in this case the fly method.
Now once you mark a method as abstract, that means the
entire class must be abstract, so we'll go ahead and mark
the class as abstract as well. So when it comes to abstract,
if you have an abstract method you have to mark the class
as abstract. It's possible to mark a class as abstract and
have no abstract methods, but that's not very common.
Normally you'll have one or more abstract methods in any
abstract class. So now the way we work this, let's go ahead
and define a Pilot we'll call our CargoOnlyPilot that
extends our Pilot class. Because it extends our Pilot class,
it has to provide an implementation for canAccept. So we'll
go ahead and set that up, we'll go ahead and use the
override annotation, and what we'll say inside of here is
that a CargoOnlyPilot is not allowed to have passengers.
So we'll take the flight, call getPassengers, and we only
return true for canAccept if there are no passengers at all.
Then we have another class called FullLicensePilot, and
he's kind of our super pilot, he's allowed to fly any
flight. So we'll override canAccept for him, go ahead and
mark it with the override annotation, and he's simply
going to return true all the time, saying he's allowed to
fly any flight. So it allowed us to define basic
characteristics and behaviors in the Pilot class, but then
require specific specializations in any derived class.