An issue that's very important to understand as we look at
the idea of inheriting one class from another, is that in
Java, constructors are not inherited. Each class is
responsible for defining its own constructors. A derived
class, though, must always call one of the base class
constructors. So as you define the constructors inside
of your derived class, there's always going to be a call
back to a base class constructor. Now that call does not
have to be explicit. If you don't have an explicit call to
a base class constructor, then it will use the base class's
no-argument constructor. But you can call a specific
constructor if you want to. You simply use the super
notation, followed by the list of parameters that correspond
to the base class constructor that you want to call. You do
have to make that the first line in your constructor though.
Let's see what this looks like in code. Now we've looked at
our Flight class, we've done a bunch of work with that
until now. And I want to focus in on the no-argument
constructor and its constructor that accepts the
flightNumber. That allows us to create code that creates
an instance of Flight, in this case, creating a new flight
with flightNumber 175. Now our CargoFlight class, that has
a number of members inside of it, has no constructors to
find. That of course means that we can create an instance
of CargoFlight using a no-argument constructor, because
Java provides a no-argument constructor for us by default
if we haven't specified one. But if we try to go off and
create a CargoFlight with a flightNumber, that's not going
to work. We get an error, because even though our base
class, Flight, has a constructor that accepts a flightNumber
CargoFlight does not. So if we want to be able to create
CargoFlights with a flightNumber, we need to define a
constructor in CargoFlight that accepts the flightNumber.
Now we don't have to do that work ourself. As we said
we can delegate that to the base class by simply using that
super notation and passing in flightNumber. And so now
we can go ahead and construct our CargoFlight with a
flightNumber, in this case 294. That calls into our
CargoFlight's constructor accepting a flightNumber,
which in turn calls the implementation inside of Flight.
Now we can of course extend behavior beyond the base
class constructors. For example, our CargoFlight class
keeps track of the idea of the maximum cargo space.
So we could go off and define a CargoFlight constructor
that accepts flightNumber and a value that we want to
use for maxCargoSpace. Now inside of the CargoFlight
constructor, we can of course set maxCargoSpace.
If we want to go ahead and call up to the base class
constructor, we again use the super notation, but it
has to be the first line of the constructor. So this would
call into the Flight constructor that accepts a flightNumber
and then sets maxCargoSpace. But in this situation, rather
than call into the base class, we've already done work
inside of our class to create a constructor that accepts
a flightNumber, so rather than call super in this case,
it would be better to go ahead and use this. So now
if we go off and we create code that says I want to
create a CargoFlight instance that accepts a flightNumber
and maxCargoSpace, it'll call our CargoFlight constructor,
that accepts those two parameters. We will then call up
to our CargoFlight constructor that accepts the flightNumber
and then that calls into the base class constructor that
accepts flightNumber. Now something that's happened is
that as we've added these two constructors to CargoFlight
we've broken a line of code, right? The line of code where
we've created a CargoFlight passing in no parameters
no longer works. If we want to have that we need to go
ahead and add that to our CargoFlight class. So now
this code would build again, and when we call into our
CargoFlight constructor, it will then call into our Flight
class's constructor that takes no arguments, right?
And that happens because we did not specify any base
class constructor. So let's say we add another constructor
to our CargoFlight. This one accepts only cargo space, and
all we do inside of here is set maxCargoSpace. So if we now
create a line of code that news up a CargoFlight, passing in
only maxCargoSpace, what does this do? Well, it calls our
constructor, but before it executes the body of our
constructor, it will call up to the Flight class's
constructor that has no arguments, and then run the rest
of our constructor. So it always calls into a base class
constructor, even when we don't specify one.