In this demo, we're going to use what we've learned in
this module to see if we can make our CalcEngine program
a little bit easier to manage and maintain.
Here we are inside of our CalcEngine program, and what I
want to focus on is this MathEquation class. If we take a
look at this class, it has a number of distinct
responsibilities. Some that are common to all operations,
and some things that are specific to an individual
operation. If we look here, first of all it declares all the
fields necessary to do the work. Then it has to have
getters and setters for all those fields. Then it has the
variety of constructors. Then if we scroll down here
towards the bottom, we get to this execute method
which actually is doing a number of different things.
And what I've found, when you see code like this, where
you've got a big condition like this, and there's individual
tasks inside of there, as a program gets more complex
and you start to work inside this method, this is a place
where, very often, enhancing or modifying the program
will introduce errors. Because we've got a bunch of kind of
loosely related code kind of clumped together. This is a
great opportunity for us to use the class inheritance
features of Java, and have a better division of
responsibilities. So what I want to do is go here and
go ahead and add a new class. We're going to call this
class CalculateBase. Just going to go ahead and new this
guy up, and as I mentioned we'll call this class
CalculateBase and based on its name you can tell that
it's probably going to be a base class. So other classes
are going to inherit from it. That's not a requirement,
it's just something I tend to do when I know a class is
going to be used only as a base class. This class will
actually act as a common point of inheritance from all
of our separate operations. So the thing that's going to
be common to all of these operations is the series of
fields we need to declare, leftVal, rightVal, and result.
In addition to that, we're going to have getters and setters
for each of those fields. So that takes care of the fields.
And now we need some constructors. And we'll of course
want our no-argument constructor, so we'll just say
public calculateBase and then give it an empty body.
Let's go ahead and create our other constructor. We'll
call this one publicCalculateBase, and in this one we want
to get our leftVal and our rightVal. And of course inside of
here, we're going to go ahead and set those into the fields.
So now we have all of our value management, the ability
to store the values we need, store the result, get and set
those values and result, and then construct the instance of
calculateBase. The next thing we want to do is have this
idea of performing an actual operation, actually do a
calculate. But the way we actually calculate will be
different for each class that inherits from this. So what
we're going to do is go ahead and create a void method
called calculate, but because there's no single definition
of calculate, we're going to go ahead and make this one
abstract. And of course as an abstract method it has an
empty body, and because there's an abstract method,
we need to go ahead and make the class abstract as well.
So that gives us our base class for all of our operations.
Now let's go ahead and create a class that inherits from
calculate base that does the individual operation.
Let's start with Adder. So again, we'll add a new class,
we'll call it Adder. So it will extend calculateBase.
So inside of here we want to have the constructors
we need, so again we'll have the no-argument constructor.
And then we'll have the constructor that accepts left and
right values. And inside of here, we're just going to call
up to our base class constructor that accepts those same
values. So with that simple bit of code we've now taken
care of kind of linking this derived class to the base class
and passing the values we need into the base class.
So now the last thing to do here is just go ahead and
implement calculate for this implementation. So we'll
go ahead and call it public void calculate, so we have our
method there. Let's go ahead and put the override annotation
on here. So now inside of here, we'll go ahead and implement
the way an Adder does its calculate, and all we're going
to do is add the two values together. So we'll declare a
local variable here. So now we've got to perform this
operation. If I try to use leftVal and rightVal directly,
it's not going to work because those are marked as
private inside the base class. What we can do though
is go ahead and use the getters. So we'll say
getLeftVal, and we'll add that to getRightVal.
Inside of here we'll go ahead and store that in the result,
so we'll simply call our setResult and pass in value.
And that's our complete Adder implementation. And you see
what we've done here is that the Adder class is very focused
on a very specific capability, adding values together.
If we go ahead and create a Subtractor it's going to be
very much the same, so we'll go ahead and add that class in.
Again, we'll call it Subtractor.
So Subtractor will again extend CalculateBase. We'll have
those same constructors we had before. We have the
no-argument constructor and then one to accept the
left and right value. Again we're going to go ahead and
override calculate, and then inside of here we're simply
going to subtract one value from the other and store it
back in result. And then we're going to do that same thing
with a Divider and a Multiplier. So we now have the four
operations - the Adder we created earlier, Subtractor,
and then if I look at Divider, it looks just like the other
classes except calculate does division. And Multiplier,
it looks just like the other classes except calculate
does multiplication. So we now have our four classes
that inherit from CalculateBase. Let's go to our main method
now and let's go ahead and use these classes. I just want to
scroll down here to the end. The first thing we'll do is
just go ahead and print out a little message in the output
window so we can see where the results for our new code
starts. So we simply print out that message using
inheritance. And then here, we'll go ahead and do the work
that we can do using our new classes. So remember that all
of our classes inherit from CalculateBase. Let's go ahead
and declare an array of type CalculateBase. So we have our
array, its name is calculators. Let's go ahead and use the
bracket-style initialization syntax. So what we'll do inside
of here is just new up each one of our classes. So first
I'll new up a Divider that accepts 100 and 50, then put
a comma. Now let's go ahead and new up an Adder, and
we'll go ahead and new up a Subtractor and a Multiplier
as well. So now we have all four operations in here.
Just going to go ahead move this divider over so it lines
up with the rest of them. So our CalculateBase can do
all four operations, and we're using the same values
here we used earlier when we were using our MathEquation
class. So now with that set up, what we can do now is
we can now loop through that array. Let's go ahead
and do a for loop. We'll declare
a variable calculateBase called calculator that's going to
loop through our calculators. Then inside of here. all
we're going to do is for each calculator, call its
calculate method, and then we'll print out the result
for each one. And so now we have new, complete
functionality using the four basic operations. So if I
go ahead and run this now, our program completes,
let's just enlarge this output window a little bit so we
can see. And we see we have our four results here.
Dividing 100 by 50 gives us 2. Adding 25 and 92 gives us
117. 225 minus 17 gives us 208.
And multiplying 11 by 3 gives us 33.
So everything works just as expected.
And everything works just as it did before. The key
difference here is this idea of manageability and
maintainability. Kind of localization of responsibility.
If I go into my MathEquation, again this execute method
is reasonably complex given the simple things that we're
doing, and it's this kind of code that easily breaks when
you're enhancing a program or changing a program.
If we compare that execute method to the Adder class's
calculate, which is two very simple lines, you see that
changing behaviors are going to be much simpler in
this environment as a result of having used inheritance
and then specialization in the derived classes.