In Java, when you call a method and you pass parameters
into it, those parameter values are actually copied
down into the parameter.
This is something we call "passing by value"
What that means is that, because a copy is actually
passed down there, any changes you make
to the value of the parameter inside the method
are not visible outside of the method itself.
Let's see how that affects us when we're working
with Primitive Types.
So let's imagine we have a
method here we're going to call Swap.
Swap accepts two integer parameters, I and J.
Then we'll set up some code to call it,
so in our coded calls, we'll first have
a variable declared called val1,
that we set to 10, which of course allocates out
some memory with a value of 10 inside of it.
Do another one val2, set to 20.
Which again allocates memory with a value 20 in it.
Of course if we print those values out,
the value of val1 will be 10 and
the value of val2 will be 20.
So, now if we call that method Swap,
passing in val1 and val2, when control get passed
down to the Swap method, memory for the parameter I
is allocated, and the value of val1 is copied
down into that memory for I.
Same thing for J, the value for val2 gets copied
down into the memory allocated for J.
So now, if inside a Swap, we do something like
allocate a local variable called K
that assigns the value of I, well K will then
get the value of 10, right, the value currently held in I.
If we then say I equals J, that means take the value
that's in J, 20, put that into I, so I becomes 20.
We then say, J equals K, the value that's in K ,10,
goes into J, which now becomes 10.
So, down inside the method Swap, if we print these
values out, the value printed out for I will be 20,
the value that's currently there.
Same thing is we print out J, the value printout is 10,
the value that is currently there.
Notice that all the changes that occur within the method
are occurring inside the copies associated with the
parameters, not the original values.
Alright, so when we exit out of this method, and
pass control back, all those copies are cleaned up.
So val1 and val2 still have their original values.
So if print this out, val1 still has 10, val2 still has 20.
Because again, things were passed into the method as copies.
Now, what about classes, we know classes behave
a little bit differently than Primitive Types, because
remember that classes work with references.
Right, so, let's say with have a class here that
we've been working with, Flight.
And let's just focus in on its field flight number.
And we'll assume we've got an accessor
and mutator set up for that.
And we've got that constructor that accepts a flight
number and of course sets the field with it.
Now we're not going to worry about any of the
other members in flight right now.
Okay, so really focus on flight and flight number here.
So, now, let's again say we have a method called Swap,
but now our method Swap accepts flight references.
Right, a flight, first one's I, second on is J.
So, now if we want to call it from our code,
we will allocate out a val1, which is a new flight
with the flight number set to 10.
Alright, so what's that going to do?
Well, it's going to allocate out memory.
That's our variable, but then we remember that we allocate
out the class instance itself separately, and then
assign a reference into the variable.
So we have another flight instance here, val2.
Where it again allocates out the place to hold the
reference, the actual flight object itself,
and then associates that reference.
So now, val1 and val 2 are not the flights themselves,
they're references to the flights.
So, of course, if I print those out,
things are what we expect.
Where val1's flight number is 10, val2 flight number is 20.
But now when we call in the swap,
we pass val1 and val2, what's going to happen is actually
the same as what happened with our Primitive Types.
We're going to have that memory called I that's allocated.
We're going to copy what's in val1.
Well, what's in val1 is the reference.
Alright, so it's going to point to that same object,
flight number.
For val2, we'll copy that into J,
again we're copying the reference,
which points to the other flight with flight number 20.
If we look at our code now, if we do the same sort of thing.
If we allocate a local variable called K
and we assign what's inside of I.
Well, what's inside of I is a reference to that
first flight object, the one with value 10.
If we then say I equals J, well I now stops pointing
at the original flight, and points to the same one that
J points to, the one with the flight number of 20.
We say J equals K, well J stops pointing to the one with 20,
points to the one that K points to,
which is the one with 10.
So inside of our method here, we print out the flight
number of the one pointed to by I, right, that's 20.
The one pointed to by J is 10.
But notice that we're swapping the references around.
We still haven't affected the original val1 and val2.
Alright, so when we exit out of Swap,
val1 still points to the one with the flight number of 10.
Val2 still points to the one with flight number of 20.
So we print those out, nothing has changed.
Val1 is 10, val2 has 20.
So, we're copying these values into the parameters,
causing us not to be able to change them inside the methods.
So that tells us that, changes to the values of parameters
inside of a method, don't affect the original values.
It doesn't matter whether it's a Primitive Type
or a class instance.
But what's important to realize is that,
although we can't change the actual parameters themselves,
we pass classes in, any changes we make
to the members of classes inside of a method, do stick.
Those do take hold. Those are visible outside of the method.
Let's take a look at why.
If we look here, that same thing we were doing before.
We're going to create an instance of our flight class.
With a value of 10.
Right, sets up things just like before.
Where val1 is a reference, pointing into an instance
of flight with a flight number of 10.
Val2 points to another one, right so,
val2 is reference pointing to an instance with
a flight number of 20.
We print them out, everything's the same as before.
Val1 is 10. Val2 is 20.
Our method this time, we're going to change
its name to Swap Numbers.
And what we want to do inside of here is swap the flight
numbers between the flight instances.
Alright, so when we call into this guy, again we're still
copying the values of the parameters.
So I still gets a copy of the reference
that was inside of val1.
J still gets a copy of the reference that's inside of val2.
But now in our code here, we're going to change the members.
So if I have an integer called K this time,
and we call I Get Flight Number
Well that takes the reference out by I
goes up to the object instance that it points to.
And that gets back the number 10.
And puts that inside of K.
So now if I say, I dot Set Flight Number,
and I pass as a parameter J dot Get Flight Number,
well, let's look at that from the inside out.
When we call J dot Get Flight Number, that takes
the reference that's stored in J, follows it up to the
object instance, gets that number that's in there,
which is 20, and then we work to the outside.
I dot Set Flight Number takes the reference
that's held in I, goes up to the object instance it
points to, the one currently with 10, but when we
call Set Flight Number, it becomes 20.
So you see that we didn't change the parameter, right.
The parameter is still a copy.
But because we're following the reference that's in
the parameter, we can change the
object that it's pointing to.
So if we now say that j.setflightnumber of K.
Well, we get the value that's in K, which is 10.
We take the reference that's stored in J,
follow it up to the object that it points to,
and we set its flight number, it now becomes 10.
Alright, so inside of the method if we print these out,
things are changed as they've always been.
The flight number of the flight instance pointed to by
I is 20, the one pointed to by J is 10.
But the key is because we followed the references in
and changed the actual objects, as we exit out of here,
even up where we called the method, those changes now stick.
So the flight pointed to by val1 has the value 20.
The change that occurred down inside the method.
The flight pointed to by val2 also has the change,
the value of 10, the changes occurred down inside the method.