As we've been working in different classes
throughout this course, we've seen that a given class
can have multiple constructors.
And that same idea can be extended to methods.
Where a class can have the same method name
appear multiple times.
And this is a concept called Overloading.
The ability to use different parameter lists
with a given method name or the constructor.
Now, the system has to have some way of identifying
what constructor or what method you want to use.
And what it uses is a concept called a signature.
It's that each constructor or method
must have a unique signature.
And the signature is made up of three parts.
Now, one part is the number of parameters.
And we saw this previously
when we were working with our passenger class.
Right, our passenger class had multiple constructors.
The first constructor here has no parameters at all.
We had another constructor that accepted the number
of free bags, so that had just one parameter.
And then we had another version of the constructor
that accepted free bags and checked bags,
so it had two parameters.
So the system was able to figure out which constructor
we wanted to use, based on the number of parameters
we passed to the constructor.
Now, we're not limited to just the number of parameters.
The signature is also affected
by the type of each parameter.
And we got to see this earlier
when we were working our flight class.
And our flight class had, again,
a constructor that took no parameters.
A constructor that took just the flight number,
so that was an integer parameter, but only one parameter.
And another constructor that also has only one parameter,
but this was a char for the flight class.
So, it's not just the number of the parameters,
but also the type of the parameters.
And the final part to identifying the signature is the name.
Now, when it comes to constructors,
the name doesn't really matter so much,
because it always has to match the class name.
But, when it comes to methods,
the name is actually a really important part of that,
because a given class can have multiple methods,
each with their own unique name.
But that one method name can also have different
numbers of parameters and parameters of varying types.
And we'll see some examples of that in our next clip.