Let's take a look at our flight class, and see how
we might be able to use Overloading to improve this class.
Remember that we have the idea of our seats are 150,
and we keep track of the number of passengers.
And we've had that method that we wrote
much earlier in the course, called Add One Passenger,
where we just make sure that there's enough seats
for one more passenger.
If so, we add them, and if not, we go ahead and
just handle that, which is just kind of report an error.
Well, as we look ahead to maybe making this flight class
a little bit more sophisticated, this idea of checking
whether there's enough seats to add another passenger,
is something that we may have to reuse a lot.
So, why don't we go ahead and make that its own method.
So we'll have a method called Has Seating.
Inside of there, we'll just put that check in for is
the number of passengers less than
the number of seats available.
And what we'll do is we'll update our Add One Passenger
to go ahead and use that Has Seating method.
So, now as we're keeping track of what's going on with
our flight, one of the things we might want to keep track of
is the number of total checked bags.
Now, we're not going to limit the number of checked bag,
but we are going to keep track of it.
But, something that we might want to limit
is the idea of carry-ons.
What we're going to do is we're going to set the maximum
number of carry-ons to whatever twice
the number of seats are.
Right, no one's supposed to have more than two carry-ons.
Then we'll go ahead and keep track of that total carry-ons.
Let's go ahead and add a method that just allows us to check
to see that based on the number of carry-ons someone has,
is there space for them.
So, all we'll do is just take how many total carry-ons we
already have, how many carry-ons they're trying to bring on,
as long as that doesn't exceed our maximum carry-ons
we'll go ahead and let them do it.
And then of course we have all the other
members we've seen previously.
So, I want to focus in on the idea of Add One Passenger.
Because now that we're keeping track of things like
total checked bags and carry-on, the idea of adding a
passenger is going to be a bit more sophisticated.
Let's go ahead and move this off to the side.
Now we're still the same Add One Passenger
we were just looking at, nothing has changed there.
Let's add a little bit more space to work here.
So now, if we think about overloading Add One Passenger.
Well, keeping track of checked bags is going to be
important, so let's add an Overload
that accepts one integer, and that's the number of bags.
And the logic inside there would be,
well we'll call our existing Add One Passenger.
Do that work.
And then we'll add how many bags they've checked
to the total checked bags.
Now, one interesting thing about what we're doing here
is that it's possible that we tried to add that passenger
and there wasn't enough seats available.
But in this case, we'd go ahead and
increase the total checked bags.
So, what we can do is go ahead wrap our code here
so that we check the Has Seating before
we do any of that other work.
And this shows us a couple of things.
First of all, notice that when we wanted to access
the Overload Add One Passenger that took no arguments,
there was no special syntax for that.
It wasn't like constructors where we had a special key word.
Here, we just call the method name
with the right number of parameters.
Also, notice that, when you're calling from one
overloaded method to another overload of that same method,
there's no rules about where it has to be.
Remember when we were talking about constructors,
the chaining of constructors had to be
the first line in the constructor.
Here, it's just kind of a method call.
You can call it from anywhere in the body
of your method you need to.
Remember that we also have the idea of a passenger class.
If we're running a method to add one passenger, it
should probably accept an instance of the passenger class.
Now, we're not really going to do anything special here,
all we're going to do is call the Add One Passenger
that accepts and integer for checked bags.
So, we just call on our passenger get checked bags,
and pass that in.
This shows us another interesting thing
about method overloading.
Our Add One Passenger that accepted integer number of bags,
alright that was adding new functionality.
That was functionality that we did not have before.
The idea of keeping track of
the total number of checked bags.
But our Add One Passenger that accepts just
a passenger instance, we certainly could have required
someone who's using our flight class to simply call
Get Checked Bags themselves on Passenger.
But that's something we do very commonly, is that
overloads sometimes are just used to add convenience.
Alright, so the one that accepts the Passenger
reference is a convenience overload.
So, someone didn't have to call Get Checked Bags themselves.
The one that accepts the integer number
of bags actually adds functionality.
So, as we look at adding functionality, another thing
we want to keep track of is this idea of carry-ons.
Alright so we have an overload here now that takes
the number of checked bags and the number of carry-ons.
So, we'll check to see if we have seating.
We'll go ahead and call the Add One Passenger
that accepts an integer number of bags.
And then we'll add the functionality
to increase the total number of carry-ons.
Now, one of the things we want to do here of course,
is that before we add the passenger,
not only do we want to check for available seating,
but we also want to make sure
that we have space for their carry-on.
Again, this is an overload that's adding new functionality,
validating that we have space for the carry-on
and then keeping track of that total number of carry-ons.
And then we'll have another convenience overload here, that
accepts Passenger reference and the number of carry-ons.
And all that's going to do is call up to the implementation
of Add One Passenger that accepts an integer number
of bags and number of carry-ons.
So our classes got a lot more sophisticated here now.
The idea of adding a passenger can do a lot more things,
as opposed to just keeping count of
the number of passengers.
We're asking it to keep track of checked bags,
the number of carry-ons, and even limit
how many carry-ons can get onto that flight.
So, let's focus in now on, not just the implementation,
but kind of just the signatures.
Remember the signature is the thing determines
which implementation of an overload gets called.
So, focusing in on just the signatures of these,
let's go ahead and make some rooms here.
So, I've just pushed them all together.
These are the same exact methods we were just looking at.
So we have just those five overloads of Add One Passenger.
And let's see how might get used in a program.
So let's add some code here that
goes ahead and creates a flight.
Let's first create a passenger.
And we're passing in zero and one to the constructor.
Reminder is the zero is how many free checked bags they get,
so in this case they get zero, none.
And how many bags they're checking, which is one.
Create another passenger that gets zero free bags,
but they are checking two bags.
So, we've got this all created.
So, now if I call on flight, Add One Passenger,
well this is the one with no parameters,
so it's nice and easy to know which one that chooses.
It just calls the implementation of
Add One Passenger that accepts no parameters.
I call Add One Passenger passing an integer.
Okay, well there's only one parameter here,
so there are two possible overloads that can handle that.
Right, the one that accepts integer,
and the one that accepts passenger.
But since we're passing an integer,
it'll use the integer overload.
Similarly, when I call the Add One Passenger
passing in a reference to a passenger,
it will call the overload that accepts a passenger.
But let's go another step.
Let's declare a local variable of type Short,
called Three Bags that we set to three.
Now, when I call Add One Passenger passing in three bags
as the first parameter, or short, and then two
in integer as the second parameter,
well there are two possible overloads here
that accept two parameters, right?
One that accepts two integers,
and one that accepts a passenger and an integer.
Notice there is no overload that accepts the short.
So how's the system decide which one to call?
Well, it starts looking for the automatic conversions
that it's able to perform.
Remember back in module three we talked about
kind of these idea of automatic type conversions?
Well, very similar rules are applied here
in order to determine how to find the overload.
So, what happens is that since the system
knows how to convert a short into an int,
it will go ahead and call the overload that accepts
an integer as the first parameter.
And then finally, if we call Add One Passenger
passing in a passenger and an integer,
and of course calls the appropriate overload for that.
The one that accepts a passenger, and an integer.