In this demo, we'll take a look at how we can use
method overloading to improve our CalcEngine program.
Here we are in our Math Equation class, and you'll
recall that we created this with three constructors.
One that accepts no parameters,
one that accepts just the op code, and one that
accepts the op code and both values we want to operate on.
Now, the way this works is that if when you create
the math equation, if you know the op code and both values
when you create it, things are nice and easy to use.
But, if you only know the op code at the time you create it,
and then later when you're ready to execute, you then
have the values, we're a little bit cumbersome to use.
Because you have to create, with the constructor
that accepts the op code, and then you have to call
Set Left Value, the left value set up, right.
Call Set Right Value to set up the right val.
Then we scroll down here a little bit.
Then finally you call execute.
Well it seems very likely that there'll be a lot of
situations where we might create an instance of
our math equation with a particular op code
and then when it's time to execute
we'd have both of the values we want.
It would be nice to be able to go ahead and
just pass in those two values as part of the execute.
Alright, so this is a great opportunity
to provide an overload of our execute method.
So, we have the one currently that takes no parameters.
Let's add an execute method that accepts two parameters,
the left val and the right val.
So that's going to be really easy for us to do here.
We're just going to declare public, void, execute,
and then we're simply going to have parameters
for the left val and the right val.
So you have both those parameters.
Let's go ahead and put the body of it here.
And all we need to do inside of here is set
the field left val to the value of the parameter left val.
Do the same thing for the right val.
And then call the other execute implementation.
So, now, in this scenario where we have
the op code at construction time, but the two values
at the time we're ready to execute,
we can do that kind of all in one step.
So, let's go over to our main program here.
And we've got the existing code that we worked with before.
What I want to do first of all before we do the actual work,
I'm just going to put a couple of print statements in here,
just to print out the message in the output window,
so we can differentiate what we've done with the array
previously with the new work we're doing with the overloads.
Let's go ahead and declare a reference
to our Math Equation class,
we'll call this one Equation Overload.
And what we'll do is just new open instance
of the math equation with the dividing op code.
So, we've got that there.
Now, before we use that, let's just go ahead
and declare a couple of doubles up here.
So we have a variable called Left Double set to 9.0
and a variable called Right Double set to 4.0.
What you want to do here is that go ahead
and perform the actual calculation.
Right, now as I said before what we'd have to do
is call Set Left Value and Set Right Value each time.
Now it gets really easy.
We'll just say Equation Overload.
We'll say dot execute.
And what we're going to do is pass in the two values,
Left Double and Right Double.
From there we can just go ahead and print the values out.
So we simply call execute, passing in the values.
Go ahead and just get the result back as we print it out.
Alright, so f we run this, it's going to work
just like we would expect it.
And we see there in our output window under Using Overloads,
we see a result of 2.25,
so that works just as we had expected.
But now what happens if, instead of using doubles here,
I declare a couple of integers instead?
So they're just basically the same values
that I had before with the doubles.
So if I copy these lines that we used with the doubles,
and what I want to do here is where I have
Left Double and Right Double.
Let's switch that to Left Int and Right Int.
So, now the question is, will that work?
Since I've declared my execute method to accept doubles,
I'm passing an int, is that going to work?
So let's go ahead and run it, see what happens.
And we see that it does work.
Our result with the integers is also 2.25.
And the reason being is that,
that's what we call a widening conversion.
Remember, earlier in the course, we talked about
calculations, how there were some
automatic type conversions that can occur.
Since a double is wider than an int, other words
a double can hold anything that's inside of an int,
the system can go ahead and infer that conversion
and go ahead and call the method that accepts doubles,
even though we're passing in ints.
Now there is one thing that's kind of curious, though.
Let me just run this again real quick.
Our result of dividing the integer nine by
the integer four is being printed out as 2.25.
We remember that in our integer arithmetic
that we learned earlier in the course,
that should actually just be two.
When you divide two integer values,
you don't get a decimal point.
You only get the whole portion of that.
So, to make our Math Equation class more effective,
what we should really do is provide another
overload of Execute that accepts two integers.
So, we go over here, and want to again copy this one
that we have here now that accepts the doubles.
And we'll go ahead and paste that in again.
And what I want to do here is convert
each of these doubles to be ints.
So we now have an overload that accepts integers.
But now if we were to run this right now,
nothing would be any different.
Because even though we're passing integers in
at the parameter level, when we make the assignments
to the fields they're going to convert
to doubles again anyway.
Well, what happens when you do division with integer values?
Right, you get a truncated value.
So, what we can do here is that after we call execute,
the value that's going to be the result would be 2.25.
Well, if we could truncate that, then our Math Equation
class would provide the right answer for integer division.
What I can do here, is I can take my current field results.
I'm going to assign it the value of results.
But, what I'm going to do here is cast it to an int.
And what that does is it takes that double value of 2.25,
by casting it to an int, it gets truncated becoming two,
that two then gets assigned back into result as 2.0.
Because again, result's a double.
Now what should happen when I go back to my program here,
now when I run this second call to execute
that passes in integers, I should get
a proper answer for integer.
And you notice now the result is two.
Now it displays as 2.0 because
it's being stored as a double.
But it's giving us the right behavior
for dividing two integers.
So, let's go one step further, now.
So, I'm going to go ahead and copy these same three lines
here again, where I passed the integers in.
So I copy that.
And I'm going to go ahead and paste that in.
So, now on this third call, what I want to do, is I'm going
to go ahead and cast this first one to a double.
Now, what happens there is I'm now calling execute
with a double as one parameter
and an int as another parameter.
Well which one's it going to select?
Right, if I go back to my Math Equation class,
if I look at my executes.
Well, I can't pass a double into an int.
Because that would be a narrowing conversion,
that's not legal.
But, I do know I can pass an int into a double.
So the system will actually choose the one that accepts
two doubles, because that's the only one
that can accept all the parameters.
Alright, so now if I go ahead and run this,
we see we get 2.25 for that last one.
The system had to pick the best overload
of all those that were available.
The one for which there was a valid way
to pass all the parameters.
In practice, the mechanism that Java uses
to resolve method overloads is pretty intuitive.
In most cases, it's going to pick the one that you expect.
But the implementation of how that is resolved
is actually quite complex because there is a lot of,
kind of, nuances to what can go on.
If you're interested in all the details of exactly how
the system chooses a particular overload, I've put a URL
on the screen that references the specifications
for Java on exactly how that works.
It's really kind of interesting,
and it's actually quite complex.
But if you're interested in learning more about it,
I encourage you to check out that URL.