As we've seen, overloading allows us to pass
differing parameter lists to a particular method name.
But what happens if we don't know exactly
how many parameters we need to handle in a method?
Let's take a look here at our Flight class.
Now, up until now, whenever we wanted to add passengers
to a flight, we always had to add them one at a time.
But what if we wanted to add a method called Add Passengers
that accepted however many passengers
we needed to add at a time.
It could be one passenger,
it could be two, it could be five.
Well it seems that the most logical way
to handle that is an array.
So we'll go ahead and have our Add Passengers
method accept an array of passenger.
One thing we'll need to do is an extra helper method here.
Up until now, we've only had to check
whether one more passenger could be added.
Now we need to check and see if multiple
passengers can be added.
So, we'll create our own private overload
of Has Seating that now accepts a count.
And all it'll do is just make sure that there's room
to add that many more passengers.
So the first thing we'll do in our Add Passengers
method is just call Has Seating, passing in the link
to that array containing the passengers.
So all we'll do inside of here is that we'll increase
the number of passengers on the flight
by the length of that array.
And then we'll just go ahead and loop through the array.
Adding up to check bags for each passenger,
so we have that complete list.
Of course, if there wasn't room, we'll
go ahead and just handle that.
So, now what's it like to call this method Add Passengers?
So we'll set up a code here and we create a flight.
Let's say we create Janet who is a passenger
that has one checked bag.
And we have John who's a passenger with two checked bags.
I'm going to go ahead and add them together.
So, we'll call our Flight, Add Passengers,
but we now have to package Janet and John up into an array.
So we have add the code where we actually create
a new passenger array and initialize it with Janet and John.
Not a horrible thing, but notice if you look,
we've actually typed more characters to create the array
than we did to actually name the two parameters,
Janet and John.
And if that carries on, let's say now we want
to add a family of three people.
Fred, Sarah and their daughter Susie.
Well, again we got to call Add Passengers.
And then again explicitly create an array
containing Fred, Sarah and Susie.
It would be nice if we could simply just list
each of the passengers we want to add.
And it turns out that we can actually do that.
Methods can be declared to accept
a varying number of parameter values.
And doing it's actually quite easy.
All we have to do, is when we declare the parameter,
just put an ellipse after the type.
So, you see here where we have Passenger as an array,
if we change that, so now we have Passenger
dot dot dot, alright, the ellipse, that now says that list
will be a varying number of passenger references.
One thing to note is that when we use this ellipse notation,
it can only be used on the last parameter for a method.
Now, in our case, our method only has one parameter.
But if we had other parameters we wanted to accept
besides this list of passengers, they'd all have to
occur before the list of passengers.
Now, here's what's really neat though.
Is that ellipse notation,
you're actually still receiving an array.
So all the code that we wrote
to handle the array,
stays in place.
We don't have to change any code in this method.
The value comes in is that it actually
simplifies calling the method.
So, if we take a look at that code we created to call
in to Add Passengers, the code as we have it written
right now would actually still work.
Because the variable number of parameters are actually
handled as an array inside the method,
we can pass them to the method as an array.
But that's not where the value comes in.
If we take a look at the first call to Add Passengers
with Janet and John, we can actually replace their array
creation with simply passing Janet and John.
And what'll happen is that Java will
take care of creating that array for us.
So, the same thing where we call for Fred, Sarah and Susie,
we can simply pass in Fred, Sarah and Susie.
So this now gives us that flexibility of handling an array
inside the method which allows us to handle anywhere from
zero or more passenger references.
While still having the convenience of calling it by simply
listing the values we want to send to the method.