The key things you want to remember from this module.
Remember that parameters are immutable.
What that means is that any change made to a parameter
within a method are not reflected once you exit that method.
It doesn't matter whether it's a Primitive Type
or a reference to a Class.
But you can make changes to members of a class.
Because remember that the parameter's
actually pointing off to that object instance.
So those individual members can be changed.
A constructor or method can actually
have multiple versions of it.
In other words, you can have differing parameter lists.
We call that Overloading.
Remember though that each one
needs to have a unique signature.
That signature is made up of its name, the number
of parameters and the type of each parameter.
And finally, remember that methods can be declared
to accept a varying number of parameter values.
Basically you process it just like it's an array,
because it actually is an array.
It's just the Java environment is taking care of
creating the array instance for you.
The one key restriction is, that can only be done with
the last parameter received by that method or constructor.