To wrap up, the key to remember here
is that when we talk about Java
Java actually comes as both a language
and a Runtime Environment.
You know there may be some variations
in those individual Runtime Environments.
But the cool thing is that the
language is pretty consistent.
By knowing the Java Language well
you've got the ability to work
across a wide range of platforms.
Now in terms of installations, End-users only require
the JRE that Java Runtime Environment.
As Developers we want the JDK as well.
Remember that the JDK installation
installs the JRE for you
so you can go ahead and run the
applications that you're creating.
All although the JDK is all we actually need
to create our applications.
We probably want to use an IDE of some sort.
There's a whole bunch of ones out there.
Again you pick the one you like best.
Out of the two I showed you
One is NetBeans which is the one that Oracle provides.
The other one when I showed you IntelliJ
is again very popular as well.
And there's no magic to it.
It really comes to down to,
you just pick the one you like best.
And with that, we have everything we need
to set up our Environments.
So in the next module we'll start Coding.