Our focus throughout this whole course
is we're going to give you a strong foundation
in the Java Language.
To teach you what you need to work effectively
with the Java programming language.
I'm going to do that as a very Hands-on approach.
We're going to be writing lots of code as we go through.
And seeing what happens when we
write and change that code.
And our focus is really here on this again
the idea of the language, right?
The Java syntax, the language constructs, the concepts
and how to use all those things
together to program effectively.
And what we're really trying to do here
is give you the language skills you need to work effectively
in any Java-based environments.
The topics we cover here are useful in traditional Java.
Which is often called Java Standard Edition.
But also when working in Enterprise Level Applications
even Java Smart Client Applications, right?
And that carries on even down to small devices
with Java Micro Edition and Android, right?
So we really got that whole thing covered.
The thing that's interesting to note is that
even though Android is really kind of
the most popular phone platform that uses Java.
That doesn't mean that Java Micro Edition
isn't important, right?
Although Java Micro Edition is
not a big part of phones anymore
it still plays a really important role in smart devices
and the internet of things, right?
So understanding the Java programming language
really gives you what you need to work across all
all levels of computers, right?
From desktops all the way down to
small devices all way back up to great big servers.