The goal of this first Module is to give us the information
we need to start working with and learning
the Java programming language.
So first we want to look at
is just take a brief overview of what Java is.
What are the parts of it, what is it made up of.
Then I'll talk about the JRE vs. JDK.
Two terms people throw around pretty freely
in a Java world.
We want to understand what those are and what they mean.
We're going to look at the details of actually
setting up you Java development environment.
And then looking at your Java
Integrative Development Environment.
The tools we use to build Java programs.
We're not going to kind of endorse or focus on any
Java, or any specific Java ID in this course.
We just want to talk about what the options are out there
and help you to choose which one's right for you.