The first thing we need to understand to get started is
exactly what is Java.
When someone says Java, what are they talking about?
Well, Java is a Programming Language.
But Java's also a Runtime Environment.
It's actually both of those things.
So when we think about the programming language
it has things like the Syntax, the Data types, Control flow
like Looping and Conditional statements
and being Object- orientated, right?
Doing Inheritance and so forth.
And then RunTime of course has to support those things.
But also provides things like Configuration, Security
a Threading Model, Input/output, that sort of thing.
So when someone says Java, they could be referring to
a Programming Language or the Runtime Environment
or the whole thing.
Now in general, Runtime Environment is when someone's
talking about when they just say Java.
Which is often referred to as Java Standard Edition.
Or kind of the basic Java Environment.
But Oracle provides other environments to derive from that.
Enterprise Edition, Java Micro Edition, and JavaFX, right?
So those are all either supersets
or subsets of this main thing
which is just a Java Standard Edition.
But the thing that's neat about Java, it's so flexible.
That there are even Runtimes that are not tied
to the Java one produced by Oracle, right?
Like Android is kind of the most well-known one, right?
Androids provides a very different Runtime
Than the Standard Java Runtimes from Oracle.
The thing is though, that all those environments support
effectively the same Java Programming Language, right?
So that one Language equips us to work in all those different places.