The JRE and the JDK are two terms
you hear people mention very frequently in the Java World.
And what they are is a two parts that we need in order
to run and create Java Applications.
The JRE is the Java Runtime Environment.
JDK is the Java Developing Kit.
And so the JRE is what you require
in order to run Java Applications.
And users normally install the JRE.
They're the ones who are going to run our apps.
The JDK provides the tools required to create Java apps.
So normally developers the ones who install
the JDK on their machines.
And in order to develop the apps you need to run them
the JDK installation includes a JRE.
So how does all this work together?
If we sit down and we type out up a Java Source File
with our program code inside of it.
And we want to go and run that in some Host Environment how do we do it?
That Host Environment might be Windows, Linux.
It could be Mac.
It could even be a browser.
It might be a phone running Android.
How do we get from that Source we typed up
to something we could actually run
on Mac or another computer.
Well that's where the Java Development Kit comes in.
Using the Java Development Kit
we can feed our Source Code into it.
And it will produce our Java application.
Now Java's not like a low level language like C.
C, when you compile a C program
it produces an application that can
run directly on the Host computer.
Java uses an abstraction called Blake Codes
that's platform independent.
It allows us to not be tied to a particular Host Environment
but actually have something that
can be run in different Host Environments.
And that's where the Java Runtime Environment comes in.
The Java Runtime Environment provides what we need
in order for our Java app that does
Blake Codes to execute in any Host Environment.
That's why End-users install the Java Runtime Environment
because they just need to run that code.
We as developers install the JDK
to give us the tools to produce that application.