Let's go and install the JDK onto our machine.
Now that URL I have on screen
the bit.ly/psjdkdownload is set to point to
whatever the current version of the JDK is.
As I'm recording this, the current version is JDK8.
So that's the one I'll install.
If you watch this course into the future
and another version JDK 9 or 10 comes out,
that same URL you see will take you
to the appropriate place to download that current version.
So here we are in our browser.
So let's go ahead and put in that URL.
We'll hit enter.
So here we are at the current download page.
Or I should say, here we are at the page
where you can get the current Java downloads.
You notice here on the left we got one here for the JDK.
Also called the Java Platforms.
We'll go ahead and click on that.
Here we are on the JDK download page.
So go ahead and scroll down here a little bit
until you see that--
here's all the various versions you can download.
And basically you just download the version
for whatever platform you're using, right?
If you're on Linux you get that one of course.
If I was on my Mac right now I'd get the Mac one.
But in this case I'm currently on a 64 bit Windows machine.
So I want to install that version, right?
Windows 64.
One thing you want to make sure you remember to do
is accept this license, alright?
If you don't accept the license
it won't allow you to do the download.
When we're ready we just go ahead
and click on this to download the File.
So my download's completed.
So I'm going to go ahead and run the installer.
I'm just going to go ahead and double click on this guy.
And now here we are inside the installer, right?
So I'm just going to get in and let the
installer get started here.
Oh, good.
Say, yep good, install everything.
And you'll notice that one of the things it has here
is that the JRE or the Java Runtime.
So it actually puts that in for us.
So we're going to say yep, and go ahead and do that.
You notice here, it prompts us again
for a Destination Folder.
And this is the folder where
the Java Runtime is going to go.
I'm going to go ahead, and just accept the default for that.
So I'll say Next.
And with that we're done.
We now have the JDK along with the JRE
installed on our computer.