If you wanted to, you could build your Java applications
having only installed the JDK.
You could've used some arbitrary text editor
to type in your program code.
And then you can use command line tools
to do all the compiling and executing of your programs.
And that would work fine.
And people did that for years.
And some people still do that.
But in general, for developing we want to
use a more productive model than that.
We like these things called
Integrated Development Environments
that allow us to type in our Code
compile it, debug it, everything all in one place.
Now Java has lots and lots of IDEs available.
Two of the most popular are NetBeans and IntelliJ.
And both of these are available for free.
NetBeans is the IDE that Oracle themselves provide.
And they provide it for free.
And it's pretty flexible in a sense that it comes
in different configurations.
And configurations are available kind of
for all the Oracle Javas.
So Standard Edition, Enterprise Edition,
Micro Edition, JavaFX.
And you can add all those in at no additional cost.
The one kind of popular Java Environment
that it does not support is Android.
Alright, just to be aware of that if you were doing
Android development and other Java development
you wouldn't be able to use NetBeans
for the Android part of it.
One kind of nicety is that Oracle does provide
a single installer that has both the JDK
and the Java SE bundle of NetBeans.
In other words that version of NetBeans
will let you work on Java SE programs.
And that's just a real kind of nicety nice convenience
if you're installing a new machine.
And you just want to kind of get the JDK on there
and have an ID all in one install.
It just makes setting up a machine easy.
Another very popular IDE for Java is IntelliJ.
I really like IntelliJ.
It's my preferred Java Environment.
Now the IntelliJ Community Edition
is a free version of a commercial product.
So you have a company called JetBrains
actually builds and sales a full blown
installation of IntelliJ.
But they make this Community Edition
available to us for free.
And what I like about it is that
the Community Edition supports
Java Standard Edition and Android.
So you can use one IDE for both of those environments.
Which I find really convenient.
If you were to decide to go ahead and go
with the commercial version of IntelliJ
you would pick up addition features.
There's some other development features.
Like Java EE does some cool server debugging stuff.
But you don't have to go to the commercial version.
Community Edition is quite substantial.
And certainly is good enough for everything we do in this course.
You'll find that most things you likely want to do
are supported in the Community Edition.