Let's go ahead and walk through the installation
of the NetBeans IDE.
Now as I mentioned you can download NetBeans with the JDK.
And that same URL we used earlier to get the most recent JDK
works for getting the most recent packaging
of NetBeans and the JDK.
So that same bit.ly/psjdkdownload.
If you want to actually kind of pick which
configuration of NetBeans you want
as opposed to getting the one that's got JDK build into it
you can go to the netbeans.org website
on their download page.
You actually pick out exactly what
configuration of NetBeans you want.
OK so let's go through the steps.
OK so here we are in our browser.
Let's go ahead and go to that bit.ly URL again.
So hit Enter.
So here on your Oracle download page
you see the big logo there that says NetBeans.
And it says NetBeans with JDK.
So let's go ahead and go there and see what that looks like.
So click on that.
And you'll notice here that right here
in the center of the page.
It actually says that here's the JDK with NetBeans.
And it's got all the different platform installations.
But looking to the right here
you'll see there's actually a link
that just says NetBeans IDE.
So let's take a look at that guy real quick.
So we're going to go to that page.
That puts us over in the NetBeans website itself.
I'm going to scroll down a little bit.
And you can see there that
these are all the different configurations
that we can download for the different platforms, right?
For just SE Support or if you want
EE Support as well, and other ones.
So if you want to Control
then pick that particular configuration.
You can do that from here.
What I'm going to do though is
go back to the page we were on.
And I'm going to go ahead and install NetBeans with the JDK.
Now remember in the earlier Demo
I installed the JDK all by itself.
Because that step was already done
I don't have to actually download
this package version of it.
I can actually just go get NetBeans by itself.
So I'm going to go in here and go get the version
for the current computer.
Which is again a 64 bit Windows
and I'll download that.
So I have the download now.
So let's go ahead and run that.
Alright, so we're in the installer.
Let's go ahead and click through that.
Now we have to accept the license
for some of the tools here.
So JUnit is a testing tool
and that gets installed as part of the ID.
So we're just going to go ahead and accept that license.
Click Next.
Again telling it where to install the JDK.
We'll say yep do that.
Now it wants to know where to install
NetBeans and some JDK Support stuff for NetBeans.
We're going to click Next on that.
And the last one here is that
"Do you want to check for Updates?"
And I leave that checked.
Go ahead and click Install.
Alright, so our setup is complete.
And the last thing it's asking us is just
do we what to go ahead contribute statistics
back into the project so they can see what we're using.
So I'm going to leave that box checked and say Finish.
And I now have the NetBeans ID installed.
Now one thing to be aware of is that
NetBeans installation is a fairly lengthy installation.
I'm on a pretty new machine here
and it probably still took between
three and four minutes for that install to run.
So if it takes a few minutes to run
don't be worried about it.
So let's go and fire up NetBeans now
and see what it looks like.
I'll go down here to my Windows.
and just go down to where all my programs are.
Scroll over here to my NetBeans.
There's NetBeans.
So let's go ahead and run that guy.
And there we have it.
We've been NetBeans installed and it's running for us.
We'll actually build a program with it in the next module.
But I just wanted to make sure
that it installed and ran correctly, and it does.