Let's walk through installing
the IntelliJ Community Edition.
The URL on screen there, the bitly URL will take
you to whatever the current version of IntelliJ is.
Currently it's 14.1.
But even as the versions evolve
that URL should still remain valid.
Here we are in our browser.
So let's go ahead and put that URL in
and get to the IntelliJ page.
We hit Enter.
Just scroll down a little bit here
so you can see where we're at.
You see this one page.
And it's got both the Commercial Edition
and the Community Edition.
Want to make sure we go ahead
and download the Community Edition.
So we just go ahead and click on the download button here.
Once the download's complete
we just go ahead and run the installer.
So we'll just step through this now so I'll start.
I'll click Next.
I'm going to go ahead and accept the
Default Installation Folder.
Now I'm going to go ahead and create a desktop shortcut
to make it a little easier to find.
And also I've got these associations
so I'm going to go ahead and associate with .java.
That way if I just double click on any .java File
it'll automatically Open it up inside of IntelliJ.
Click Next.
I'm going to keep all the defaults here on the Groups.
And it's off and installing.
So my installation's complete.
So I'm going to go ahead here and just click this box
that says go ahead and run IntelliJ when I exit.
So I'll click finish.
I'm going to tell it not to worry about
importing any previous settings.
I'm just going to say OK.
Now the first time you run it
it wants to ask you how do you want set it up.
Do you want to customize its appearance and everything.
I'm just going to say just skip all that
and just set the defaults.
And see now I'm at the starting window.
Now we have IntelliJ installed as well.
And again in the next module
We'll actually start using this
and building some Code with it.
We now know we have a successful install.