Welcome to the final module
of the Pluralsight Java fundamentals course
on the Java language.
In this module, we're going to look at static members,
nested types, and anonymous classes.
My name is Jim Wilson.
So as we go through this module,
we're going to touch on a number of things.
First of all, the idea of static members
having static methods and fields
and then we'll look at something called
static initialization blocks,
the ability to do one time type initialization.
Then we'll look at nested types
and then a very particular type of nested type
called inner classes where we actually can have
the nested classes instance automatically associated
with an instance of its enclosing class.
And then finally, we'll talk about anonymous classes.
The ability to declare and create a class all at one time.