In the classes we've been working with
throughout the course, we've always been using
what are called instance members
where each class member is associated
with specific class instance
and that's what you normally want,
but sometimes you want to be able to have a class member
that's available class-wide
and that's where static members come in.
So a static member is a class member
that's not associated with any individual instance.
Now the way you declare static members
is very similar to the way you declare instance members
except you include the keyword static.
So a static field is declared just like a regular field
except you put the keyword static in front of it,
similarly when declaring a static method.
The thing is that when you create static members
because they're not associated with individual instance,
you can actually access them using the class name.
So if you think about static fields,
a static field would be a field
whose value is not associated with any specific instance.
Again, it's a class Y.
What that means is that each instance of the class
will actually access the same value for that field.
So a static method is usually a case
where you have a method that wants to do some work
that's not specific to any individual instance.
Static methods can only access static fields.
They can't access instance fields because, again,
they're not associated with any individual instance.
So let's take a look at using this in some code.
So we've got our flight class we've been using
throughout the course and we know that
one of the things we've done is keep track
of the number of passengers.
So each flight can track how many people
are on that one flight with the passenger's field.
We have this add one passenger method
that increments the count there.
Now let's say what we want to do now
is that in addition to each flight
keeping track of how many passengers
are on that flight, we'd like to have an easy way
to keep track of how many passengers
are on the total of all flights.
And that's a great use for a static field.
So what I'm going to do is add a field here
called all passengers.
Again, I declared just like an instance field,
but I've actually marked it with static.
That now means it's not associated with any instance.
I'll add some methods to work with it.
I'll have a method here get all passengers
and then I'll simply return back the value
of all passengers.
So again, get all passengers to declare
like any other method except it's marked as static.
And I also want to have the ability to set number
of all passengers back to zero.
So I have a method here called reset all passengers,
which then just sets it to zero.
So let's use this in some code.
So we go out here and let's say first of all
we want to just go ahead and reset all passengers.
Now again, the key thing to understand in static members
is that they are stored separate from any instance.
Alright, so the storage area for all passengers
is outside of any instance of the flight class.
Alright, so if I go out here and I say
print line flight dot get all passengers,
get all passengers will get the current value
of all passengers, which of course is zero
and print that out.
So now the question is, how do I change the value
of all passengers?
How do I increment that, cause I want to increment it
each time I add a passenger.
Well in our add one passenger method,
just below where you increment passengers by one,
we'll go ahead and just simply add one to all passengers.
See we're not really interacting with it any differently.
What's going to change its behavior
is the way its storage is managed.
Let's say we have now our flight LAX045.
So we actually created an instance of the flight class.
Alright, it has its own memory.
Again, notice that instance memory is separate
from the all passengers memory.
So if I go off and I say LAX045, add one passenger,
of course, the passenger for the instance LAX045
gets incremented by one as does all passengers.
Alright, so if I call add one passenger again
on LAX045, LAX045 passenger increments by one
as does all passengers.
But now let's create another instance.
We have our SLC015.
Of course, it has its own memory associated with it.
So when I call add one passenger on SLC015,
passengers in SLC015 increments by one
going from zero to one, but all passengers
keeps its old value.
So it now goes from two to three.
You see that all passengers is continuing to count up
even as we interact with it through different instances.
That's where the power statics come in.
So now if I go ahead and print out the value
of get all passengers, I get three.
So I'm not doing any extra work to keep this total value
across all instances.
So by declaring it as static, gave me that ability.
Now as I mentioned, we can access static members
by using the class name.
But Java also has a shorthand for accessing static members
called static import.
And static import allows you to access static members
without even using the class name.
So it's really just going to be shorthand mechanism.
So we take a look at our code here, again,
where we're using the flight class
and we were calling in to reset all passengers
and get all passengers.
Well rather than have to always say flight dot
in front of it, we'd like to be able to say
reset all passengers or get all passengers.
We'll use a static import to do that.
So first I'm going to give us just a little bit more room
to work here and so it's an import statement
so we're going to use an import at the top.
Remember, we used import earlier
to actually be able to use shorthands for classes
so we didn't have to package qualify them.
Now we're going to use the import for shorthands
for static members, but we don't have to qualify them.
So we have the word import.
In this case, we include the word static.
So this is a static import.
We then give it the package name, dot the class name,
which is our flight class and then we also include
the member name.
So reset all passengers.
So now where we say flight dot reset all passengers,
now that can simply become reset all passengers.
The import statement allows us to use just a method name.
So the same thing for get all passengers.
I can have it import, static, the package name,
dot the class name, in this case flight dot the method name.
So in each case we now print out
and call get all passengers, instead of saying flight dot
get all passengers, we'll say get all passengers.
Same thing in the other print statement.
And so these static imports just allowed us
to type that more succinctly.
In the next clip we'll see some other uses
and other behaviors of working with statics
as we talked about static initializers.