There are times in our applications
where we need to do some kind of work to prepare a class
before we use it, and that's where
static initialization blocks come in.
Static initialization blocks perform basically
one-time type initialization.
The neat thing about them is that
they execute automatically before your types first use.
Now remember, we've talked about initialization blocks
earlier in the course, but those were instance
initialization blocks.
Remember that the instance initialization blocks
automatically executed before any of your constructors.
Well static initialization blocks execute
before you actually even start using the type.
You can kind of think of those as type initializers.
Now basically, there are statements enclosed in brackets,
outside of any method or constructor,
but you have to mark it of course with the keyword static.
Now being static, they cannot access any instance members.
They can only access static members.
And because they're called automatically,
you have to handle any checked exceptions within
the initialization block.
There's no concept of a throws keyword on here.
You have to make sure you take care of everything
within the initialization block itself.
So let's see an example of using this in an application.
Now let's imagine that we have a file listing crew members
that are available to do some work.
If you'll look at this you'll notice that the first column
is the person's job, like a pilot or a copilot
and each of these values corresponds
to the enumeration we created earlier in the course,
which is our flight crew jobs.
And then after the job we have a comma
and then the person's name.
What we want to do with these values,
is we want to be able in our code
to be able to declare variables like crew member
and we'll have a class that we'll call crew manager
where we can call a static method on it, find available,
where we identify the job that we need to fill
and the crew manager find available method
will return back a crew member who can fill in that job
that's not already reassigned to another job.
So let's look at our crew manager class.
Now the idea of find available is pretty simple.
Alright, as we lay out a crew manager class,
of course, we'll need to have a constant
for the file name we want to load from.
We'll need to have the array of crew members
that we'll call pool and then we can go ahead
and have our find available method.
Again, accepts the job as a parameter
and the implementation is pretty straight forward.
Basically, we'll have to have a variable to hold
the matching crew member.
We'll add a loop through that pool of crew members
and then inside there we basically just want to check.
As long as there's a valid spot in the pool,
if the job matches, then we know we want that person,
so we'll store reference to them from the pool.
We'll remove them from the pool
so we don't assign them to two different jobs
and then from there we break out
and return back to that crew member.
The question is though is that how does pool
get initialized from the file?
Now we could go write another static method
called initialize or something like that,
that loaded up to file contents,
but in complex applications, you can't always be sure
kind of what order of things are going to happen.
It would be nice to be able to know that
that pool field would automatically get loaded
prior to our first use.
And that's where static initialization blocks come in.
So if we take a look at that.
Let's add a little bit more room here
to add some code to our crew manager class.
And what we'll do then is that we'll add
our static initialization block.
Remember that it's just the brackets
marked by the word static outside of any method.
So we've got that there.
So what we want to do is read from the file,
so we'll go ahead and create our reader.
We'll need to of course have a variable to read
a line from the file and index to track our way
through the array.
We'll want to allocate some space in the array
and then from there we just start reading through
the file.
So we read through the file.
We go ahead and read the line and split it into its parts.
The first part is a string representing the job.
The second part is their name.
We then want to map that string
into our flight crew job enumeration.
Now remember that earlier in the course
we talked about mapping strings to enumeration values
and we did it with a series of explicit if statements
and that gave us a lot of flexibility
because we were actually completely independent
of string case or anything like that.
If we have a scenario where we know that the string value
coming in matches the case in capitalization
of our enumeration values, we can use the enumerations
value of method.
So for example, pilot is always capital P
in our enumeration.
So if we know our string is coming in
with the pilot capital P, we can use value of.
Copilot is capital C, capital P.
So as long as the strings match that capitalization,
rather than reading that explicit if,
we can use this value of method.
So I'll go ahead and map that into a job
from the string value that's in the file.
So we'll go ahead and create an instance of crew member
based on that job, put them in the array,
set their name from the value inside the file,
and then index through the array.
So that takes care of actually reading in the contents.
But remember though that we talked about this earlier
that when we interact with a file,
there are IO exceptions that can occur.
That's a checked exception.
Inside of our static initialization blocks
we have to handle all checked exceptions.
We want to make sure that we go ahead
and wrap this up with a try catch that handles
that IO exception.
So with this, our crew manager class is all set to go.
And the magic here is that, that static initialization block
is automatically called for prior to the first use.
So what we can do then is when we're ready
to use this class, whenever we call the crew manager class
for the very first time, our find available,
the system will automatically run that code
that's inside of the static initialization block
and load up the array for us.
Each time after that, that we use it,
the array is already loaded so we can go ahead and find
the next person who matches a job
and the next person.
So these static initialization blocks
are this really powerful capability
that takes care of initializing our classes
prior to their first use with no special calls
on the part of the user.