At a few points during the course we've mentioned
nested types briefly and I've always said that's something
we would talk about later.
Well later is now.
Now a nested type is simply a case where you have a type
that's declared within another type.
So you can have classes that are declared
within the other classes or within an interface.
You can also have interfaces that are declared
within classes or a different interface.
When you nest one type inside of another,
the nested type is actually a member of its enclosing type.
So what that means is that the nested type
actually has visibility of private members
of its enclosing type.
Also as a member, it can have all the member
access modifiers.
Alright, so a nested class can of course be public
or packaged private just as a top of a class
but you can also have a nested class that is protected,
being that it would only be accessible by classes
that inherit from its enclosing class.
Or it can even be private.
So you can have a class that's only visible
to the class in which it's contained.
When we work with nested types,
there's generally two ways we work with them.
In one case we only use them for structure and scoping.
In this case, there's no special relationship
between instances of the nested class
and instances of the enclosing class.
It's really because you want to make the type
only usable in certain scenarios
or you want to structure its naming
relative to another class.
So this happens when you have what's called
a static nested class or if you put a class
inside of an interface
or if you have a nested interface.
See what this looks like.
Remember we have our passenger class here
and one of the things we did with passenger
is we had a rewards program.
Now the rewards program relied on two values.
What the person's level was in the rewards program
and how long they'd been a member of the program.
And this is the case where it takes two values
to represent a single concept
and oftentimes when we have that scenario,
we go ahead and wrap that up in a class.
So we could go off and create a rewards program class.
But this is rewards program as it applies to a passenger.
What if we had a different rewards program
as it applied to crew members?
Well we could start naming one like
passenger rewards program,
another one crew member rewards program,
or we could have a reward program class
that we nest inside of passenger.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So we'll wrap up those two values
inside of our reward program class.
So reward program is the nested class,
passenger is the enclosing class.
The reward program is marked as static,
which means we're using it for structure and scoping.
As a class, you can do all the things classes are allowed to do.
So we could have methods inside of it.
So we have a getter and a setter for member level
and a getter and a setter for member days.
Now all we've done at this point
is declare the reward program class.
There's no instance of it yet.
So what we're going to do inside of our passenger class,
we'll add a field to type of reward program
that we'll call reward program.
Now it's still a reference type so we need to go ahead
and new it up, so we'll new up an instance of it.
Now we've marked reward program as private
in terms of the field, but notice our reward program class
is public.
So you can't access the field directly,
so we'll go ahead and put a getter around that as well.
Okay, so now we have our reward program class
that's nested inside of our passenger class.
Let's see how this effects our code when we use it.
So let's go over here and we'll go ahead create an instance
of a passenger and we'll call him Steve.
If we want to go ahead and set up
his reward program information,
it's just like working with any other field
that's based on a class.
We have our Steve variable.
We call get reward programs
and actually get a reference to his
reward program information
and then we just call methods on it.
So we can set his level to three
and we'll go ahead and set his member days to 180.
So really there is nothing different there.
But now remember we said that we declared reward program
as a public nested class.
So it's usable outside of the passenger class.
So we can actually create variables and instances
of that reward program outside of the passenger class.
Let's go ahead and create a variable here called platinum.
But you notice the name of the class.
The class's name is passenger dot reward program.
Alright, the enclosing class dot the nested class.
And when we new it up, we use the class name.
So we go ahead and new up an instance
of passenger dot reward program.
So you see how we've got a structured name here.
So the reward program name is qualified
by the passenger class.
If we had a different reward program for crew members,
we can nest that inside of the crew member class,
then its name would be qualified by the crew member class.
So we can go ahead and use this platinum variable,
and so we'll go ahead and set the level to three.
So we're saying now that this variable platinum
represents a reward program at the platinum level.
So we can use all of this stuff just as we do
any other bit of our code.
So if I want to do a test I can say hey Steve
get the reward program, what's its level.
Well if its level equals the level in platinum,
then we know that Steve is platinum.
So again, this is a case of using nested classes
as a mechanism for providing structure and scoping.
A reward program is a nested class that's marked
as static so its name was scoped within the passenger class.
In the next clip we'll see how things differ
if we nest a class and do not mark it as static.