As we saw in the last clip, nesting one class
inside of another or one type inside of another,
provides scoping where we can limit who can access the type
and structure.
We can even kind of create the name of one class
to be structured inside of another.
But that's just the beginning of what nested types can do.
We can get a much closer relationship when we nest one class
inside of another.
There's a concept called inner classes.
And with inner classes you actually have a class
who each instance of which is associated
with an instance of its enclosing class.
So there's just kind of an implicit relationship
between instances.
This occurs anytime you nest one class inside of another
and don't mark the nested class as static.
To see how this works, let's take a look
at our flight class again.
So remember that our flight class implements
the iterable interface.
So its method iterator returned back an instance
of this class called flight iterator that we created.
If we look at flight iterator, it has kind of one job.
Alright, walking through that list of crew and roster.
The has next and next methods are needed of course
because they're part of the iterator interface,
and of course, we need the index field
to keep track of our location.
But the constructor that we have there
and the crew and roster fields, those exist
just kind of to duplicate content that's already inside
of the flight class.
Using inner classes we can actually simplify
our flight iterator by taking advantage of
the implicit relationships that can occur
between the classes.
So let's take our flight iterator class
and we'll move it inside of our flight class here.
A couple of things to note here,
the flight iterator class is marked as private,
which means that the type can't be seen
outside of the flight class itself.
Also, the class is not marked as static.
Alright, that's what makes it an inner class.
It's a nested class inside of another class.
The nested class is not marked as static.
So of course, we'll need our index field
to keep track of our location,
but then we'll implement our has next method.
So of course inside of here, we're going to check
where the index is.
So we have our index and we can actually compare the index
to crew and roster even though crew and roster
are not declared inside of flight iterator.
They're part of flight.
Alright similarly, we have our next method.
We can, of course, use the index to get
to the right member of crew or roster
and then of course return that back.
With this, our flight iterator class is nested
inside of the flight class can replace
that separate flight iterator class.
And so when we actually, inside of the iterator method,
when we create flight iterator, we don't have to pass in
any parameters.
We just create that nested flight iterator itself.
So why does this work?
Well as a nested class, the flight iterator actually has
two this references.
It has the traditional this reference,
the ability to access its own members,
but it also has a flight dot this reference,
which allows it to access the members
of the instance of flight in which it was created.
And that gives us power of inner classes.
By simply declaring flight iterator as in class
that's nested inside of another class,
and not marking it as static,
each time we create an instance of flight iterator,
that flight iterator instance is automatically associated
with the instance of the flight class in which
it was created.