Java provides the ability to create anonymous classes.
With anonymous classes, rather than use the class keyword
to go ahead and give a class a name,
to give its declaration then later go off and create it,
with anonymous classes, we're able to declare our class
as part of the class's creation.
And what they're useful for are cases
where you want to implement an interface
or extend a particular class generally to provide
some specific solution, something you're not generally
going to use throughout your application, but to solve
a particular problem.
Now anonymous classes are inner classes.
So that means that your anonymous classes
have access to the instance members
of the enclosing class.
We create an anonymous class as if we're constructing
an instance of the interface or base class
that we want to extend.
But what we do then as part of that creation process
is we go ahead and follow it with the opening
and closing brackets and then provide
our class implementation right there
where we're creating it.
Now to see how this works, let's take a look
at our flight class again.
And again, we're going to look at our
iterable implementation.
Now in our last clip, we actually used an inner class
to provide the iterator implementation.
Alright, so we had the flight iterator class
and then inside of our iterator method
we actually go ahead and create an instance of that class.
Well that flight iterator class is not used anywhere else
in our program except within this one method iterator.
So this is actually a great chance for us to use
an anonymous class to kind of further make our code
a little bit more concise.
So what I'm going to do is go ahead
and take the flight iterator out of my code here.
So I'm getting rid of the declaration as well as
the creation of it.
Then here inside of our iterator method,
we're going to go ahead and move that closing bracket down
so we have a little bit more room
and we're going to start out very similar
to what we did before.
We're going to go ahead and have our return statement
and call them new, cause we're about to create a class.
But normally we would follow new with an existing class
we've already declared and we want to create.
But in this case, we're going to go ahead
and put the interface name there.
You notice that the interface name
has the opening and closing parens there
cause we're calling a constructor.
Now because we're implementing an interface,
we got a constructor we can call
as the no argument constructor.
But if we were extending a base class
we could use any constructor provided by that base class.
But here, rather than just end statement
we're going to go ahead and put in our opening
and closing brackets.
And it's inside these brackets or where we're going
to go ahead and implement our class.
So basically we've done this iterator several times now
so we know that we need to have a field for the index
to keep track of our location.
We'll go ahead and provide our has next method.
Now in our has next, we're going to check
our index location.
We're using the field inside of our anonymous class.
And we're going to go ahead and check that against
the combined length of the crew and roster.
Remember again, that our anonymous class
is an inner class, so it has access to
the members of the containing class,
cause again this instance is associated
with the instance of our enclosing class flight.
Then we'll go ahead as well and implement our next method,
just as we did previously.
And that's it.
We now have our anonymous class.
So we're actually implementing our iterator interface
right here as part of the creation.
So anonymous classes allow us to avoid the need
to go off and declare these bunch of classes
and give them names that we're only using in one place.
Instead, right here where we need it,
we take care of the entire job of declaring the class
and creating it.