To wrap up, here are the key things
you want to remember.
Remember that static methods and fields
are shared class-wide.
You can access them using the class name
and they're not associated with any individual instance
of your class.
Static initialization blocks allow you to provide one-time
type initialization.
It allows you to have a block of code
that's automatically run before the first time you use
that type.
A nested type is a type declared within another type.
Now they can be used to provide just structure and scoping
and that's true if you have a class that's marked as static
or anytime you're using interfaces with nesting.
Or you can use inner classes.
Inner classes occur when you have one class
inside of another and that nested class
is not marked as static.
In that case, whenever you create an instance
of the nested class, that instance
is automatically associated with the instance
of the enclosing class from which it was created.
So you get a lot of power with that automatic association.
And then we have anonymous classes
that are actually declared as part of their creation.
Remember that anonymous classes are considered
inner classes so they can actually access the members
of the enclosing type and they're useful
for those situations where you want to implement
some interface or you want to go ahead and extend a class
for a very specific situation, so you don't need to go off
and declare a class explicitly, just go ahead
and create it right there in place when you need it.
And that brings us to the end of our course Java Fundamentals
the Java language.
So whether you're planning to go off
and work on servers, clients or devices,
you're now armed with the knowledge of the Java language that
you need to start building your killer app.
To continue developing your Java skills,
I encourage you to take a look at the Pluralsight skills pad for Java.
It contains a great progression of courses that will build your skills
as a Java developer.
In fact there's a good chance you arrived at this course
from the Java Skill Path.
If you haven't already checked out the Java Skill Path
I encourage you to go over and take a look at this courses contained there.
And finally. Thank you for joining me throughout our discussion on Java Language.
I wish you the very best as you begin applying your
new Java language skills and as you continue learning and developing your skills
as a Java developer.