Welcome to the next module
of the Pluralsight Java fundamentals course
on the Java language.
In this module, we talk more about data types.
My name is Jim Wilson.
As we go through this module,
we'll first look at the String class
and how to work with string values.
We'll then look at how we can work with strings
and manipulate strings more efficiently
using the StringBuilder class.
We'll see how we can bring the capability of classes
to primitive values, using the primitive wrapper classes.
We'll see how to create fields
that can't be changed once set, using final fields.
Then we'll finish up with enumeration types,
which allow us to define types
that can only hold a finite list of values.