In this demo, we'll enhance our CalcEngine program
to take advantage of the data type capabilities
we've talked about throughout this module.
What we'll do is add in some string processing capability,
so we can take a string like
add space 1.0 space 2.0.
We'll calculate the answer and then write it back out
in a more traditional format,
like 1.0 plus 2.0 equals 3.0.
Here we are in our CalcEngine program
and it's basically just like it was
when we left it at the end of the last module
with just a few small changes.
One thing I've done,
is all the code that was in our main method,
I've moved into other methods
so it's kind of not in our way here
as we're writing our new code.
I actually have the code in place here to call those methods
and I've just commented them out
because we're not going focus on those right now.
The other thing I've done
is I've created a string array here
that actually has four strings in it.
And these strings all have the operations we want to perform
in the syntax we want to use.
Like this first one says divide
100.0, 50.0
and with each one those separated by a space,
then what we want the program to do
is be able to print out something like
100.0 slash 50.0 equals 2.0.
And do that for all four math operations.
So, to get started, the first thing we want to do
and let's go ahead and add in an enumeration
that contains values for each of the four operations
we want to perform.
I'll go ahead and create our enumeration.
Just like I create a class.
Now, the way most of the IDEs let you do it is that
when you want to create something that's not a class,
you can just say which one it creates.
So, I'm going to go ahead and say Enum.
And let's go ahead and call my Enum, MathCommand.
I'll create that.
And we want to put our four operations in here.
So operations are going to be add, subtract,
multiply and divide.
So, we have our enumeration,
with each of the command values separated by a comma
and that's all we need to do with that for right now.
Let's go ahead and now and let's create a class
that we'll use to do the string processing for us.
So it will do the work to process a string value
and get us those results back as the other string format.
So we're going to create a new class again.
And we'll go ahead and call this one
our CalculateHelper.
So, we have that, create it.
So inside of here, what we're going to need
are four fields.
Basically we'll need one field to hold the command.
So, we'll declare that as our math command.
So in our command field we've typed MathCommand.
Now declare one for the left value
and then we'll do the same thing for right value,
and result.
So we have all fields we need now.
Let's go down to method,
we'll call process that will accept the input string
and do the work to process the contents of that string.
So, we'll make it a public void method.
And its only parameter is the string
that'll be the statement that we receive.
So we have that there.
Now, remember that what we want to do is receive a string
that looks something like this, right.
Add space 1.0 space 2.0.
So we have to go ahead and process each of those parts.
Remember that when we were
looking at the methods that the string class offers,
there was one called split
that handles this scenario of breaking a string up
into its parse based on some separating character.
So, let's go ahead and deal with that.
So, we want to create a string array called parts.
And all we have to do here is set it equal to
statement.split
and then we specify the separating character,
which is just that space.
Split will return the values inside of statement
based on the space separator.
All right, so the first value inside of there
is going to be the command.
And command string is going to be set
equal to the value of parts subzero.
And what we expect to find in there
is the value like add.
Now, the next thing we want to do
is get the left value out of there.
So, let's go ahead and put the left value
right into our field called left value.
And that value is going to be in part sub one.
Now, part sub one though is a string
so we want to go ahead and convert that string
into a double.
So, we'll use double.parsedouble
to convert that string into the primitive type double.
So that'll give us back to 1.0 as a double,
we'll then do the same thing for the right value
from part sub two.
So, with that we'll have
the value on the right-hand side.
Something like 2.0.
All right, so now we have our command as a string
and then the left values and the right value.
Now, what we want do is convert our command
from being a string into our math command enumeration.
So, let's go ahead and create another method here.
It'll be a private method.
And we'll call it set command from string.
And it's only parameter will be the command string.
So, we have that there.
Now, remember that what we want this guy to do
is take that string value, like add,
and convert that into our MathCommand.Add.
So what we'll do now is we'll take our command string
and we'll want to do a comparison with that so we'll say,
if, let's say command string
and I'm going to use EqualsIgnoreCase.
So now, the question is what do we compare that to?
Because all we have is our enumeration.
So, let's take our enumeration value for add.
Well, remember that I mentioned that
if you want to convert a type to a string,
you can call this toString method.
That's also true for enumeration.
So I want to say, .toString.
And what that will do
is it will actually take those characters,
capital A-D-D and convert them into the string, A-D-D.
So we're actually taking our enumeration value
and making it a string.
So, if we get a match on that,
what we can do is we can take our command member variable,
which is a type math command
and assign it the value of MathCommand.Add.
Then we can do that same thing on a else if,
but we'll do it for subtract this time.
And if that matches,
we'll set command to be MathCommand.subtract
and then we'll do the same things for
multiply and divide.
So now we have all four cases handled.
I'll just scroll down here so we can see a little better.
As we bring in that command string coming in,
we can now translate it into the enumeration math command
and store that into command.
So, if I scroll back up here a little bit,
in our process method now,
what we'll do is we'll call that set command from string
passing in the command string.
So, when we return back from set command from string,
we will now have our command
with the appropriate enumeration value inside of it.
So what we want to do inside of here,
is take advantage of those calculate base derived classes
we created in the previous module
to do the actual work.
So what I'm going to do is create a local variable.
A type CalculateBase called calculator.
And with that variable I can reference any of classes
that derive from CalculateBase.
So, what I'll do is,
put a switch statement in on command.
And then based on the value of my field command,
I will go ahead and create the appropriate instance.
So, we'll start start of by creating our switch statement.
It's going to be oncommand.
So, we have that in there. And what we'll do is do a case
on each of the possible values.
Want to say case and I'm going to just say Add.
Notice here, inside of the switch statement,
when we access the value of our enumeration,
all we need is the value itself.
Normally, when we work with enumeration,
we often have to include the enumeration name,
but we don't have to do that
when we're inside of a switch statement.
So we're checking our case Add.
If our command was an Add,
what we're going to do is take our calculator
and assign it a new instance of Adder.
Because our Adder knows how to do addition.
And what we'll do is we'll create it
with our left value and right value.
So at this point, calculator references an instance of adder
that has the values that have to be operated on.
So, let's go ahead and put a break here.
We'll then do case subtract.
We'll then set our calculator
to a new instance of subtractor.
Again, we need a break.
And then we'll do that same thing again,
but for multiply and divide.
So now our switch statement will take care
of creating either an adder, a subtractor,
a multiplier, or a divider,
based on whichever command was typed in.
So now we know that we can just use our calculator
to do the actual word.
So, what I'll do is I'll take my calculator
and call calculate method,
so that'll do the actual operation
and then we will get the result from the calculator
and store that into our result field.
And so with that, our process method is complete.
I'll scroll back to the top here.
Inside our process method,
we receive a complete string.
We then break it into individual parts.
We translate the string command
into our math command enumeration.
And then if I scroll down here a little bit,
we then look at that command
and create the appropriate calculate base derived class
to do the work.
And then actually perform the work itself.
So this guy is all set here.
So, let's go back to our main program now.
And so, what we can do here is,
inside of our main program,
we can go ahead and create
an instance of our calculate helper.
Let's just go ahead and call it helper.
So, we have that.
So what we can do is just do a for each
for each statement in our statements array.
And then inside of there, we'll take our helper
and we'll say, process
and we'll give it a statement.
So, that'll then go through, do all the work
to take apart the string and perform the operation.
So, the question is, how do we get the output out?
Now, it'd be really nice if we could just simply write out
the helper at this point.
In fact, let's go ahead and do that.
So we use our system.out.print line
and let's go ahead and just put our helper inside of there.
All right, so the idea here then is we'll just loop
through each of those statements,
tell the helper to process them,
and just ask the helper to write it out.
So let's go ahead and run this and let's see what we get.
And if you take a look at our output,
it's not really what we were looking for.
But, if we notice this, we actually can recognize this
from something we talked about earlier in this module.
Notice that we're seeing the class name
that symbol
and then what looks like a hashcode.
Well, that tells us that it's actually calling the helper's
toString method.
Now, we haven't overridden the toString method,
because we're seeing the results of toString
as it's implemented in the object class,
but that does tell us that
if we implement toString appropriately,
we should be able to control what gets written out here.
And that's what we'll talk about in the next clip.