So let's look at how we can update our calculate helper
to have an appropriate toString method,
so we can actually see the right results coming out
from each helper instance.
So let's get this bottom window out of the way.
Let's head back to calculate helper.
Scroll down here towards the bottom.
And what we'll do is we'll go ahead and override
the toString method.
So, that's a public string.
So we have that there.
Let's go ahead and mark it as an override.
All right, scroll down here so we can see a little better.
So, now what we want to do in here remember is we want to
write out something like this.
So that's a output that we want to produce.
So now, one of the things we'll need to do
is identify the appropriate symbol.
Is it a plus sign, or a slash for dividing,
or a minus sign.
So what we'll want to do here is go
and declare a local variable.
We'll call it symbol and make it a type char.
and I've just initialized it to a space
because variables have to be initialized.
And what we'll do here is again use our switch statement
to test the values of our command field.
All right, so we'll first do a case for add.
And of course, what we want to do here
is set our symbol to the plus sign.
So, we'll do that.
Now one thing to note here
is that we're putting this literal
right in the middle of our code.
And this would actually be a pretty cool place
to use a named constant.
So we could actually say something like,
add symbol as opposed to just a char to the plus.
So, why don't we go ahead and declare named constants
for each of the four operation symbols.
So, let's scroll up to the top of the class.
What we'll do up here is we'll make them private.
And remember that we can use file
because once a field's assigned, it can't be changed,
but for named constants,
we like to go ahead and make them static.
That way no class instance can set them at all.
The values are the same for every instance of the class.
So we make this guy a char and we'll call it ADD_SYMBOL.
Remember, named constants are all capitalized.
And we'll simply set it to the character plus.
So that's our add symbol.
Let's go ahead and do the same thing for subtract,
multiply and divide.
So we now have the symbols for all four operations.
Let's scroll back down here to our toString method
and we'll change this from that literal plus character,
to ADD_SYMBOL.
All right, so that's much more readable,
just kind of really showing what we're trying to do here.
Let's go ahead and put a break in there.
And then what we'll do is do that same thing
for the other three operations.
And so now we can set the symbol for all four operations.
Add, subtract, multiply and divide.
Let's get these extra spaces out of here.
Clean that up a little bit.
And so now we have everything we need
to build the output string.
We know the two values, the results, and what symbol to use.
So, let's add a little space down here
at the bottom so we can work.
So the most efficient way to build that output string
is to use the StringBuilder class.
So, let's declare a local variable type StringBuilder.
We'll call it sb.
And we'll open a new instance of StringBuilder.
And remember we talked about things perform best
if we pre-allocate the size.
Let's make room for, say 20 characters inside of there.
So, we've got that guy in place.
And now we need to start adding
the values into the StringBuilder.
All right, so we'll want to go ahead
and add the left value in.
So, we'll say sb.append.
Put leftValue in there.
So that puts that value in.
Let's put a space after that.
All right, next we want to get the symbol.
So we'll use our symbol variable.
So we've got that there.
Let's me just scroll down a little bit so we can see better.
We'll put another space after the symbol.
Then we need our right value
and then we can append a space equals space
followed by the result.
And with that, now we have our complete string built,
but it's inside of the StringBuilder.
Remember the way we get the string back,
is by simply calling toString on the StringBuilder instance.
So that's what will return back.
sb.toString.
And that gives us a complete implementation
of our toString method.
Now, one thing to note, we're using this StringBuilder here,
which is a really efficient way to build this string up.
There's another mechanism that you can use
that I mentioned briefly inside the module,
which is the string class has a method called format.
I've got the URL onscreen for where you can find
the documentation on the format method.
When you have a chance, you might want to check that out.
It's just an alternate way
you could've actually built this output string.
Ok, but we've got our implementation here complete.
So let's head back to our main now.
Now we haven't changed anything in main
and remember, what we're doing is that after we've processed
each instance of helper, we're just writing out helper.
And we know that that'll actually call our toString method.
All right, so let's go ahead and run this now.
And there you see in our output window
we've now got the appropriate output.
So our input string,
like divide space 100.0 space 50.0
now writes out, 100.0
space slash space 50.0
space equals space 2.0.
And the same thing for each of the four operations.
So by using these things we've talked about throughout this module,
we've been able to add some really nice functionality to our program.