To wrap up, remember the key things you want to remember from this module are first,
we have the string class,
which allows us to store a sequence of unicode characters
and any class that you create,
you can override the toString method to define
how your class behaves when converted to a string.
Remember that because strings are immutable,
meaning that they can't be changed directly,
we don't want to manipulate strings themselves directly.
Instead we use the StringBuilder class,
which provides an efficient way
for us to manipulate strings.
Primitive types provide a very efficient way
to manage primitive values,
but they lack the capability of classes.
So the primitive wrapper classes
give us the ability to get to class features
when working with primitive values.
Remember though that the primitive wrapper classes
are much less efficient than the primitive types themselves,
so only use the primitive wrapper classes
when you need the capabilities they provide.
Final fields allow us to define a field
that cannot be changed once set.
Remember that there are two kinds of final fields.
A simple final field is set
during the creation of an object instance.
Whereas a static final field
serves more as a named constant.
It can't be changed by any object instance.
Its value is associated instead with the class itself.
And, finally we have enumeration types,
which allow us to define a type
that can only hold a finite list of values.