Earlier in the course, we talked about the char type,
which allowed us to work with individual characters.
In practice, we tend to work with sequences of characters
more than individual characters.
And that's where the string class comes in.
It stores a sequence of Unicode characters.
It stores them using the UTF-16 encoding,
which basically means that, the Java String class
can store pretty much any character
you're likely to ever want to work with.
Working with strings is really straightforward.
Literal strings are enclosed in double quotes.
So, let's say we want to have a variable called name
and assign it a literal string.
We simply declare it as a string
and assign it to little string Jim enclosed in quotes.
We can easily combine string values
using the plus or plus equals.
Plus combines two strings and gives you back a new string.
Plus equals adds a string onto the value
of an existing string.
All right, so if I want to do something
like print out "Hi Jim",
I can use our print line method,
put the little string "Hi"
and then add a plus sign and name after that
and that will print out that value, "Hi Jim".
Now, one thing to be aware of is that
string objects are immutable.
And what that means is that
once a string object is created,
it can never be changed.
So, anything that changes that value
requires that a new instance
of the string object be created.
So, let's see what that looks like.
Let's say I declare a variable called greeting
and assign it to literal "Hello".
So, of course, I've got my variable
that a string is allocated out in memory
holding the value Hello.
Of course, the variable greeting then references it.
But then if I do something as simple as greeting
plus equals space.
Now, all I want to is add a space onto the world "Hello".
In order for that to happen,
a whole new string object has to be created holding
all the existing values, the "hello", plus the space.
And then greeting is repointed to that new instance.
So, it will feel like just a space was added onto the end,
but actually a whole lot more is going on.
So, if I then now say greeting plus equals world,
again it allocates out another object
holding the entire string and repoints greeting to that.
So we want to be aware of this idea
of strings being immutable
because we can end up doing things really inefficiently.
Now, later in this module,
we'll talk about how we can use other mechanisms
to work with a string situation like this more effectively.
Now the string class has a number of methods on it.
We're not going to talk about all of them,
but I just want to point out some of the highlights here.
One of the methods we commonly use is the length method,
which gives us back the length of the string.
How many characters are in that string.
Very often we want to convert
non-string values in the strings.
Like we have, maybe, the integer value 100.
If we want to get back to characters one, zero, zero,
the string method valueOf will do that.
The string class provides methods
for creating a new string from existing strings.
Concat combine two string values to create a new string.
Basically the same as the plus operator.
Replace, toLowerCase, toUpperCase and trim,
create a new string based on modifying values
of an existing string.
The split method is useful for cases
where you have a delimited string,
like a list of common delimited values.
It'll give you an array of strings back
of the individual values inside that original string.
We can do string formatting.
We can extract a substring from existing string.
We can check for the presence of a substring
in an existing string.
And then, of course, we can do comparisons.
CompareTo and compareToIgnoreCase.
Check to see if one string is greater than, equal to,
or less than another string,
based on the Unicode character sequences.
IsEmpty tells us whether we have a zero link string.
Then equals and equalsIgnoreCase
obviously check for a equality.
Equals checks to see do we have the exact same
character sequence in two strings.
EqualsIgnoreCase does the same thing,
but ignoring the case of course.
The thing is, equals actually raises some interesting issues
that we need to talk about,
which we'll talk about in the next clip.
To get the full documentation on the string class,
just check out that URL I have onscreen.