Let's take a look at the issue
of comparing strings for equality.
Let's say I have a string, I'll call s1.
And I assign it the value, I space love.
Then I add on space Java to the end of that.
I have another string called s2
and I set it to the value of I
and I add on space love space Java.
So now we have two strings, s1 and s2,
and both of them have the value
I space love space Java.
So now if I compare them for equality,
using the equal equals operator, what I'll get is
false.
And let's see why that's the case.
So, if I look at s1,
it contains the value, as we said, I space love space Java.
And of course the variable s1 references that.
And we look at s2, what it also has,
I space love space Java.
And s2 references that.
But, remember that the equals equals operator
compares values based on whether they both
point to the exact same object instance.
And what we see here is that,
s1 points to one instance and s2 points to another.
So, they're not equals by the definition
of the equal equals operator
because they don't point to the same object instance.
And that's where the equals method comes in.
The equals method does a
character by character comparison.
So, as long as the character by character comparison
of the two values matches,
then in that case, we get true.
So, in most scenarios, of comparing strings for equality,
we're going to use the equals method.
Now something to consider though is that
reference based comparisons are actually quite inexpensive.
Whereas character by character comparisons
can be very expensive,
particularly in very long strings.
So it would be nice if we had situations
where we're going to do a lot of comparisons
for a particular string value,
it might be nice to take advantage of that
inexpensive nature of reference based comparisons.
And that's where the intern method comes in.
The intern method gives us back
a canonicalized reference
of a string value.
And let's see what that means.
So, let's say I declare another string variable, s3
and I assign it the value s1.intern.
Again, intern returns back a canonicalized value
and that's a fancy way of saying,
when you call the intern method on a string value,
it will always return back
the same exact string object
for a given string value.
So when we call s1.intern,
we get back the canonicalized reference
to I space love space Java.
s3 gets assigned a reference to that.
So now, if I say,
string s4 equals s2.intern,
s4 will get a reference to that
exact same object instance.
So, the intern assures that two strings with the same value,
will reference the exact same object.
What that allows us to do then
is use that very inexpensive equals equals operator
to do the comparison.
So, s3 equals equals s4 returns true.
As you might expect, there is a bit of overhead
to interning a string.
So, in general, when you're doing a series
of one-off comparisons of strings,
you'll use the equals method to do that.
But, when you have situations where you expect
to do a lot of comparisons to a given set of string values,
that's where the intern method comes in.
You'll often intern a series of string values
you expect to search over and over again
and put those into an array or some other collection
and then as you search that collection,
you'll then intern the incoming values
and use that very inexpensive equal equals operator
to see if you can find the value
in that array or collection of intern string values.