We often need to convert non-string types into strings.
Having a value as a string
makes it easy to do things like build a message,
or display output to a user.
The string class provides a helper method called valueOf.
It provides overloads that will handle converting
many different types to strings.
And using it is really straight forward.
So, we have something like an integer here, iVal,
that we set to 100.
If we say sVal equals
string.valueOf iVal,
sVal will get the string, one zero zero.
Now, valueOf is useful when you need to do those
explicit conversions.
But, very often, Java will take care
of doing conversions to strings for you automatically.
Let's say we have some code here where we have two integers.
I has a value of two and j has a value of three.
If I say result equals i times j
and I now want to display out to the user
a full string showing the operation and the result.
So, I say i followed by plus
and the string space asterisk space.
When Java sees that I'm taking an integer
with a plus and the other is a string,
it knows that I actually want the string
representation of i.
So now, if I go in to say,
plus j plus space equals space,
then plus result,
Java will go through and convert i, j,
and result the strings for us
and then concatenate them all together,
so we get that complete string,
two space times space 3 space equals space six.
All right, it builds that string together for us
and took care of those conversions.
Now, in this case, we're dealing with a very simple type,
right, a very primitive type, an integer.
But what about things like more complex types,
like classes where the string representation
is not so easily known.
Well that's where the toString method comes in.
Remember we talked about that the object class
provides some standard methods
that all classes will have.
toString is the one we use to get the string representation
of a class.
Let's take a look at some code for that.
Now, remember that we have our flight class
that we've been using throughout the course.
So, here we created flight class instance
with a flight number of 175.
If I now say print line my flight is
and then we simply can concatenate on my flight,
what Java is going to do is call toString
on the object referenced by myflight.
Now, we haven't implemented toString
in the flight class.
So, it's going to call the implementation
from the object class.
And what that will do is give us results
that look something like this.
Of course we have that literal string,
myflight is,
but then what we get is
the fully qualified class name,
including the package that it's in,
followed by an at symbol,
followed by whatever value is returned
by the hash code method.
So that gives us kind of a unique representation
of this instance, but it's not really very helpful.
All right, so we can improve that.
So, if we look at our flight class,
remember that our flight class
had two ways of identifying flights.
A flight could be created to have a flight number,
or a flight could be created to have a flight class.
So, what we want to do now is have our toString method
represent a given flight instance in a meaningful way.
So, we'll go ahead and override toString
and what we'll do here is we'll check and say,
well, if it's a flight that has a flight number,
what we're going to do is return back the string
flight space hash and then add on the flight number.
If it's a flight that has a flight class instead,
we're just going to say flight space class space
and whatever that class character is.
So now if we take a look at this code over here,
when we call print line,
what we're actually going to get out is
"My flight is Flight #175".
So now we're getting back a more meaningful
string representation of that object instance.
And that's what we want to do inside of our toString method,
is provide that meaningful representation of an instance
as a string.