As we've talked about, strings are immutable.
And that means that any modification to a string
results in the creation of a new string.
And that's just not efficient.
But there are, of course, times
that we need to be able to efficiently
manipulate strings.
And that's where StringBuilder comes in.
StringBuilder provides us with a mutable string buffer,
providing us with an efficient way to manipulate strings.
Now although you don't have to,
when you create a StringBuilder instance,
you'll get the best performance if you pre-size the buffer.
Let's look at some code here.
I declare StringBuilder sb, say new StringBuilder 40.
Well that allocates out an instance of StringBuilder
that has room for 40 characters inside of it.
In fact, if we were to call the
sb.capacity method on that instance,
we'll get back the value 40.
Now the StringBuilder will grow automatically
if you exceed the capacity,
but you want to minimize how often that happens
because there's a fair bit of overhead
each time the system has to grow a StringBuilder instance.
StringBuilder has a number of methods available,
but the ones we use most commonly are append,
which lets us add new content
to the end of the StringBuilder,
or insert, which gives us the ability to add new content
within the body of the StringBuilder.
So, let's look at some code.
So, we have our flight we've been using here.
We have flight number 175.
And we'll have a string called location
with the value of Florida in it.
Let's say we want to build up a message.
So we want to go ahead and say,
sb.append I flew to space,
well that adds to the end of the StringBuilder.
The StringBuilder is empty.
That adds it to the beginning.
So then we say, sb.append location,
takes the value of location Florida,
adds that on to the end.
Literal string space on space,
that gets added on to the end.
Then we say sb.append myflight.
Well, myflight is a class, so we'll
go ahead and call toString on it.
So we get, flight #175.
So we've been able to build these four values together,
doing it all in a single buffer.
But let's say we come along a little further in our program
and we realize that we actually have access to the time
of this flight as well.
We want to go ahead and add that into the message,
but we want to put it somewhere
into the body of the message.
Let's say we want to do it just before the space
in the word on.
Now, since we know how many characters
we've written into this buffer from the beginning,
we could just count how many characters it takes
to move over to get there.
But, let's say we didn't know that.
Let's say that all we knew is that
we've added content inside of here
and we've added the word on
and then the information from our flight class.
And we want to calculate where the insert point is
going backwards.
So, from the end of the current values.
Let's see how we would do that.
So, I'm going to declare a variable position
and I'm just going to say sb.length
and that tells me how many characters are currently
in this StringBuilder instance.
Remember, capacity said how much space is allocated,
length says how much is in use.
And we'll say that we want to go back to length
of that literal on.
Now, honestly I could've use the integer value four here,
but I just wanted to show you that we can call string
methods on string literals.
And then we'll use our myflight toString.length.
All right, so that now tells us how far back we have to go
to get before that space before the word on.
So now with that, I can now say something like sb.insert.
Give it the position and then what I want to insert,
which is space at space.
What StringBuilder will do is move over that on flight #175
and then write the at in there.
And then if I say, sb.insert position plus four,
and I'm going to add the value of time in.
Right, the position plus four is just I want to get
past that space at space,
move to time as an integer,
but insert will take care of doing that conversion.
So now it'll move over the on flight #175
and write that nine in there.
So now we've got our content built exactly as we want it,
but it's not quite a string yet.
The way we get the string out
is the way we get the string out of any other class.
We simply call the toString method.
So, inside of here, if we say
string message equals sb.toString,
the message we'll then get, the actual string
I flew to Florida at 9 on Flight #175.
So StringBuilder gives us a really efficient way of building
and manipulating strings.