Throughout our discussions in this course,
recently we've been talking about classes.
Now, the thing we see when we talk about classes
is that classes provide convenience.
One of the conveniences is that all classes
inherit from the object class,
so we can use object as a standard way to interact
with all class instances.
So, that's a good thing.
Classes have fields and methods
that are specific to that type.
That means that we can have values
and operations directly associated with a type.
So that's a good thing.
One of the things we need to be aware of though
is that classes also have overhead.
Every class instance has a certain amount of memory
that's always taken up just by the fact that it's a class
and that's before it even has
its own specific values inside of there.
So, generally we consider that,
that little bit of extra overhead worthwhile
to get those conveniences.
Now, the thing is that primitive types
focus on efficiency, where we use them a lot.
So, we want primitive types, in general,
to be very lightweight.
All right, so the idea is that
if you have a four byte int,
it simply occupies four bytes, nothing beyond that.
So, that's certainly a good thing.
But now, in order to get that efficiency
we have to give some things up.
We can't have fields or methods
associated with primitive types.
And primitive types cannot be treated as objects.
And most of the time,
this division between classes and primitive types
gives us kind of a really effective way to work.
But there are times when we're working with primitive values
that we're willing to give up these efficiencies
in order to get the convenience that we have with classes.
And that's where the primitive wrapper classes come in.
The primitive wrapper classes give us
the capability of classes,
but they do also incur that overhead,
but they allow us to have these capabilities
when interacting with primitive values.
Now, the primitive classes are indeed classes.
As with all classes, they inherit from the object class
and each of the primitive types
has a corresponding wrapper class.
So, the Boolean primitive type
has a wrapper class called Boolean.
The only difference is capital B for the class,
lowercase B for the primitive type.
The char primitive types
has a class called Character.
And it when it comes to the numeric classes,
they all have a common base class called number.
Number is an abstract class that all the numeric
primitive wrapper classes inherit from.
We have four classes, one for each of the integer types.
And we have two, one for each of the
floating point types.
And, again, these are all real classes.
So they can be treated as object
and they have fields and methods associated with them
that are particular to that type.
One thing to be aware of,
all the primitive wrapper classes are immutable.
So, a given instance always has the same value inside of it.
So, if you have a reference to a instance
of one of the primitive wrapper classes
and you do something that changes the value
you will get a reference
to a different instance of that class.
Very much like working with strings.
So, you just want to be aware of that.
And as you would expect, you often have to convert between
the wrapper classes and the primitives.
And Java provides a number of ways to handle that.
The news is that the most common scenarios
are handled automatically by Java.
And we take a look at some code.
So we go in here and we declare
Integer a equals 100.
Well Integer a means that a is a reference
to an instance of the integer wrapper class.
But 100 is the primitive value 100.
Java will take care of
getting a reference to an instance of the integer class
that has the value 100 inside of it.
Now, if we say int b equals a,
well b is a primitive type,
a is a reference to a wrapper class.
Java will take care getting the value out of a
and just to note that the idea of conversions
happens with both variables and literals.
All right, so just like we had an integer a equals 100,
we could have integer c equals b,
while b is a primitive variable,
c is a reference to the integer class.
Java will take care of getting a reference
to the integer class that has the same value
that b has inside of it.
When it comes to making these conversions
Java also provides methods for doing explicit conversions.
If you want to convert from a primitive type
to a wrapper class,
the wrapper classes all have a valueOf method on them.
That process is known as boxing.
The idea of boxing is that you take a primitive value
and you wrap it up in a box,
which is now the class.
If you want to convert from a wrapper class
to the primitive type,
each of the wrapper classes has a,
what I call xxxValue method.
And basically the xxx
is the name of the primitive type.
So integer has integer.intValue.
Double has double.doubleValue.
As you might expect, this is what's called unboxing.
To see this in practice,
I have a little more code here.
We'll say integer d equals
integer.valueOf 100.
All right, it takes that primitive 100
and gives us back a reference to the integer class
with that same value.
Int e equals d.intvalue.
d is a reference to one of the wrapper classes.
That intValue method gives us the value out of it.
And again, integer f equals integer.valueOf e.
Again, it gives us a wrapper class reference
that corresponds to the value of e.
If you take a look at the code at the top there,
we say integer a equals 100.
And then we look at integer d equals integer.valueOf 100.
You notice that we're doing very much the same thing there.
It turns out, we're actually doing exactly the same thing.
In a situation like that, the compiler actually injects
that integer.valueOf call for us.
In fact, we don't really have to use these valueOf's
and intValues that often anymore.
Prior to Java 5, you always had to use them.
Starting at Java 5,
the compiler started inferring their usage.
So a good deal of the time, you can rely on the compiler
to do the conversion for you.
But know that those methods are there if you need them.
And just to be clear, they're not limited to integers.
These are there for all of the wrapper classes.
So I look here like Float g equals float.valueOf.
Right, that returns back a reference
to the float class, with a value of 18.125 inside of it.
All right, I say float h equals g.floatValue.
That gives me the primitive value back out
of that instance reference by g.
Now, there's one other type conversion
we need to think about.
And that's strings.
And Java provides mechanisms for that as well.
If we want to convert a string to a primitive value,
each of the wrapper classes has a parse method on it.
So, like integer has parse.int.
That will parse a string value
and give you back the primitive value corresponding to it.
We also have an overload of valueOf that accepts a string.
And this give you back a reference to a wrapper class.
So, we just look at that in code.
If I say, I have a string here s with a value of 87.44.
If I say, double s1 equals double.parsedouble of s,
notice that even though I'm calling parse double
on the wrapper class double,
it returns back a primitive type.
It actually returns back to primitive 87.44.
Whereas if I say double s2 double.valueOf s,
valueOf returns back a reference to
a wrapper class that has that value, 87.44 inside of it.