Now that we have the primitive wrapper classes,
we can take advantage of the capabilities
that all classes have
when working with our primitive types.
For example, we can now treat the primitive types
as object.
So, if we have a situation where
we have maybe an object array
or any other type that expects object references,
in addition to putting in things like a reference
to a flight class or a passenger class,
we could even drop in a value like 100.
Right and what happens in this case is that
Java will go ahead and get a reference to an instance
of the integer wrapper class, with a value of 100
and assign that reference into stuff sub two.
We also have the benefit of null references.
So we have a distinct idea of a value not being set.
Let's take a look at our flight class here.
Our flight class, as you'll recall,
has an int for flightNumber
and a char for flightClass.
So, inside of our two string method,
we said well, if flightNumber is greater than zero,
we go ahead and return back a string
containing the flight number.
Of course, the idea there is that we're saying that,
well, if the flight number is greater than zero,
we know it's been set, but we make the assumption
that if it's not greater than zero,
it must not have been set.
Even though it's potentially possible
to have a flight with a flight number of zero.
Then we also make the assumption that well,
if flight number is not greater than zero,
well you must have set flight class
because we don't really have a distinct way of knowing
that the values haven't been set.
But if we now convert our int and our char
to the wrapper class equivalent,
so we take flightNumber and we make that an integer instead
we take our flightClass and make that a character instead,
now we go inside of our two string method.
We want to check and see if flightNumber has been set,
rather than check and see if it's greater than zero,
we can check to see if it's not equal to null.
If it's not equal to null, we know it's been set,
no matter what value inside of there.
When it comes to checking the flightCass,
rather than just assuming that,
well flightNumber wasn't set,
they might've set flightClass,
we can actually check and see if flightClass
is not equal to null.
So that gives us, instead of just two states,
you've set one or the other.
We have three states.
You could've set one, you could've set the other,
or, maybe, you didn't set anything at all.
So, we're getting that benefit that we've had,
with our classes all along,
now with our primitive values.
Now, as we mentioned, the wrapper classes
provide members as well.
Let's take a look at just a few of those.
So, I have here on screen, a list of just a few
of the members in each of the classes.
If you look at the integer classes,
Byte, Short, Integer and Long,
you see that we have things like
MIN_VALUE and MAX_VALUE,
which are fields that tell us the bottom range
and the top range of that each type.
A method like bitCount that lets us see
the individual bit values in an instance.
Or things like toBinaryString that lets us
get a string back with the
binary representation of an instance.
On our floating points, we have MIN_VALUE
and MAX_VALUE again for bottom in range, top in range.
But notice it introduces concepts like infinite
or not a number.
Or in Character.
Once again we have a minimum value and
a maximum value,
but then we also have things like
isDigit and isLetter to see what kind of character
is inside of a given instance.
And then on Boolean, we even have fields for representing
a reference to a true instance or a false instance.
Now, these members I have on screen here
are just a tiny, tiny sampling.
To see the complete list of members,
over there on the right-hand column,
I have a shortcut link to the documentation
on each individual class.
Check those out when you have a chance,
and you'll see that there's actually a lot going on
with each of these individual wrapper classes.