Let's take a look at how the wrapper classes
affect the idea of comparing for equality.
So, we have some code here where we have a variable,
i1000a, whose type is integer.
We assign it 10 times 10 times 10.
So, we have the value 1000
stored into the integer wrapper class.
And I say integer i1000B equals 100 times 10.
So, that also has the value 1000
stored into an instance of the integer wrapper class.
Now, if I compare them using the equals equals operator.
Now, if these were two primitive variables,
equals equals would compare just fine.
But, because these are references to classes,
this will actually test for false.
Because remember, equals equals only returns true
if both references point to the same exact object.
So, when we're working with these wrapper classes,
we generally want to use the equals method,
to check for equality.
So, we say i1000A.equals i1000B,
we get back the value true,
because it actually checks the value
stored inside each one.
But let's look at another example.
I have a variable i8A, which again
is a reference of type integer,
equals four times two, so it has the value of eight
in that integer wrapper class.
Then I have integer i8B equals two times two times two.
So, again it has the value eight
stored inside of a integer wrapper class.
But now when I do i8A equals equals i8B,
I get back true.
Now remember that that can only return true
if both those references point to the same exact object.
And that turns out to be true because in Java,
certain boxing conversions are defined
to always return back a reference
to the exact same instance.
And there are five types when that happens.
You have an int, a short, or a byte
in the range of minus 128 to positive 127.
When that is converted into
the corresponding wrapper class,
you will always get a reference to the same exact object
for the same exact value.
All right, so an int of value five,
when it's converted to an integer,
it will always be a reference
to the same exact integer instance.
On the char type, it's any character value
from the range of the character zero
all the way up to the character zero zero ff.
And for Boolean, it's all of its values.
Because, remember Boolean only has two.
True or false.
So any time you convert to Boolean value true
to the class capital B Boolean,
all the trues will point to the same object instance
and all the falses will point to the same object instance.