Often times in our programs, we'll have fields
that we don't allow to be set once they've been initialized.
That's where final fields come in.
Now, there are two kinds of final fields.
A simple final field must be set
during the creation of an object instance.
That means it must be set using either a field initializer,
an initialization block, or a constructor.
Let's look at some code that uses that.
Remember we have our passenger class.
Remember our passenger class,
we had this idea that a passenger could be created
with a number of free bags that they received.
And we set that, of course, inside of our constructor.
Now, we may define in our business model,
the fact that it's a number of free bags
is considered an aspect of the passenger.
So, it can only be set
during the creation of that passenger.
So, we can do that by taking our free bags declaration
and simply including the word final there.
By including that word final,
any attempt to set free bags
after it's been set in the constructor
would actually result in a compile error.
So compiler enforces that rule
that it can't be assigned once it's been set.
Now, there's also what's known as a static final field.
Static final fields create, basically, named constants.
A static final field cannot be changed
in any object instance.
Its value is actually tied to the class itself.
So, we look at that in code.
Look at our flight class.
Remember that our flight class has this concept
of the number of seats on a flight.
So an instance of our flight class
can set the number of seats.
So we simply have a setter to do that.
But, let's say that the Federal Aviation Administration,
right, that's the organization in the United States
that sets the rules for planes.
Let's say that they set a rule
that there's a maximum number of seats
that a flight is allowed to have.
And we'll say that that's 550.
So, we can declare a static final field called
MAX_FAA_SEATS
that has a value of 550.
Now, the convention is,
that whenever you have a static final,
you use all caps for the name of the field.
And what we can do here is down inside of our set seats,
we can actually use that MAX_FAA_SEATS
just like it's a value.
All right, so inside of here let's say we make some room
and we can actually put a check in to say well,
if seats is less than or equal to MAX_FAA_SEATS, we set it.
Otherwise, we handle the error.
The key here is that, no object instance can create this.
MAX_FAA_SEATS will have a value of 550
in all flight instances.
We use this most commonly
when we're trying to avoid what we often call magic numbers.
Where we don't like to put literal numbers
inside of our code.
Because when we look at this code,
we know that the reason we're checking the value of seats
is that the FAA has a rule on the max.
If we just dropped a 550 in there,
that wouldn't necessarily make sense.
Now, we often have times where we want to limit
a type to a finite number of values
And that's where the enumeration types come in.
Enumeration types allow us to define a type
that has a list of valid values.
We declare those using the enum keyword.
So let's go ahead and declare an enum for the
jobs that the flight crew is allowed to have.
So you notice we use the word enum there
instead of the word class.
And then inside there we can simply
provide a comma separated list of the valid values.
Let's say the flight crew jobs could be a Pilot,
a CoPilot,
a FlightAttendant, or an AirMarshal.
So now we can use FlightCrewJob as a type.
So, let's say we introduce a new class here
called CrewMember.
Crew members have a job of type FlightCrewJob,
so we can go ahead and set that
as part of the constructor of CrewMember.
As well as we have a setter to change the job
of a crew member.
So now if we go off and create an instance of CrewMember,
called Judy, one of our new crew members,
we can give her a job,
so we'll say she's a copilot.
So, notice the way we do this
is we use the name of the enumeration
dot one of the values.
So, we've created Judy to be a copilot.
Let's say some time goes by
and Judy get a promotion.
Well, we can now make Judy the pilot.
So we can set that Judy.setJob,
again we use the enumeration name FlightCrewJob
dot and the value, Pilot.
Enumerations are most commonly used in this way.
Defining this finite list of values.
But, enumeration types actually
have a number of much more advanced capabilities beyond this
that we'll talk about later in the course.