To wrap up, remember that variables are strongly typed in Java.
And the foundation of the Java type system
are the primitive types.
We saw that there were four categories of those.
Integers, floating point, character, and Boolean.
But then within the integer and floating point types,
there are even types of varying sizes.
So integers could be as small as a byte with only 8 bits,
or as large as a long with 64 bits.
Similarly floating points had float with 32 bits
and double with 64 bits.
We have a really rich list of math operators.
Anything from the basic operations,
like add, subtract, multiply, and divide,
to the postfix and prefix operators,
which allow us increment and decrement values,
to the compound assignment operators
that allow us to apply an operation to the value
in a variable and store that result
back into the same variable.
We learned too that our math operators follow
a well-defined order of precedence.
Remember that you can actually affect an order of precedence
by using parenthesis.
And then when it comes to type conversions,
we often have to move between different types
because as our programs, as they get more complexity,
will likely involve multiple data types.
The compiler can handle type conversions that are widening,
moving from one type to another that can hold larger values.
But you can also use casting to explicitly perform those type conversions
that the compiler can't perform automatically.