In order to do anything interesting in a program,
we have to have the ability to store and manipulate values.
What allows us to do that are what we call variables.
A variable, simply put, is just named data storage.
Now Java is a strongly typed language.
Now what that means is that when we declare a variable,
like in this case, we have a variable named datavalue,
we have to specify the type of that variable.
In this case, it's what we call an int,
something that can store integers.
So what that means is that the datavalue variable
can only store things that are compatible with the type int.
As we go through the course, we'll talk about this idea
of one typing compatible with another.
Now, we declare a variable, we can of course, then
assign a value to it, right,
so our variable, datavalue, now holds the value 100.
Now, when we use variables,
we can do it the way we've done here
where we declare it, then assign it
or as a matter of convenience,
we can declare them and assign them in a single statement.
Java is a language that allows you to modify
the value stored in a variable.
So you can store an initial value in a variable
and throughout the course of your program,
you can modify the value that's stored inside that variable.
When it comes to naming variables in Java,
we follow a combination of rules and conventions.
The rules allow us to use letters, numbers,
the dollar signs, and the underscore
but by convention, we only use letters and numbers.
The rules require that that first character is not a number,
but since convention say that we never use a dollar sign
or an underscore, that means that
we always end up starting it with a letter.
So some examples are like,
if I wanted to declare a variable called total,
writes t-o-t-a-l, all right that's valid
or grade4 because the four is not the first character,
that's a valid variable name.
By convention, we follow the naming style
known as Camel Case.
What that means is that the first letter of the variable
name is a lowercase letter.
We start each word after the first with an uppercase letter
and all other letters are lowercase.
Example would be bankAccountBalance.
All right, the first word is bank.
That starts with lowercase.
The second word's account, so we have a capital A.
Next word is balance, it's a capital B.
Another example, level2Training.
First word level is all lowercase.
We still have the number two in there, that's valid,
but when we start the next word, training,
we use a capital T.
So let's take a look now at a simple case
of using some variables.
So I've got a program stubbed out here
with my entry into my main method.
I'm going to, again, declare a variable here
called myVar, whose type int.
We can also call this a local variable
just because it's local to the method mean
and we'll see some other ways to store information
that are not local throughout this course.
But here we have local variable myVar.
If I go ahead and try to use myVar right now
instead of trying to print it out,
that would actually be an error
because local variables don't automatically
get a value.
There's nothing define stored inside of them
so we don't want to do that.
Before we actually use a variable,
we want to make sure
and put something inside of it.
So in this case, I have stored the value 50
inside of myVar.
So, of course, now if I print that out,
I'll get the value 50.
Now I can go ahead and declare another variable here,
I'll call anotherVar.
You'll notice that my variables don't have to be
all declared at the top.
I can declare them anywhere in my flow of logic
that I want to.
So my anotherVar has a value of 100 stored inside of it.
If I print that out,
of course I get 100.
I can assign one variable to another.
So I've assigned anotherVar to myVar.
What I'm saying is that I'm assigning the value
of anotherVar to myVar,
so if I print out myVar,
I get the value 100.
And what's interesting to note is that
if I go out here and I change anotherVar,
so I assign it to 200,
if I print it out it has 200 in it.
But if I print out myVar,
it still only has 100 in it.
Basically we're doing what's called
copy by value, there.
We'll talk a little bit more shortly
about what's actually happening under the covers
that allows the sign between one variable and another
without them staying linked.
But the key thing to remember here
is that you can declare variables,
we can assign values to them, we can modify our variables,
and we can assign values from one variable to another.