So as we've seen when we declare variables,
we give them a type.
One of the most fundamental types in Java
are what are called primitive data types,
and these are the data types
that are actually built into the language.
Now when you hear the term primitive data type,
you may think there's something kind of lowly about them.
Something less than modern about them,
but that's not true at all.
Primitive data types are actually very important.
They're really the foundation of all other types
that we use in Java.
So they're really that strong foundation
that we're going to build on
for any other data types we use in our programs.
Now there are four categories of primitive types in Java.
There are the integer types, floating point,
character, and Boolean.
So let's look first at the integer types.
Now, there are four different integer types,
but the difference in them really is just the size
of storage that they take up.
But that difference in the size of storage that they take up
affects the range of values that can be stored there.
The smallest integer type is the byte type.
It takes up 8 bits,
so it can only store between -128 and 127,
and so we see we declare our variable type byte
and we assign the integer literal to it.
So here we have a byte numberOfEnglishLetters = 26.
The next large integer type is short,
which takes up 16 bits.
Lets you store between -32,000 and 32,000.
Use it exactly the same way.
So we have here short feetInMile = 5283.
Probably the most commonly used integer type
is the one called int.
That's a 32 bit integer.
And being 32 bits, it lets you store between
2,000,000,000 and 2,000,000,000.
And then the big integer type
is what we call a long.
It's a big 64 bit integer
and you can see it can store huge values in it.
The key thing to notice, though,
is that when you use a long literal value,
you have to put that capital L at the end of it.
Now Java also has floating point types.
Now, the floating point types can form to the IEEE standard
for floating point,
and that may or may not be meaningful to you.
What it really comes down to is that floating points
allow you to store values
that have a fractional portion to them.
Basically, it support positive, negative, and zero values
that have some fractional portion.
There's a lot of nuances to the way floating points work.
They're kind of outside the scope of this course,
but I've got the URL on the screen there for you.
If you want to know a lot more about the details
in terms of how floating points work
and the oddities of them,
I encourage you to check that out.
But basically, we have our two floating point types in Java.
First, we have the float type which is a 32 bit
floating point value.
Notice that when we use the float type,
we have to put the "f" at the end of any constance for it,
so when we declare this float
called milesInAMarathon,
we say 26.2f,
saying that it's actually a floating point value.
And then we also have double,
which is a 64 bit floating point value.
If you just use a literal that has a decimal in it,
the compiler assumes it's a double,
which can also make it explicitly a double
by putting a "d" at the end.
So we look here we have double atomWithinMeters.
You see that 0.0001d denotes that that is a double literal.
And our last two primitive types are character and Boolean.
A character, or the acts of a char type,
stores a single Unicode character.
Basically, you denote the literals of these
by just using a single apostrophe or a single quote
surrounding the constant.
If I say char regularU= and I put 'U',
that assigns that char into it.
I know this is different than strings.
We'll talk about strings later.
Char is just a single character value.
And because the char type supports Unicode,
you can actually specify
any valid Unicode character in there.
So if you want to assign a Unicode character
you don't have on your keyboard,
you can use the Unicode code point
by using that slash U notation.
So you see here I've got this char accentedU
with the '\u00DA'
says that that is actually a U with an accent on it.
And then finally we have our Boolean types.
Our Boolean types store true and false.
The literals for that are true and false.
So if I say Boolean iLoveJava = true.