Java primitive types are stored by value.
And that's important to understand
because it affects the behavior of applications
when we assign values from one variable to another.
Let's take a look here.
If I declare an integral variable called firstValue
and I assign the value 100 to it,
what's actually happening under the covers
is that an area of memory is being allocated.
It's named firstValue.
And the value 100 is stored inside that memory.
So now if I declare another variable,
in this case otherValue
and I assign firstValue to it,
again I'm allocating an area of storage.
I'm giving it a name,
otherValue.
And when I make the assignment,
the value 100 is being copied from firstValue
into other value.
And what that means is that
there's a distinctly separate copy of that value 100
being moved over into other value.
What that allows me to do, then,
is that if I make modifications to firstValue,
for example, assign the value of 50 to it,
that 50 replaces what's in firstValue,
but it leaves the variable called otherValue
completely untouched.
And that's what I mean by being stored by value.
So each primitive type variable
has its own separate copy of the data.