Something we commonly have to do in our programs
is perform arithmetic operations.
Java provides three basic categories
of operators for performing math operations.
There are the basic operators
like add, subtract, multiply, and divide.
What are called prefix and postfix operators
and then there are called compound assignment operators.
The basic math operators are just what you would expect.
Things like add, subtract, multiply, and divide.
The operators we use for these are, again,
things that are very familiar,
where if I'm adding I need a plus sign.
When I do things like add,
it doesn't really matter whether I'm using a floating point
or an integer.
So if I say 1+2, the answer is going to be 3.
For subtract we use the minus sign.
Again, it doesn't really matter whether we're using
floating point or integers.
If I subtract 4 from 5, I get 1.
If we multiply we use an asterisk.
4 times 2 is 8.
All this stuff is really straight forward.
As we get to the divide operations, though,
there are some differences between floating point
and integer.
If I take 13.0 and divide it by 5.0,
that's a floating point operation.
Floating points have fractions.
So I will get 2.6.
But now if I take the integer 13 divided by 5,
that's an integer operations.
Integers don't have fractions.
So I'll actually get just 2.
It doesn't matter what the fractional portion would be,
it's just dropped.
There's no rounding or anything,
it's just the whole number of times
that you can do the division.
So 5 goes into 13 two whole times.
There's another operator called the modulus operator,
also known as the remainder operator,
and that gives you the remainder of the divide.
So let's look at the integer first on this one.
If I say 13 modulus 5, that's the percent symbol,
my answer will be 3.
5 goes into 13 two whole times,
leaving three.
5 times 2 is 10,
subtract 10 from 13,
you get 3.
And you can do a modulus on floating point, as well.
So I do 13.0 % 5.0, I'll have a remainder of 3.0.
As we look at the prefix and postfix operators,
they allow us to operate directly on value.
The ++ symbol is the increment.
Increments value by 1.
The -- symbol,
decrements value by 1.
So if we look here,
if I have a variable myVal and I set it to 5,
if I say print out ++myVal,
that's the increment operator,
because it's before the actual variable,
the ++ before the variable,
that's a prefix,
which means that the operation is actually applied
before we get the value back.
So the result as print statement is actually 6.
The 5 was incremented for a print out of a 6.
If I print myVal again,
it's still 6.
But now if I move the operator after the variable,
it's now a postfix operator.
What that means is that I get the value back
and then the operations perform.
So if I look at similar code here,
where I have my variable myVal,
I set it to 5,
but this time I print it out I say myVal ++,
so I'm doing a postfix increment.
The value printed will be 5
because that 5 was returned.
But myVal is now incremented.
If I print myVal now, I will get 6.
The last category of math operators
are what we call compound assignment operators.
What these do is they combine an operation
and the assignment,
so basically it looks at the right side of the operator,
takes whatever that is
and applies the operation to the left side
and then stores the value into the left side.
So let's see what that looks like.
Right here I have myVal.
I set it equal to 50.
If I say myVal -= 5,
so the right hand side's value is 5,
the left hand side value is currently 50,
it applies the operation, which is the minus sign,
so it subtracts 5 from 50,
and then stores that value back into myVal.
So if I print out myVal,
myVal has 45.
And they're available for all five basic math operations.
In my experience, I used the minus equals
and the plus equals far in a way the most,
but you do find occasions to use the other ones, as well.
So looking at another example,
if I have a int result = 100
and I have two more variables.
val1 = 5 and val2 = 10.
If I now say result /= val1 * val2,
remember that it's going to take the complete result
of the right side.
So if I look at val1 times val2,
the result of 5 times 10 is 50.
It then take the existing value and result,
which in this case is 100,
and it then takes that operator,
which is divide,
and performs that operation between them.
So it's going to divide 100 by 50
and then store that back into our variable called result.
So we print out the value of 2.