To get a better sense of how operator precedence works,
let's take a look at some code.
We have simple program here
with four variables declared at the top.
What we want to do is set up some math operations
and see how the order of precedence
affects the result we get.
Let's go ahead and declare an integer for a result.
So I'll just call that result1.
What you want to do here
is you want to take the variable valA,
then I'm going to go ahead and subtract valB from it,
and then I'll divide that by valC.
Now I'm going to go ahead and just duplicate that now
so I have another one just like it.
Call this one result2.
And all I'm going to do
is put a parenthesis in,
put a parenthesis around valA and valB here.
All right we have these parenthesis in place,
so the last thing we want to do
is just go ahead and print these guys out.
All right, so let's go ahead and run it.
And as we run it,
you can see that we get two very different results.
The first one, result1, gives us a value of 19.
The second one, result2, gives us a value of 5.
What's happening there?
Well on the first line, where we set result1,
remember that multiplicative operations
take precedence over additive operations.
So division is a multiplicative operation,
so basically valueB, which is 6,
was divided by valueC, which is 3,
which gave us the result of 2.
So then we subtracted that 2 from valA, which is 21,
giving us 19.
The second one, result2, because of the parenthesis,
we overrode that normal order of operations.
As a result, we first subtracted 6 from 21,
which gave us 15,
and then we divided that by 3,
which gave us the result 5.
So we overrode that normal order of operations
by adding parenthesis.
So let's look at another case here.
We'll go and set up another equation.
We'll set up a result3 here.
And for result3, what we'll do is we'll set valA,
we'll divide that by valC,
then we'll multiply that times valD,
and then finally add in valB.
That sets up one.
So let's go ahead and copy this now.
And we'll duplicate it,
but then we'll modify it a little bit.
So we'll call a result here result4.
We'll use some parenthesis.
So the first thing I'll do is put parenthesis
around this addition here,
valD and valB,
and then what I'll do
is I'll put another set around valC
and the result of valD plus valB.
So I've now got nested parenthesis.
So with that in place now,
what I want to do is just go ahead
and print these guys out, as well.
Okay, we're all set there.
Let's go ahead and run it.
You'll notice again,
we get very different results.
For the result3 we get 13.
For result4 we get the number 1.
Well what's different?
Well again remember that multiplicative operations
come ahead of additive,
and then when two operations are on the same precedence,
they're left to right.
So on our result3, the first thing that happens is valA
is divided by valC.
valA has a value of 21,
valC has a value of 3,
so that gives us a value of 7.
Then that's multiplied by valD,
which has a value of 1,
so it's still 7,
and then we add in valB,
which gives us a value of 6.
And that gives us 13.
But now in result4,
because of the parenthesis,
we're changing that order of operations.
So we have nested parenthesis
going to the inner most ones,
so first we get valD plus valB.
So valD is 1, valB is 6,
so 1 plus 6 is 7.
We multiply that times valC, which is 3, which is 21.
And then we divide valA, which is 21,
by 21, giving us the result of 1.