Operations in our applications
will commonly involve multiple data types.
Because of that,
we have to deal with type conversions.
Now there are implicit type conversions
and those are type conversions
that are performed automatically by the compiler.
To see a simple example of that,
we look at something like here
we have an integer iVal
that we have assigned the value of 50.
If I then saw long lval = iVal,
the compiler has to convert that 32 bit integer iVal
into a 64 bit integer as its stored into lval.
There are also explicit type conversions
and these are conversions
that I explicitly perform in my code.
I do that using a cast operator.
See here if I had that long lval = 50,
so I'm now assigning 64 bit integer
the value of 50,
if I want to assign that into this iVal,
a 32 bit integer,
I have to explicitly cast it.
I have to tell the compiler
that I want to go from that 64 bit integer
into a 32 bit integer.
And I do that by using type you want to convert to,
in this case int,
putting it inside the parenthesis,
and putting it next to the value I want to cast.
So this says, the int parenthesis says,
to take the lval and cast it down to a 32 bit integer.
If we looked at these implicit type conversions,
these are generally what we would call widening conversions
and these can be done automatically
because we're moving to a wider data type.
So if I have a 32 bit integer
and I want to move to a 64 bit integer,
that's wider, right?
So the values can be safely moved
so those can be done implicitly.
The compiler has to make decisions
about how to make these conversions.
The rules are pretty straight forward.
If I have an expression with multiple integer sizes in it,
if we have a short and a long,
whatever the largest integer size is
is what we convert it to.
So if I do an operation with a short and a long,
the short will be implicitly cast into a long.
By performing an operation with mixed floating point sizes,
so I have a float and a double,
they'll always go to the double.
The double is the largest floating point size.
If I have an operation that uses integer types
and floating point types,
the compiler will cast to whatever the largest
floating point in the equation is.
So if I do an operation with a long and a float,
the long will be cast into a float.
If I do an operation with a long and a double,
the long will then be cast to a double.
Explicit type conversions are the ones
that we explicitly perform in our code
when using this cast operation.
When we do that,
we're taking responsibility for whatever happens
as a result of that type conversion.
Because of that,
we can perform both widening conversions
and narrowing.
So widening going from a 32 bit to say a 64 bit,
narrowing, going from a 64 bit down to a 32 bit.
We just want to be aware
that we know what could potentially happen.
If we do an explicit cast
from a floating point to an integer,
well floating points can have fractial portions,
integers can't.
So any fractional portion would be dropped
when I cast that float down to an integer.
You want to be careful
when performing a narrowing conversion.
If I have a 64 bit integer,
it has the ability to hold values that are too large
to fit into a 32 bit integer.
So if I cast that 64 bit to a 32 bit,
the program will actually do it,
but if the value is too large to fit into a 32 bit,
you'll get some odd results from that.
So you want to make sure that
when you're doing a narrowing cast,
that you know that what you're doing is safe.
And the last one is just
that you want to be careful when converting
from an integer to a floating point
because if you have an integer
with a large number of significant digits,
because of the way floating points are stored,
you could lose some of those significant digits.
The deep details of how these type conversions occur
are beyond the scope of this course,
but if you'd like to understand them in more detail.
I've got that URL on the screen for you
that actually points to the Java documentation
and talks about those details.
You check that out,
you'll particularly want to look at the sections
on widening primitive conversion
and narrowing primitive conversion.