Let's jump into some code now
to see these type conversion behaviors in action.
We have a simple program here
that has some declarations at the top.
Float, double, byte, short, and long,
and the variables for each name to help identify
what they're types are.
Like float is floatVal,
long is longVal.
And the program will print out a success message
if it runs.
So let's just see how some of these type conversions
come into play.
So first of all, let's just go ahead and create a variable.
We have a short which is called result.
In fact, let's go ahead and call it result1.
And let's just do a simple assignment.
So first, we'll just assign the byteVal to it.
And now as we expect,
if I go ahead and run this,
so this'll run successfully.
We know that's a valid assignment
because a byte can be assigned into a short
because that is a widening conversion.
If I take this byteVal, though,
and I make it a longVal instead,
so now it's actually a long.
If I run this,
I get an error message here saying incompatible types,
possible loss of conversion from long to short.
So what I can do here is that I can do an explicit cast.
I'll just put short in front of this.
So now it's valid so I can run it.
Of course, it works.
Because the long could not go into the short
because that was a narrowing conversion,
but by putting the explicit cast in front of it,
now it's valid.
If I want to, I can put a cast notation in any time I want.
If I want to be very explicit and say that,
you know, I know although the byte conversion is legal,
I want to explicitly show that I am casting it,
by putting the short cast in there.
I can do that, and that's completely legal.
So let's take a look at another scenario.
I'm going to create another variable called result2
and result2 is a short, as well.
And what I want to do here,
is I'm just going to take my byte value
and I want to subtract the long value.
Now we know that's not legal,
because the result of the expression
is going to be the size of the largest integer in it,
which is the long.
So if I run this,
I just get an error saying that it's not valid
to convert a long to a short.
Let's say I want to go ahead
and keep that result to a short.
Well I need to do a cast.
But what I want to cast this time
is the value of the entire result here.
So what I'm going to do
is put the short cast in front of it here,
then what I'll do is go ahead
and wrap the whole thing in parenthesis.
So now, what we're saying
is that the result of byteVal minus longVal,
which will be a size long,
we want to cast that down to a short.
So we're going to run this now.
It will run successfully.
So now let's try another one.
Go ahead and declare another one called result3,
and I'll declare this one as a long.
So I've got my result3
and what I'll do here is I'll assign that our longVal
minus our floatVal.
So now if I run that,
my error now says that it's a lost conversion
converting from a float to a long
because whenever we have a integer type
and any floating point type,
the result is going to be the floating point type.
So let's go ahead and convert our result now to a float.
So I've made that a float
so I should be able to go ahead and run it.
And it runs successfully.
But now if I take the floatVal here
and I convert this to be a doubleVal
and if I try to run this,
I'll get the error
because it says the result is going to be a double.
Because again, when you do an integer to floating point,
it's the size of the largest floating point in the equation.
So let's go ahead and make this result a double,
so now we can run it.
All right, let's look at one more.
So I'm going to have another result that I'll make a long.
So this result we're calling result4
and what I'll do here,
is I'll just take the short value
and subtract the long value from it.
Now we know that's valid
because the largest type in there is the long
and the result's long so that's okay,
but now let's go ahead and add in a floatVal.
So if I run it now,
I'll get an error message saying
it doesn't know how to convert a float to a long.
Let's go one step further now
and let's go ahead also and add in our doubleVal.
Now if we run it, we'll still get an error,
but now it says it's unable to convert a double to a long.
So as we see our result here,
our errors are changing based on the types
that are involved.
When it was all integers,
it was the size of the largest integer there.
Once there was a floating point involved,
it's the size of the largest floating point.
So one of them is a short and a long is a long
and when it's a short, a long, and a float,
the result became a float,
and when it was a short, a long, a float, and a double,
the result became a double.
So to run this, let's go ahead and cast this whole thing
to be a long.
So I'll make this a long.
Again, we'll wrap the whole thing in parenthesis,
and now we should be able to run it just fine.