Welcome to the next module,
in the Pluralsight Java Fundamentals course
in the Java language.
In this module, we're going to cover working with packages.
My name is Jim Wilson.
So as we go through this module,
the first thing we'll look at is
what exactly is a package in Java.
We'll look at a lot of capabilities of packages
and the benefits they provide,
such as packages acting as a name space.
What does it mean to import a package?
How do we use packages to limit access to content?
So we can have types and capabilities
that are visible inside of a package
but not outside of a package
and then this idea of distributing packages
and working with Java Archive Files
or otherwise known as JAR files.