Packages are an important concept in Java
but they're actually a pretty simple concept.
Basically a package is just a group of related types.
But by putting our types in packages,
we get kind of three core benefits.
One, packages create a name space
They provide a way for us to avoid type naming collisions.
To provide an access boundary.
They provide a way for us to limit access to types
and types members and also,
they act as a way for us to distribute our types.
Now we'll look at each one of these ideas in detail
throughout this module but first,
let's take a look at the idea of how we declare packages.
Now each source file identifies the associated package.
We do that by using the package keyword.
The package declaration and a source file
must appear before any type declarations.
If we take a look at our idea of our flight class here
that we've been using throughout the course.
To put that into a packet,
we simply added the keyword package
and then the name of that package.
In this case, XXXXXX.
Once that package declaration's in the source file,
any types that appear within that source file
will now be part of that package.
Now obviously, a package name like XXXXXX
is not going to be very useful
in terms of dealing with naming collisions and so forth.
So in this next clip, let's take a look
at this idea of packages being useful as a name space