As we mentioned, packages create a name space
which is useful in avoiding naming collisions
and that's because the package name
becomes part of the type name.
Looking at our flight class,
the flight class is now part of that package
and the package's name, again,
is part of now the flight class's name.
But now naming a package all X's
is not going to be very useful
in avoiding naming collisions.
But you recall from Module two,
we mentioned that we follow a convention
in our package names that creates uniqueness
and what we do is we use reverse domain naming.
What that means is that if we take
something like Pluralsight.com.
Now Pluralsight has registered with an authority
to have the rights to use the domain
Pluralsight.com and no one else in the world
has the rights to use that domain.
So we make our package names a deviation
of this registered domain, we now get uniqueness.
Again, we do it in reverse order,
so if we have a domain, Pluralsight.com,
we take our package and we name it
something starting with com.Pluralsight.
If everyone follows that convention,
we don't get naming collisions.
Now we can further qualify the package name
to be useful for whatever project we're working on.
So for things like flights,
maybe we'll put it into the travel package.
So our flight class is now in the package
com.Pluralsight.travel and the type name
now includes the package name.
Or we can say the package name is qualified
by the package name.
So if we go into code and we want
to go ahead and use a class flight,
there is no class named flight anymore.
What there is a class named
com.Pluralsight.travel.flight.
And that fully qualified name now
is unique throughout the world
because of the conventions we follow.
The classes name is fully qualified in all uses.
Whether we're declaring a variable like this
or if we're creating an instance of it.
With the package name being part of the type name,
that's really useful for avoiding naming collisions.
Fully qualifying all of our type names
like we have here, can be really cumbersome.
We need a way to get the benefits
of the package name being part of the type name
without having to fully qualify it each and every time.
That's what we'll take a look at in the next clip.