With packages serving as a name space for our types,
obviously the compiler needs to know each type's package.
Now, of course, we can explicitly qualify each type
with its package name but doing that,
just is impractical, it just makes our code hard to read
and honestly, it's a lot of typing.
Now Java offers several alternatives
to explicitly qualifying our types.
What this does is it allows us to use
the simple names of our types in our code.
Java handles a couple
of very common scenarios for us automatically.
One of those is that, whenever you're working in a package
any types that you refer to that are
part of that same package, don't need to be qualified.
Also, any types that we work with
that are part of the java.lang package
and that's the core package for the Java language.
Those don't need to be qualified
and that includes things like the Object class,
our primitive Wrapper classes,
the String class, StringBuilder,
lots and lots of others.
To see the full list of classes that are
in the java.lang package,
just check out that URL out on the screen there.
These two behaviors take care
of two kind of extremes.
That the current package is the thing
that's very personal to you
and the java.lang is the thing that's very general.
What about all the things in between?
Most applications are going to involve
a number of different packages.
That's where type imports come in.
Type imports provide a way for us
to tell the compiler how to map
simple type names to qualified names.
We do that using the import key word.
One thing I want to note is that,
the keyword, import, may give you
a sense of direction, loading something in
and that's not what import does.
Import is just a mapping for the compiler.
Basically there's a couple of different ways
we can do the import.
One way is what's called a single-type- import.
What a single-type-import does
is it allows you to provide an import statement
that maps in a single type.
Let's see what that looks like.
Let's say we're working in our code
and we're building up to classes
that we've been working on.
So we have our flight class
and we specify that being part of a package.
We've got our passenger class
and we specify that as being part of a package.
Now both of those classes are in our
com.Pluralsight.travel package.
Let's say if we're building up our application,
we want to also incorporate maybe
a third party package.
So if we think about it, if we're building
code around flights and passengers.
Something that flights commonly do
is provide beverage service.
Things like selling beer and wine.
We want to go ahead and use a third party package for those features.
We have a class like beer,
that's specified as a package from
some company called xyzcompany.
It's also got a class in it called wine.
It's part of that same package.
Our package com.xyzcompany.bar provides
those capabilities around providing beverage service.
If we go off and we start building our application
and we want to go ahead and create
an instant of our flight class.
We don't want to have to explicitly qualify the class name,
so in order to just say flight,
what we'll do is, at the top of our source code,
we'll have an import that says,
com.Pluralsight.travel.flight.
That tells the compiler that whenever
we use the class flight,
what we're really referring to
is the fully qualified class com.Pluralsight.travel.flight
or another way to say it is that,
we're referring to the flight class
as defined inside the package com.Pluralsight.travel.
If we want to use the beer class,
we'll do an import for that.
We'll say Import com.xyzcompany.bar.beer
which tells the compiler that whenever
we use the simple type name beer,
we're referring to the beer class
as defined in the package com.xyzcompany.bar.
Same sort of thing if we want to use passenger,
we provide an import that maps that in.
Or if we want to use the type wine,
We end up with an import statement here
for each of our individual types.
Now, an alternative to the single-type- import
is what's called Import on demand.
What Import on demand lets us do
is rather than providing a separate import
for each individual type,
it allows it to provide an import
for each package and it allows compiler
to map in all the types from within a package.
If we take a look at the code we have there.
If we look at the four import statements
we have here at the top,
we can actually replace those
and then instead of having a separate one
for each individual type,
we can have one for each of the packages.
We can have one that says, Import com.Pluralsight.travel.*
says to map in all the types from
the com.Pluralsight.travel package.
We can do the same thing with Import com.xyzcompany.bar.*
brings in all types from that package.
Then, during the compilation process,
when the compiler sees the simple name flight,
it looks inside those packages to find
a definition of a class called flight.
It will automatically resolve that
to com.Pluralsight.travel.flight.
Or for beer, it will resolve to com.xyzcompany.bar.beer.
That may sound like a really good way to go.
Why would I use single-type-imports?
Well let's look at a scenario.
Let's say that we're using these packages
and remember that com.xyzcompany.bar package
comes from a third party.
So we go and install a fresh version
of that package because maybe there's
a bug fix or something in there that we want.
Inside of that package,
maybe they've added another type.
Maybe they've added a type inside of there called flight.
Something that's becoming very common in recent years
is rather than buying a single large beer
is something called a beer flight.
Beer flight is this idea of three or four
small beers where each one's a different kind
so I can try out different things.
As this company wanted to stay current,
they introduced this class called flight
representing that concept.
The problem with this is that,
now if I go ahead and compile my application,
even though I haven't changed anything
in my application, I'm now going to get
an error on this line where I used flight.
Because the compiler's going to say
that well, both of those packages
have a flight class inside of there.
I don't know which one to use.
With no changes to my code,
I now have a bug.
But if we use a single-type-import instead
because we've explicitly said,
"When I use the class flight,
"I mean com.Pluralsight.travel.flight,
"I'm not exposed to this problem."
The single-type-import prevents me
from that kind of situation.
If we look at our options here,
our single-type-import is really
the preferred way to import types
because it's much safer.
Now you might be thinking that,
well I don't want to have to type in
all those imports all the time.
You don't have to worry about that.
Modern IDEs will add
your single type imports for you automatically.
Pretty much all of them do.
I know certainly, IntelliJ and NetBeans do.
Basically, when you're typing up your code,
when you use the single-type-name,
the ID automatically just adds the import
to the top for you.
Now, if you decide you want to use
Import on demand, remember that
you want to use that with caution
because as we've seen,
that exposes you code to potential breakage
from things outside of your code itself.