As we mentioned, a package is generally
a group of related types and those types
will provide some kind of related functionality.
But sometimes, all the capabilities
inside of a package may not meant to be used publicly.
So a package can serve as an access boundary.
A concept we've often referred to as
package private and what that's useful for
is you have this case where you're providing
some sort of public functionality
but sometimes, there's some kind of
internal work or internal housekeeping
that has to go on that you don't want
used outside the package.
So the idea is that you've got these
either types or features
that support the package but they're not
meant to be used stand alone.
You can do this, again, at the type level.
You may have entire classes that provide
functionality that's used by other classes
inside the package but not outside the package
or you might even have a public class
that has certain features about it
that are not meant to be used stand alone,
they're only meant to be used to cooperate
with other classes inside that package.
So thinking about this now.
We have four kinds of access modifiers
available to us in Java.
The one we just mentioned,
the idea of this package private.
Again, you do that by putting no access modifier
either on a type or a type member
which means it can only be used
by other types inside that package.
Of course, we also have public
which means that the type or member
can be used anywhere.
We also have private,
which means that it's a member
that can only be used within the type itself.
And then a concept of protected.
Protected says it can be used by the type itself
or other types that inherit from it.
As a protected member,
it can be used by any type inherited from the class
whether it's in the same package or not.
Package private is the only one
that really applies to package boundaries.
One thing to note, the ideas of private and protected
only being usable on types,
is limited to the concept of top level types.
If something called nested classes,
they can be marked as private or protected.
We're going to talk about nested classes
just a little bit later in this course.