In this demo, we'll take our CalcEngine application
and separate out the application part of it
from the classes we might want
to reuse in other applications.
The way our CalcEngine project is currently written,
the app part of it, our main entry point
is in the same package as all the classes we used
to do the work.
Now there's a high probability
that if we do a good job with these classes,
we might want to use these features in other applications.
So it probably makes sense to split
the application part of this out from
those other classes we might want to reuse.
So we're here in our main application.
Let's get it out of the com.Pluralsight.calcEngine package
and let's move it into one called
something like com.Pluralsight.myapp.
Remember that the way we change
the package from a Java standpoint
is simply change the package declaration.
If I change this CalcEngine to say my app.
From a Java standpoint changing
that package declaration is all we have to do.
But remember, as we talked about in Module two,
some of the IDEs actually require
that the source file structure,
to say the source folder structure
matches the structure of the package name.
For IntelliJ, we actually have to move
Main into a folder that corresponds
to our package structure.
Fortunately, IntelliJ will do that work for us.
Notice this little light bulb that's up here.
If I click on that, to say move to package
com.Pluralsight.myapp,
making that selection now causes it
to move that source file and reset up
all the folder structure we need.
NetBeans does that same thing.
If you look over here now,
the way it's laid out is we've got
under our source folder com.Pluralsight
and there's two sub folders.
One for CalcEngine and one for myapp,
myapp contains Main.
And again, that works very similarly
inside of NetBeans.
Now the problem now of course is that,
because the main source file is no longer
in the same package as our support code.
Things like calculate helper,
we now need to add import statements for those.
One of the nice things though is that
the IDE helps with that.
Like our Calculate Helper here.
Notice that it's saying that if I just do
ALT-enter, it will go ahead and add
that import for me.
You notice the import was added at the top.
Scroll up so you can see everything here.
So we still have our package declaration
but that import was added for us.
Again, NetBeans works very similar to that.
It will go ahead and add those imports for us.
If I scroll down here, things like
an invalid statement exception.
Again, I can just do ALT-Enter
and it will add the import for that as well.
If I scroll back up here,
I've got that as well.
If we scroll down here, again,
that's going to happen for all our classes
that are coming from our com.Pluralsight.CalcEngine package/
Math equation, scrolling down here,
things like calculate base, divider,
add or subtract or multiplier, all those.
What we want to do is make sure
we have imports for all those.
So we have to add space so we'll have
room for all those.
Now again, I could go through and have
IntelliJ add all those for us but I'll go through
and just add them here quickly.
Now we have all the import statements
that we need here.
One thing to note here is that right now
we have about eight imports all coming from
com.Pluralsight.CalcEngine.
As we mentioned, it's good to use
the single-type-imports because
it protects us from any changes
in an outside package.
One thing I want to point out about
a behavior in IntelliJ.
I don't want to spend a lot of time on the IDE
but this is something that's important to note.
IntelliJ does something with the imports.
By default, if you have five or more imports
from the same package,
it actually switches over to Import on demand.
It just replaces all these individual imports
with one import with a star on it.
That's a dangerous behavior.
Let me just show you quickly how
to fix that inside of IntelliJ.
If we go up to our File menu
and we choose Settings.
Here under Settings, you want to go
to the Editor section, the Java section under that,
or I should say Java subsection.
There's an imports tab.
You want to set this entry here
where it says Class count use import with *.
Normally that's five by default.
You want to move it to a high value
like 100 or 1,000 to prevent it
from actually switching over to Import on demand.
NetBeans does not have that issue,
that's an IntelliJ thing.
Now, we have all our reusable classes
in the CalcEngine package with Main
off in its own package for the application.
Now something to think about here.
Let's go to our Calculator Helper class.
Remember, our Calculator Helper class
has a field inside of it called Command
that uses the type math command.
Remember, math command is an enumeration
that we're using inside of Calculator Helper
so that once we determine the string
representation of the operation,
we can use the enumeration the rest of our code.
Now that's meant for our own internal usage.
We don't want other people using it.
We don't want that to be public.
What we'll do is go into our Math Command
source file here and we'll just take away
the public on it.
Alright, so now it has become package private.
It can only be used in our packet.
It's important to do that with things like
Math Command here that we're using internally.
Because it may seem at first okay,
to say, "We'll just go ahead and leave it public."
"If people use it, who cares?"
Well, if other code that you don't control
starts using this enumeration
and then you need to make a change
to it for some reason,
you now risk breaking their code.
So any types that we create that were meant
only for use in our package,
it's important to not declare them public.
To make them package private.
What happens is that now that that's package private,
if I go into Main which is in a different package
but if I try to use Math command,
it won't actually let me.
If I just type Math command,
notice that Math commands not even
coming up in our options?
I'll go ahead and type if all the way out.
Notice that it still just says that that's an error.
I don't know what that is.
I can't resolve the symbol.
Even if I try to forcibly put
the package name in front of it.
You notice now, I end up with
an error saying it can't be accessed outside the package.
So that protects it from being used outside the package.
Now with Main being off in its own package
in myapp, everything should still work fine
because I have all the necessary imports in there.
If I run this, you notice that we ended up getting
an error here and you see this thing
Class not found exception.
It's our main entry point.
The problem here is not a Java problem,
it's an IDE problem.
Again, I don't want to spend a lot of time
on IDE details but one thing to be aware of
is that if you change the class it's associated
with your application entry points
and the IDE, you want to make sure
that the IDE knows about it.
So to tell IntelliJ that we've changed
the startup path, we're going to go to Run,
Edit Configurations and notice
that the main class here is still
pointing to the one in CalcEngine.
I could just go here and change this to myapp
or I could click the button here
and just choose it.
Notice it says, well here's a class called Main
in the com.Pluralsight.myapp package
that will actually satisfy the requirements
of a startup path.
So we'll go ahead and choose that.
Now we'll say OK.
Now we run our application.
Everything works just as it should.