When we create software whether it's
for an entire application or just some classes
we wanted to give to other developers to use,
at some point, we want to distribute that software.
By working with packages,
our software gets built into a predictable structure
and that predictable structure
simplifies this idea of distribution.
Our class files get organized in
hierarchical folders that reflect
the name of our package.
Basically, each part of the package name
gets a separate folder.
If we look at something like our flight class
that we've got in the package
com.Pluralsight.travel.
When we build this, we'll get a folder COM
with a sub folder Pluralsight,
with a sub folder travel and then
we have our flight.class file that goes
into that travel folder.
That flight.class file is the compiled version
of our class, it's the (mumbles) codes for our flight class.
Now if we have another class like passenger,
it's in that same package.
It will be in the COM folder with
a sub folder Pluralsight,
sub folder travel and then we get
our passenger.class file in there
with a compiled version of that class.
So while the classes that are in that package
will be organized under the same folder structure.
I can actually distribute this software
by taking that COM folder and its contents
and just copying it to another computer
and it will have the software.
Now as nice as it is working with
a simple folder structure like that,
there might be a better choice than that.
That's where archive files come in.
Archive files allow us to put that folder structure
into a file and these are commonly known as JAR files.
What it does is it takes that entire hierarchy
of the folders and can put it into a single file.
That file can even optionally be compressed.
We now get the convenience of moving
from an entire folder of files
into a single file and that file can be efficiently stored.
In addition, the archive file can optionally include
a manifest and that manifest provides
information about what's going on inside that archive.
Basically it's just a bunch of name value pairs
and I've got the URL on screen.
I'm showing you the documentation for the manifest.
One of the things we commonly use
the manifest for is identifying
the startup class that's contained
in an archive file making it easy for us
to run a program that's inside
of an archive file.
Now it's easy to create archive files.
The JDK actually provides a utility for doing so
called the JAR utility.
It's a command line utility and it's easy enough to use.
We have other options as well.
Many other tools actually include
the ability to create JAR files.
A number of the Integrated Development Environments
are what we commonly know as IDEs have that ability.
In fact, both the ones we talk about
in this course do.
IntelliJ does as well as NetBeans
as well as many others have that
built right into it, so it's part
of our build process we can generate a JAR file.
Also, many of the build automation systems
are what are commonly known
as Build Managers have that ability.
Those include things like Gradle
as well as Maven and many others.
So that we have that command line utility
for creating JAR files,
very often we never have to use that.
We can actually produce the JAR files
as part of other build processes that we do.
So in our next clip, let's take a look
at using packages for distribution
and working with those packages in archive files.