In this demo, we'll take a look at
how we can package up our applications
as a JAR file for distribution.
Here we have our application opened up in an IDE, in this case it's IntelliJ
and the application's in the exact state
it was when we finished up the last demo.
Now as we know of course,
we could run this right inside of the IDE.
We've done that a bunch of times.
We want to look at now how we can
distribute it around so people
without the IDE can run it.
We touched on this briefly back in Module two.
We're going to look at things a lot more closely now.
If I switch over to the folder where
this is built out at.
Here I am in the folder that contains
the demos for this module.
Working on the CalcEngine demo right now.
Let's just go inside there.
What we want to look at is the Out folder.
Again, this Out folder is something that IntelliJ uses,
other systems use different folder structures.
We go in here into a production folder and CalcEngine.
This is the output from CalcEngine.
And you see the only thing we see here
is a COM folder.
Remember that we said that building
the Java applications creates a folder structure
that corresponds to the package names.
So I say COM, Pluralsight and when
I get inside of there, there's two folders
because I have two packages that
fall under COM.Pluralsight.
CalcEngine and myapp.
And from a nomenclature standpoint,
CalcEngine is considered to be
a sub package of COM.Pluralsight.
There's no special relationship there
other than how they're stored.
But it's just a terminology that's used.
The same way myapp is a sub package of COM.Pluralsight.
If I go into my app, we see the class file for Main,
this is a complied version of Main.
We go back to the Pluralsight,
go into CalcEngine, see all the class files there
for all the compiled versions
of the classes we have in that package.
If I want to jump back up here to COM
and then I'll go up one more level where CalcEngine is.
This is the root of my package.
I should be able to run the program from here.
If I want to, I can go in here
and I can open up a command prompt.
Here we're on the command prompt.
If I want to run the program,
I just type Java and then the class
that's my entry point which is
COM.Pluralsight.myapp.main.
Now just go ahead and hit Enter
and of course, the application runs.
So that proves that if we were to actually
take this COM folder and its contents
and copy it over to another machine
as long as that machine had Java installed on it.
We could run it on that machine just like this.
As we talked about, JAR files are
a much more convenient way to distribute our applications.
Let's take a look at how we can
actually create that JAR file using the IDEs.
First doing it with IntelliJ
and then I'll show you, as well,
how to do it in NetBeans.
Again, of course, you could also use
the actual JAR utility.
I've got the URL on the screen
for the documentation for the JAR utility.
We're going to focus on the IDEs for right now.
We go back here into IntelliJ.
Now IntelliJ is kind of interesting.
It uses an unusual way or at least
a nonstandard way of how you specify
you want to create a JAR file.
Other environments tend to do it
more directly as part of the build process.
IntelliJ actually has the generation
of the JARs as something separate.
The way we set up the JAR file in IntelliJ
is we go to the File menu,
go to one here called Project Structure.
You notice here under Project Settings
here on the left, there's one option here
called Artifacts and Artifacts are other things
you can produce from the project.
A JAR file is considered an artifact in IntelliJ.
So what we do is we go up to this plus sign up here, we choose that.
It says, "What kind of artifact do you want?"
Well I want a JAR artifact and I want
to generate a JAR file from the modules
that are in this project.
So I'm going to choose that.
Notice one of the options here
when this dialogue pops up is Main class.
So it says, "Well, do you want me
"to actually put a Main class as
"the entry point in this?"
And we do want to do that.
I'm just going to choose the dot, dot, dot here.
I'm going to choose my COM.Pluralsight.myapp.Main.
So say, OK.
Now what this does once I choose that option
is it actually will generate the manifest
for this JAR file specifying that
that's the main entry point.
We'll see why that's useful in a minute.
Go ahead and say OK.
That's all set up now, so we'll say OK again.
Now if I was to go off and just build
my project right now,
I still wouldn't have a JAR file.
In order to get the JAR file,
what I have to do is
go to the Build menu, choose Build Artifacts.
It says, "What do you want me to do?"
So it's CalcEngine JAR, I want to build it.
That now goes off and builds that JAR file.
What I want to do is let's go back
to the file system now.
Here we are in the file system
and you'll notice that before we just had
that COM folder here.
Notice now that there's a meta.INF folder.
That's actually going to contain our manifest.
If I go inside of here,
it says manifest.mf, that's our manifest file.
If I double click on this,
you notice that it has an entry here
Main class, COM.Pluralsight.myapp.Main.
That actually gets included in the JAR file
so we're able to just basically execute
the JAR file and Java will know what class
we want to run.
Let's go ahead and close this guy out.
I'm going to jump back up here to my Out folder and you notice here
there's an Artifacts folder.
I go inside of there, notice there's a folder
called CalcEngine_JAR.
So that's our JAR file.
Let's go ahead and open a command prompt
in this location now.
Here we are in the folder containing the JAR file.
What's nice about this is since
the JAR file actually specifies
what the main entry point is,
I can effectively just run the JAR file
and just say Java, I'm going to use an option
JAR and then I'm going to put in the name of the JAR file.
Basically that tells Java to run this JAR file.
Because the JAR includes a manifest
that says what the main entry point is,
Java can figure out what class to run.
If I go ahead and run this now,
our application runs correctly.
So you see, that's where if I have the JAR files
come in as that, not only do we have
this nice packaging of the whole application
in a single file but even the file
includes the information necessary
to run its contents and there's other
information that can be included in there as well.
Let's go back to our file system for a second.
Remember I mentioned that JAR files
follow the standard ZIP file format.
We can actually explore inside of a JAR file pretty easily.
Just note, there are utilities that will
actually let you generate the source code
tied to the contents of the JAR file.
That's what I'm looking at here.
I just want to show you what the structure
of the inside of the JAR file looks like.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm going to take this file
and I'm just going to copy it.
I'm going to paste it back in.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to change its name.
I'm going to change its name to CalcEngine.zip.
The reason I changed its name
is because I'm on a Window system right now
and on Windows, once it sees that that's
a zip file extension, it will actually allow me
to explore it as a zip file.
We'll go ahead and hit enter.
Windows just prompts me to make sure
I really do want to change the file name
and I'll say yes.
Now when I double click on this CalcEngine.zip
I can now explore its contents.
You notice that it's looking very much
like the folder we were looking at earlier.
We see our COM folder, Pluralsight
and then these are the packet sub folders
containing the class files.
So we can see the JAR file really is
just a zip file with the addition of that manifest.
As I mentioned earlier,
IntelliJ uses a very different process
for generating the JAR files than
most other environments do.
I'd like to show you here just quickly
inside of NetBeans how you set NetBeans
to generate a JAR file.
What I have open here is this Hello NetBeans project
we created earlier in the course.
What this is really straightforward.
I'm going to go over here to
the Project Structure, right-click, choose properties.
You notice there's an options here
our sections say on packaging.
We're just going to choose packaging
and basically we'll go ahead
and create the JAR file, compress the JAR file
and we'll say OK.
The simple fact of doing that,
now when we build a project,
NetBeans will now generate the JAR file.
So the JAR file will just be part of the build process.
Unlike IntelliJ where generating the JAR file was a separate process,
here in NetBeans it will just be part of the overall build process.