To wrap up, remember that basically
a package is a group of related types.
We put types into a package
by just simply putting a package declaration
inside of their source file.
But remember that that package declaration
must occur before any type declarations do
and although a package is a group related types
that grouping of being a package
provides a number of capabilities
or a number of features.
First of all, packages act as a name space
because types are qualified by their package name.
That avoids naming collisions because
it gives us fully qualified names
but typing those fully qualified names
all the time is cumbersome.
So we use the import statement
to match names to qualified names.
Packages serve as an access boundary.
So we can have types and members
that are visible inside of the package
but not outside of the package
so they can provide support for
the capabilities of that package
without being directly usable on their own.
Packages serve as simplified distribution.
Remember that types inside of a package
are organized hierarchically which is nice
but to go one step further than that,
simple organization that we have
archive files organize JAR files
which allow us to take that package hierarchy
and put it into a single file.
Remember that archive files can also
have a manifest which then provides
descriptive information about what's going on
inside that archive file.